<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: freelancing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/freelancing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-17T15:46:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Ways To Build A $200,000 Consultancy]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/5waysto_key.png" width="260"></p>

<p>I recently read an article entitled <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">5 ways to build a $100 million dollar business</a>. It discusses different business models that vary on the number and size of your customer base. Some businesses work with a few enterprise scale clients, while others work with a larger number of smaller customers. Patrick Mackenzie mentioned on Twitter that <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/521878305151000577">"The math here is equally applicable if you are trying to build, say, a $200k a year business"</a>.A $200k/yr consultancy is a goal that seems both attractive and attainable, so I decided try and answer the question "How can you build a $200,000 consultancy?"</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Find 1 Client That Pays You $200,000 (The Elephant)</h3>

<p>I've been a part of projects where a single engagement has had a price tag of $200,000 or more. I think this scenario is a little unlikely. If you can find one of these clients, then you can find more, and you are on your way to becoming a $1mm+ consultancy. It would also be very risky for a company to put all of it's eggs in one basket like this.</p>

<h3>Find 10 Clients That Pay You $20,000 (The Deer)</h3>

<p>There are a few examples of consultancies that make this kind of money. One is custom application development services that can handle ten projects in a year. Most of the client work I find is in this range. Another example is high end consulting engagements. People like <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/">Patrick Mackenzie</a> and <a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com/">Brennan Dunn</a> charge anywhere from $10,000 - $30,000 for a week of their services. They could work 10 engagements a year and hit this $200,000 benchmark.</p>

<h3>Find 100 Clients That Pay You $2,000 (The Rabbits)</h3>

<p>With this setup, your consultancy would have to have a service that scales very well. One way to accomplish this would be to find a way to service multiple clients at one time. Hosting courses or seminars is a way you could accomplish this. For example, Big Nerd Ranch offers <a href="https://training.bignerdranch.com/classes/advanced-ios-bootcamp">programming courses that cost $4,200</a>. At this point, the focus of the work changes. This is less of a consulting model and more of an information product model. There are plenty of gigs out there that pay $2,000 for smaller jobs, which are fine but those are hard to scale.</p>

<h3>Find 1,000 Customers That Pay You $200 (The Mice)</h3>

<p>At this level, you need a product that you can resell. It could be a course that requires little to no interaction for $200 (For example, a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/comprehensive-ruby-on-rails/?dtcode=Q73iZAp1GbIa">UDemy</a> course), or it could be some form of subscription product, which would cost just shy of $20/month. For software developers, you may be able to build a premium software framework or plugin that can sell for this amount. The <a href="http://www.magentocommerce.com/magento-connect/">Magento Connect marketplace</a> is a good example of people going this model. I can't think of any kind of repeatable service model that works at this scale.</p>

<h3>Find 10,000 Customers That Pay You $20 (The Files)</h3>

<p>You are a product business at this point. You could sell ebooks, themes, plugins, or something of that nature. You really can't call it a consultancy at this point. For this kind of business, it looks like the math doesn't scale don't quite so well at this point.</p>

<h3>Applying This To Your Business</h3>

<p>Do you want to work on $2,000 or $200,000 projects? Before you say "$200,000, duh." Think about the pros and cons of fewer clients vs. more, and smaller clients vs. large. Fewer larger clients means a more rigorous, in-depth sales process, and a higher risk if you lose a client.</p>

<p>What kind of consultancy do you want to run, and how are you going to scale it? You can scale not only by getting more clients, but by getting bigger ones as well. If you think about the kind of business you <strong>want</strong> to be running, then you can start making deliberate steps to get there.</p>

<p><small>Image by <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">Christoph Janz</a></small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talking Productized Consulting with Nick Disabato[Video]]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T04:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Origin Story of Draft Revise</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/nickd.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>In this interview I am talking with Nick Disabato, Owner of <a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft</a>, Author of <a href="http://cadence.cc/">Cadence &amp; Slang</a>,, and <a href="https://draft.nu/revise/">Draft Revise</a>, a recurring split testing service that Nick offers to clients. In this interview, Nick talks about creating a new service offering from scratch, How he got his first customers, and how Draft Revise has changed his business.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>




<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Lib91re3onM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Show Notes</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft, a small interaction design consultancy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/nickd">Nick Disabato on Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nickd.org">Nickd.org</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start A Consultancy In 16 Hours From Kai Davis]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T07:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>An Actionable Plan From The Side Hustle Nation</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/kai-davis.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>My friend <a href="http://kaidavis.com/">Kai Davis</a> was recently on the side hustle nation podcast. The episode is <a href="http://www.sidehustlenation.com/start-side-hustle-consulting-business-gets-paid/">How to Start a Side Hustle Consulting Business that Gets Paid</a>. One particular nugget of gold from this podcast: When asked what he would do if he had to start all over, Kai responds with how he would start a new consultancy in 16 hours.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Hours 1-3: Identify A Target Audience</h3>

<p>Decide which market you want to focus on. This could be segmented geographically, or by industry type. If you aren't sure where to begin, try looking at local business directories. Your local chamber of commerce is a good place to start. You could even look in a phone book if you manage to find one.</p>

<h3>Hours 4 - 8: Book Four Calls (But Not Sales Calls)</h3>

<p>Start reaching out to people who you think might be potential clients. Ask them to sit down with you over lunch or coffee, or just hop on the phone with you to discuss their business. People love talking about themselves, and even strangers will be more receptive to this than you would believe. Your goal here isn't to sell them anything, this meeting is research. You want to find the <em>pain points</em> that your potential clients have.</p>

<h3>Hours 9 - 12: Begin Crafting A Service</h3>

<p>Now that you know what problems people in your target audience are having, how can you solve them? Look for ways you can apply your current skills and knowledge to these problems, or how to apply new skills that you could pick up in a reasonable amount of time. If you don't find a good fit, that's OK, you may just have to try again. You don't marry the first person you date, and you don't want to pursue the first job idea that comes to mind.</p>

<h3>Hours 13 - 16: Offer Your Solution</h3>

<p>Now you have connections to your market, and understanding of their problems, and a solution to those problems. Go back to your original contacts and offer your solution. Now you're in business!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Multiple Packages In Your Proposals Instantly Increase Conversions]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-15T09:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The 3 Tiered Approach That Closes More Sales</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/baseball.png" width="260"></p>

<p>When a freelancer submits a proposal, they will often only include one offer. They will set the deliverable, and the price, and throw their proposal over the wall. When you do this, you give the client a binary option: Hire you or don't.</p>

<p>By giving the client a few different options, you are changing the conversation into one that is more likely to end with the client hiring you.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Selling Services is More like Selling Products Than You Might Think</h3>

<p>Many of the selling principles that I mention in this article are going to be identical to the once I addressed in <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid/">Breakdown of a Pricing Grid</a>. There is more common ground in selling products and selling service than most people realize. When you submit a proposal, you are selling a product to a very specific customer, and you are only selling it once.</p>

<h3>Offers And Solutions</h3>

<p>All proposals that you write follow a simple narrative. "How are you going to get the client from point A to point B?". Point A is why they starting talking to you in the first place. This is a pain point they are having, or a moment they decided that they needed to change something in their business. A <strong>solution</strong> is "point B". The solution is tomorrow. The solution is the inverse of the problem. The <strong>offer</strong> is how you are proposing to get the client from point A to point B. There are multiple ways you can get a client from point A to point B, and these are going to be the basis of the packages you offer.</p>

<h3>The 3 Packages You Should Include In Your Proposal</h3>

<p>Let's say you are at bat in a baseball game. The problem is that you are not on base. The solution is that you want to get on base. There are several ways you can get there. The following is the 3 package template I use in my proposals: The bunt, The line drive, and the home run (now the image at the top of this post makes sense!). Approaching the proposal this way gets me thinking about multiple ways I can solve a client's problem, and helps me and my clients find the offer that fits their needs and wants the best.</p>

<h3>The Bunt</h3>

<p>The lowest package you should offer should be the absolute minimum you can do to get the client to where they want to be. I also call this the <strong>half-complete package</strong>. Based on previous communications with the client, this offer is usually <strong>less</strong> than what they originally asked for. This package is useful because customers that may not have taken your core offering may take you up on this one, turning non-clients into small clients.</p>

<h3>The Line Drive</h3>

<p>This package will be the most in line with what the client requested. In the middle package, I include everything that the client has asked for or that I no are 100% crucial to a successful project. I call this one the <strong>complete package</strong>.</p>

<h3>The Home Run</h3>

<p>Once I have a handle on what the client is looking for, I ask myself "How can I go above and beyond what they asked for?". There is where I come up with the final, most expensive package. I call this one the <strong>complete plus package</strong>. This package is a place where I can up-sell the client, and show my expertise.</p>

<h3>Multiple Packages Give You Built In Up-sells</h3>

<p>The complete plus package is a straight-up up-sell. You took the clients needs and offered to meet their expectations and then some. No matter which package your client buys, you will still have a chance to up-sell them. If they purchase the smallest package, you can always go back and offer to complete more work for them. You have already presenting the client with several offerings, and these can be valuable tools later on in the client relationship.</p>

<h3>Change The Conversation</h3>

<p>The biggest advantage to this approach is that instead of the client thinking "Do I accept this proposal or not?", They now have options. They think "Which option on this proposal do I choose?".</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Freelancing Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/04/my-freelancing-stack/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T16:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/04/my-freelancing-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>10 Tools I Use to Manage and Automate My Business</h3>

<p>In web development, the group of software, frameworks, and tools is called our "stack". In businesses, you have a similar "stack", which is made up of the tools and systems that you use to run your business. Today I wanted to list out my personal stack that I use.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Sales and Lead Management: PipeDrive</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.pipedrive.com/en/features/lead-tracking-software">Pipedrive</a> has the best visualization of the sales pipeline I have seen, and it can be completely customized. But the most valuable feature is that every time you finish a task that is related to a deal, it will automatically prompt you to create another. This way you never forget to follow up with a potential client, and deals don't fall through the cracks. This is great way to keep track of your leads.</p>

<h2>Contracts: Docracy</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.docracy.com">Docracy</a> is a free resource for open source contract templates. It also has e-signatures, so you can use it to get contracts signed with remote clients. Here a couple of templates that I either use, or have my own modified version of:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.docracy.com/649dkpe7g9/contract-killer-3">General Work Contract</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.docracy.com/0i2fahvpv5t/statement-of-work-digital-advertising-services">Statement of Work</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.docracy.com/27/generic-shortform-nda">Generic Short Form NDA</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Invoicing: FreshBooks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.freshbooks.com">Freshbooks</a> is one of the largest invoicing tools out there. It makes generating invoices simple. Freshbooks is great if you bill by the hour, however since I moving away from that billing structure I have found Freshbooks to be a bit lacking. It doesn't really have support for daily and weekly billing. But it does have simple time tracking, expense tracking, online payments, and really good reporting. I do appreciate that when tax time rolls around, I can print out a couple reports, hand them to my CPA, and boom. Done.</p>

<h2>Customer Support: ZenDesk</h2>

<p>When I was looking for a customer support tool, my one requirement was that it had to work 100% via email for clients. Clients are busy and don't want to have to learn a new tool just because they found a bug. <a href="http://zendesk.com">Zendesk</a> met this requirement. My clients can send all inquiries to a support email address, and I can keep track of conversations and tickets via the application. When working with clients on monthly retainers, this is a great tool to keep things organized.</p>

<h2>Scheduling: Calendly + Google Calendar</h2>

<p>I hate having to go back and forth via email to schedule an appointment with someone. With <a href="http://www.calendly.com">Calendly</a>, I can send people a calendar of my availability, and they can select the time that works best for them. The real "killer feature" for me is the Google calendar integration: Not only does it add events to my calendar, it will automatically remove my availability if I schedule something else in that time slot, even if it wasn't through Calendly.</p>

<h2>Writing Articles: Draft</h2>

<p><a href="https://draftin.com/">Draft</a> is a new tool I've started using recently. I love the clean interface and how easy it is to share drafts with people. I've been using to send some beta versions of chapters for my book project <em>Professional Freelance</em>. It also has a 'Hemingway mode', which disables the backspace and delete buttons for you. This makes the writing experience similar to writing on a typewriter, which is helpful when writing first drafts, and keeps you out of slipping into editing mode.</p>

<h2>Writing Books &amp; Courses: Scrivener</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php">Scrivener</a> is like Photoshop for words. It allows you to break your writing project in nested sections, and move them around freely. This way, moving chapters and sections around are easy. When I first began to attempt to write a book, I figured I would write an outline, and then fill it out. As the project went on, I've completely rearranged the books three times. Sometimes entire chapters are deleted, and whole new ones are added. Scrivener makes this process a breeze.</p>

<h2>Publishing: OctoPress + WordPress + Medium</h2>

<p>I have a few different tools that I use to publish content online:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> Octopress is the site you are reading right now. It's a static site generator. That means that instead of having software like WordPress installed on a server, I generate the pages on my local machine, and put the result online. This way, there are no load times, and no worry of hacking because there is nothing to hack.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://wordpress.org/">WordPress</a> WordPress is the granddaddy of online publishing, and I use it for my company site <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. WordPress can be a bit unwieldy at times, but it does make publishing simple, and it's impossible to beat the ecosystem around it. All of the plugins and themes available make it easy to get something set up quickly.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://medium.com">Medium</a> is a very slick looking online publishing platform. It was created by Ev Williams, one of the founders of Twitter. Medium is focused on longer form content and providing the best reading and writing experience for its users. The benefit of Medium is that it helps you reach out to new audiences. When I'm not writing here, I'm writing there. In fact, I am considering moving more of my writing over to Medium in the future.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Email Marketing: ConvertKit</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a> is responsible for all those little calls to action at the bottom of each post. ConvertKit has a different approach from other mailing list providers. Instead of just putting everyone onto one list, you create different forms. These forms usually come with an incentive, such as a download or a course. Then, you can segment users based on which form they signed up for. This allows you to send more targeted emails.</p>

<p>In addition to forms that you can embed, ConvertKit also allows you to build landing pages which can then be embedded on your site. I also like the simple look of the emails. I hate the idea of "newsletters". I view my list as communication at scale. ConvertKit is just an easy way to email a few hundred people and start some conversations. All the emails come from my email address so that you can hit "reply" to get in touch with me. And I always write back. If you want to see what one of their landing pages looks like and/or sign up for my list, <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/letters">Here is the link</a></p>

<p>Do you have any tools that make your life as a freelancer easier? If so, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">Drop me a line</a> and let me know!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
