<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: freelancing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/freelancing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-16T19:43:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 Postmortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/28/2014-postmortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-28T14:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/28/2014-postmortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every Year I take a look back at my business, and do the same exercise I do with every client project: a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmortem_documentation#Elements_of_a_project_post-mortem">postmortem</a>. I ask myself 3 questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>What went well?</li>
<li>What went wrong?</li>
<li>What steps should I take in the future?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is a valuable writing exercise, and I’d strongly encourage you to do the same. This is my postmortem of 2014, as well as a review of how I did on my goals I set for myself at the beginning of the year.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Did I Hit My 2013 Goals?</h2>

<p>I was listening to <a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/episodes/episode-214-our-goals-for-2015">Episode 214 of Startups For The Rest Of Us</a>, where the hosts Rob Walling and Mike Taber look back at their goals they set for the year, and give themselves between 0 and 1 points based on wether or not they felt they achieved that goal. Before I get into my postmortem, I wanted to go through the exact same exercise.</p>

<h3>Goal: Generate a Stream of Product Based Income</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 0 points</h4>

<p>It seems like every year I have a vague goal of launching a product, and I tend not to do it. While I did launch a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/offerings/overnight-site/">Productized Service</a>, I didn’t create any kind of profitable project this year.</p>

<h3>Goal: Better Time Management</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 0.5 points</h4>

<p>I’ll give myself half a point here. While I made some improvements in managing my time, I still feel like there is a lot of room for improvement. Some good steps forward I have made has been more diligent about scheduling my time, and eliminating tasks that kept me busy, but weren’t productive.</p>

<h3>Goal: Keeping an Eye on Business Metrics</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>This was mostly in regards to sales and marketing. I started using <a href="http://bit.ly/1itwiuw">PipeDrive</a> to both systemize and keep track of the numbers on my sales funnel. PipeDrive also allows you to add custom fields to your leads, so I have started tracking 4 data points on each lead that I come into contact with:</p>

<ul>
<li>Size of the company</li>
<li>Company vertical</li>
<li>Project type</li>
<li>Source of lead</li>
</ul>


<p>This way I don’t only see how many leads I am getting, but I can drill down on which leads are the most profitable, which convert the best, and what are the best sources of leads that convert.</p>

<h3>Goal: A More Defined Sales and Marketing Process</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>See PipeDrive above. Now I have a defined sales process, email templates that I use for communicating to leads and prospects at various points in the conversation. This has allowed me to spend less time selling and more time creating value. I also feel that I have a strong framework for writing proposals.</p>

<p>Since I’ve implemented these practices, the number of leads I get have increased, and my conversion rate as more than doubled.</p>

<h3>Goal: Have a Better Pricing Structure</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>In addition to raising my rates last year, I have eliminated work billed by the hour with the exception of some legacy clients. I finally implemented this towards the end of the year, and so far the results have been tremendous. I feel happier working not having to punch a time clock, client relationships are better, and I feel I am providing more valuable work.</p>

<p>I did experiment with daily and weekly billing, and that for the most part was a bust in my experience. Some people swear by weekly billing, however I found that many prospects didn’t “get” it, and it was just causing more friction in the sales process.</p>

<h3>Total Score: 3.5 / 5</h3>

<h2>What Went Well in 2014</h2>

<h3>Putting Myself on a Salary to Eliminate Feast and Famine</h3>

<p>In 2013, I would divide up the bounty of each paid invoice into a few different buckets: a percentage for the company coffers, a percentage for Uncle Sam, and a percentage in my pocket. Now, I pay myself a monthly stipend regardless of income. This makes personal budgeting and financial planning easier, reduces stress during the lean months. This also means that I have more cash on hand in my company account that I can invest back into the business.</p>

<h3>Diligent Practice of Inbox Zero &amp; GTD</h3>

<p>Email used to be one of those tasks that was a large time sink for me. Then I started practicing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z9UjeTMb3Yk">inbox zero</a>.  Now I check email twice a day, and each time I am able to get though my inbox quickly. <a href="http://www.mailboxapp.com/">Mailbox</a> is a great app if you’d like to start practicing it.</p>

<p>On that same note, I started implementing the principles of <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/">Getting Things Done</a>, which is essentially the principles of inbox zero applied to your to do list. I now have one task management system, and everything I need to do goes into an inbox. The inbox is processed daily, and then tasks are knocked off. Since doing this I’ve had almost nothing fall through the cracks, and I feel less stressed and more on top of things. I use the Mac/iOS app <a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/">Things</a> to manage my to do lists.</p>

<h3>An Online Presence I’m Happy About</h3>

<p>I’ve gone through multiple redesigns of this site, and my company site, Concordant Solutions. I finally <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">decided to only manage one site</a>, and give it a facelift. It’s an ongoing process, but right now I feel like my site is the best it has ever been.</p>

<h3>Writing and Publishing More Content</h3>

<p>I invested a lot more in writing content this year. I’ve had some articles gain some traction, including making the Medium.com top 100 one month. I also published a free eBook that has been downloaded over 1,000 times. Both of them have helped me reach more people, and have started many a great conversation. Here are my most popular posts in 2014:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@gsto/how-i-used-writing-to-double-my-freelancing-rate-as-a-programmer-7b321bedecdc">How I Used Writing to Double my Rate as a Freelancer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">The Freelance Pricing Handbook</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/">5 Ways to Build a $200,000 Consultancy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">Why Multiple Packages in Your Proposals Instantly Increase Conversions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/20140917184430-36107098-how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-opened-and-convert?trk=prof-post">How to Write More Personal Emails to Your List That Get Opened And Convert</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Building an Audience</h3>

<p>While I had good intentions as far as releasing products went, I wanted to start building an audience of people beforehand. While the product idea never came to fruition, I’m glad that I started this. I have had some <em>fantastic</em> conversations, Got invites to be a speaker on a webinar, and get to keep in touch and build relationships with people at scale.</p>

<p>Building an audience also gives everything else I do more purpose. Now writing articles isn’t just about sharing content, it’s an entryway to building relationships.</p>

<h3>Joining a Mastermind</h3>

<p>Being self employed is lonely work. If there is one thing I miss from the employed world (in fact, I think this is the <strong>only</strong> thing), It is having people to relate to what you are doing, and  being able to reach out for help.</p>

<p>This year I joined a mastermind with three other freelancers. Each week we hop on a Google Hangout, and discuss what is going on in our business. It gives each of a chance to get a few extra pairs of eyes on anything we’re working on, and a forum to even about frustrations we wouldn’t otherwise. I’ve learned just as much, if not more from the conversations I’ve had in these mastermind meetings than I have all the books and podcasts I’ve consumed this year.</p>

<h2>What Went Wrong in 2014</h2>

<h3>A Sabbatical That Went Unintentionally Long</h3>

<p>After a couple of large projects and heavy workload, I became burned out towards the middle of the year. I had some money in the bank, and decided to schedule some time off to rest and invest some time in my business. This turned out to be the worst decision I made all year.</p>

<p>Firstly, trying to take time off and invest in my business was a poor plan. It really should have been one or the other. Secondly, It just enough small jobs rolled in that I didn’t really get to relax or make very money, leaving me dealing with the worst of both worlds. Finally, it’s hard to build up momentum after stopping. What was going to be a break of a few weeks ended up being more like a break of a few <em>months</em>, which really put pressure on both my cash flow and sanity.</p>

<p>On the bright side, this was also the moment that led me to do a lot of introspection and make some decisions about what my business was going to look like in the future.</p>

<h3>A Company Brand That Was Dead In The Water</h3>

<p>Last year I formed an LLC and formed a company site called “Concordant Solutions”. Both the site and the brand was a failure in every metric I can think to measure it in. Managing two sites was more time consuming than managing one. Any content I wrote for my company site tended to fall flat, and did not generate leads of any sort. Explaining to people in person that I was “company” that was just one person, and what the hell “Concordant” means became exhausting and distracting.</p>

<p>For now, I’m back to being plain old me. The name Concordant Solutions now only exists in the world of contracts and invoices.</p>

<h3>The 30 Day Publishing Challenge</h3>

<p>In September, I decided to join Colin Devroe in taking a <a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/9527/blogging-every-weekday-for-30-days">challenge to publish something every weekday for 30 days.</a> While I did finish the challenge, (and wrote a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem/">postmortem</a> about that too), I don’t think it was that valuable of an exercise. It led me to publishing a lot of content that wasn’t all that good, and took up a lot of my time.</p>

<p>I think that if you were tempted to do something similar, writing every 30 days would be a much better goal.</p>

<h3>I Didn’t Launch a Product</h3>

<p>This is something that has been on my goal list for a few years, and one I haven’t been able to capitalize on. I started work on a few, but I was usually stopped by the fear that I was launching a product for product’s sake, and not because I was unsure that It would be valuable. This is a fear I need to get over, so I can at least try to launch something to generate a more passive revenue stream.</p>

<h3>Problems With Client Communication and Expectations</h3>

<p>I had some client relationships this year that didn’t go as well as either one of us would have liked.I did a poor job of managing the client relationship and their expectations. Since these experiences I’ve worked hard at streamlining my communication and pricing structure to support a better relationship.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, the relationship between a consultant and their client should be a partnership. However, I think we all do things that tend to frame it instead as an adversarial relationship.</p>

<p>My shift away from hourly billing was based on these principles. When billing based on time, the client has a financial incentive to decrease your contribution to a product, while it gives you a financial incentive to increase it. Right off the bat, this is the kind of adversarial relationship I was unknowingly fostering.</p>

<h2>Steps Moving Forward</h2>

<h3>A More Systemized Business</h3>

<p>This is my primary goal for 2015. This year I learned about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_operating_procedure">standard operating procedures</a>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/E-Myth-Revisited-Michael-E-Gerber-ebook/dp/B000RO9VJK/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;sr=&amp;qid=">how to separate yourself from your business.</a> While I have written some procedures, My coverage is far from complete. The ones I have written have been valuable, and I really want to double down on this.</p>

<p>Standard operating procedures are just step one in building a more scalable, effective business. Even just by themselves, they reduce the mental overhead of making decisions, much like <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/nov/10/obama-zuckerberg-us-president-facebook-founder">wearing the same clothes everyday</a>. But beyond that, they enable you to hand work off or automate. Once you have a defined process, you can hand that work off to a virtual assistant, a subcontractor, or a python script. (Standard operating procedures are basically Python scripts for human beings).</p>

<h3>Strategic Outsourcing</h3>

<p>When I started this business two years ago, if you asked me which parts of my job would be the first to be outsourced, I would not have guessed the actual production work. After all, writing code is <em>what I do</em>. Or at least that is how I used to look at it.</p>

<p>Now, I see that I have much more interest and provide more value in dealing with the “big picture” issues of both my own company and of my clients. Neither one of those requires me to write code.</p>

<p>I don’t plan on removing myself from writing code completely, nor do I plan to be a middle man that farms out work to the lowest bidder on the other side of the world. What I <strong>do</strong> plan on doing is sending well defined parts of projects off to other implementers, and relying more on people that have stronger skills than I do, such as graphic design.</p>

<p>I fully expect this to enable to provide more value to every one of my clients than I have in the past two years.</p>

<h3>Better Positioning</h3>

<p>This year, I made some good steps moving from “guy who writes code” to “guy who solves problems”. This year, I want to hammer out exactly what kinds of problems those are. There is more than enough work available in the world, and being a generalist does more harm than good. In the coming year I hope to have a more clear positioning statement and brand. That might a new job title, it might mean a new company brand. What it definitely means is a marketing strategy that is laser focused on a particular set of problems that a particular set of people have.</p>

<h3>Investing In My Business</h3>

<p>I invested significantly more in my education and in networking than I did last year, and both paid off in spades. Many books I’ve read, groups I’ve joined, and services I’ve used have paid for themselves many times over. This year I’m excited to find more opportunities where I believe I can make my money work for me.</p>

<h3>25% Revenue Growth</h3>

<p>Self-explanitory.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Only 3 Numbers That Matter To A Freelancer's Bottom Line]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/16/the-only-3-numbers-that-matter-to-a-freelancers-bottom-line/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T12:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/16/the-only-3-numbers-that-matter-to-a-freelancers-bottom-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>And 5 Tips to Improve Each One</h3>

<p>The end of the year will be here soon. It's a time to reflect on how the past year went, and plan for the next year. There are three numbers that are the determining factors for your bottom line. By understanding these numbers, you will know what metrics you need to move in order to get the business results you want. By doubling just one of three numbers, you'll double you revenue, without doubling your workload. So instead of saying "I want to make more money next year", by the end of this email I want you to say <strong>how</strong> you plan to make more money next year.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Metric #1: Number of Leads</h2>

<p>You want to measure this as number of leads per month or per quarter. A <strong>lead</strong> is defined as any person who has expressed interest and capability in purchasing your services. If you respond to a listing on a job board, that is not a lead. However, if the person you contacted responds to you and wants to continue the conversation, that is a lead. If you are consistently turning some of leads into customers, then more leads will always equal more customers, which equals more revenue.</p>

<h2>Metric #2: Conversion Rate</h2>

<p>Your <strong>conversion rate</strong> is the percentage of leads that you convert into customers. Don't get discouraged if this number is low. I consider 10% to be a good conversion rate, and anything above that to be excellent. By increasing your conversion rate, you can increase the number of customers that you bring in, without increasing the amount of time you spend on sales. If you need 3 customers a month to make enough money, and your conversion rate is 5%, then you need to start conversations with 60 potential leads a month. If your conversion rate is 10%, then you only need 30.</p>

<p> <em>(If you don't use a CRM to track your leads and conversion, I would highly recommend getting one. There are hundreds to choose from, but I like <a href="http://bit.ly/1itwiuw">PipeDrive</a>)</em></p>

<h2>Metric #3: Customer Lifetime Value</h2>

<p><strong>Customer lifetime value</strong> (often shortened to 'LTV') is the average amount that a customer pays you as long as you two do business together. If you don't know what this number is, you can calculate it by adding up the total amount each client has payed you for all invoices, and then find the average. For example, let's say you bill weekly at $2,000 per week. Your last quarter looks like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Client A: 3 weeks of work:   $6,000</li>
<li>Client B: 5 weeks of work:  $10,000</li>
<li>Client C: 2 week of work:    $4,000</li>
<li>Your customer LTV:       $6,667</li>
</ul>


<p>The more you make per customer, then the less customers you need to make revenue.Once you know these numbers, you can project your income for 2015. The formula looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
$leads_per_month * $conversion_rate * $customer_ltv * 12 = $annual_revenue.
</code></p>

<p>So, let's say you made around $50,000. Your year might look like this:</p>

<p><code>
8 leads per month * 10% conversion rate * $5000 LTV * 12 = $48,000
</code></p>

<p>So, what if next year you want to make closer to $100,000? Instead of setting an arbitrary goal, now you can focus on moving the needle on a particular metric. If you wanted to double you revenue, you either need to figure out how to get more leads, increase your conversion rate, or increase the average amount a customer pays you.</p>

<h3>Tips for Increasing Leads</h3>

<ul>
<li>Adding an email capture to your website, start building a newsletter, and bring in clients that way.</li>
<li>Send more emails out on job boards that you frequent.</li>
<li>Give a seminar or a talk to prospective customers.</li>
<li>Double down on whatever is currently working for you. If you meet people in person, go to even more events.</li>
<li>Get more referrals, by asking for them. Reach out to past clients and current colleagues.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Tips for Increasing Your Conversion Rate</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">Add packaging to your proposals</a>, in order to give clients more ways to say yes.</li>
<li>What have clients said before about why they decided to hire you? Work that into your emails and conversations.</li>
<li>Do clients trust you? Add some convincing work to your portfolio, or get testimonials from past clients.</li>
<li>Add calls to action to all of your client emails. Always make it clear how a client should proceed to move towards working with you.</li>
<li>Get comfortable saying this sentence to prospects: "So, what is going to take to get you to become a client of mine?"</li>
</ul>


<h3>Tips for Increasing Customer Lifetime Value</h3>

<ul>
<li>Raising your rate. Easy-peasy.</li>
<li>Find ways to provide more value for your clients. For example, if you are a developer, providing documentation for other developers or an ''instruction manual' to your client can be a value add that you should price for accordingly.- Offer auxilery services. If you design sites, you could also learn to handle some of the copy writing or data entry for the client.</li>
<li>Sell retainers. Find a way you can provide value to your clients on a monthly basis, and sell clients on those services.</li>
<li>Up-sell. The best time to add someone to the beginning of your sales pipeline is right after a completed project. If you can think of another project that would be beneficial to the client, or a retainer mentioned above, that would be the perfect time to sell them on it.</li>
</ul>


<p>What are your goals for 2015? And <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">what could I do to help you achieve them?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Ways To Build A $200,000 Consultancy]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/5waysto_key.png" width="260"></p>

<p>I recently read an article entitled <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">5 ways to build a $100 million dollar business</a>. It discusses different business models that vary on the number and size of your customer base. Some businesses work with a few enterprise scale clients, while others work with a larger number of smaller customers. Patrick Mackenzie mentioned on Twitter that <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/521878305151000577">"The math here is equally applicable if you are trying to build, say, a $200k a year business"</a>.A $200k/yr consultancy is a goal that seems both attractive and attainable, so I decided try and answer the question "How can you build a $200,000 consultancy?"</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Find 1 Client That Pays You $200,000 (The Elephant)</h3>

<p>I've been a part of projects where a single engagement has had a price tag of $200,000 or more. I think this scenario is a little unlikely. If you can find one of these clients, then you can find more, and you are on your way to becoming a $1mm+ consultancy. It would also be very risky for a company to put all of it's eggs in one basket like this.</p>

<h3>Find 10 Clients That Pay You $20,000 (The Deer)</h3>

<p>There are a few examples of consultancies that make this kind of money. One is custom application development services that can handle ten projects in a year. Most of the client work I find is in this range. Another example is high end consulting engagements. People like <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/">Patrick Mackenzie</a> and <a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com/">Brennan Dunn</a> charge anywhere from $10,000 - $30,000 for a week of their services. They could work 10 engagements a year and hit this $200,000 benchmark.</p>

<h3>Find 100 Clients That Pay You $2,000 (The Rabbits)</h3>

<p>With this setup, your consultancy would have to have a service that scales very well. One way to accomplish this would be to find a way to service multiple clients at one time. Hosting courses or seminars is a way you could accomplish this. For example, Big Nerd Ranch offers <a href="https://training.bignerdranch.com/classes/advanced-ios-bootcamp">programming courses that cost $4,200</a>. At this point, the focus of the work changes. This is less of a consulting model and more of an information product model. There are plenty of gigs out there that pay $2,000 for smaller jobs, which are fine but those are hard to scale.</p>

<h3>Find 1,000 Customers That Pay You $200 (The Mice)</h3>

<p>At this level, you need a product that you can resell. It could be a course that requires little to no interaction for $200 (For example, a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/comprehensive-ruby-on-rails/?dtcode=Q73iZAp1GbIa">UDemy</a> course), or it could be some form of subscription product, which would cost just shy of $20/month. For software developers, you may be able to build a premium software framework or plugin that can sell for this amount. The <a href="http://www.magentocommerce.com/magento-connect/">Magento Connect marketplace</a> is a good example of people going this model. I can't think of any kind of repeatable service model that works at this scale.</p>

<h3>Find 10,000 Customers That Pay You $20 (The Files)</h3>

<p>You are a product business at this point. You could sell ebooks, themes, plugins, or something of that nature. You really can't call it a consultancy at this point. For this kind of business, it looks like the math doesn't scale don't quite so well at this point.</p>

<h3>Applying This To Your Business</h3>

<p>Do you want to work on $2,000 or $200,000 projects? Before you say "$200,000, duh." Think about the pros and cons of fewer clients vs. more, and smaller clients vs. large. Fewer larger clients means a more rigorous, in-depth sales process, and a higher risk if you lose a client.</p>

<p>What kind of consultancy do you want to run, and how are you going to scale it? You can scale not only by getting more clients, but by getting bigger ones as well. If you think about the kind of business you <strong>want</strong> to be running, then you can start making deliberate steps to get there.</p>

<p><small>Image by <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">Christoph Janz</a></small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talking Productized Consulting with Nick Disabato[Video]]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T04:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Origin Story of Draft Revise</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/nickd.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>In this interview I am talking with Nick Disabato, Owner of <a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft</a>, Author of <a href="http://cadence.cc/">Cadence &amp; Slang</a>,, and <a href="https://draft.nu/revise/">Draft Revise</a>, a recurring split testing service that Nick offers to clients. In this interview, Nick talks about creating a new service offering from scratch, How he got his first customers, and how Draft Revise has changed his business.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>




<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Lib91re3onM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Show Notes</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft, a small interaction design consultancy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/nickd">Nick Disabato on Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nickd.org">Nickd.org</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start A Consultancy In 16 Hours From Kai Davis]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T07:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>An Actionable Plan From The Side Hustle Nation</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/kai-davis.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>My friend <a href="http://kaidavis.com/">Kai Davis</a> was recently on the side hustle nation podcast. The episode is <a href="http://www.sidehustlenation.com/start-side-hustle-consulting-business-gets-paid/">How to Start a Side Hustle Consulting Business that Gets Paid</a>. One particular nugget of gold from this podcast: When asked what he would do if he had to start all over, Kai responds with how he would start a new consultancy in 16 hours.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Hours 1-3: Identify A Target Audience</h3>

<p>Decide which market you want to focus on. This could be segmented geographically, or by industry type. If you aren't sure where to begin, try looking at local business directories. Your local chamber of commerce is a good place to start. You could even look in a phone book if you manage to find one.</p>

<h3>Hours 4 - 8: Book Four Calls (But Not Sales Calls)</h3>

<p>Start reaching out to people who you think might be potential clients. Ask them to sit down with you over lunch or coffee, or just hop on the phone with you to discuss their business. People love talking about themselves, and even strangers will be more receptive to this than you would believe. Your goal here isn't to sell them anything, this meeting is research. You want to find the <em>pain points</em> that your potential clients have.</p>

<h3>Hours 9 - 12: Begin Crafting A Service</h3>

<p>Now that you know what problems people in your target audience are having, how can you solve them? Look for ways you can apply your current skills and knowledge to these problems, or how to apply new skills that you could pick up in a reasonable amount of time. If you don't find a good fit, that's OK, you may just have to try again. You don't marry the first person you date, and you don't want to pursue the first job idea that comes to mind.</p>

<h3>Hours 13 - 16: Offer Your Solution</h3>

<p>Now you have connections to your market, and understanding of their problems, and a solution to those problems. Go back to your original contacts and offer your solution. Now you're in business!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
