<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: email | Essentialist Software Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/email/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-20T18:04:04-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Get Through Your Inbox in Under 30 Minutes a Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-19T06:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your inbox is a trap. It’s a place you can go at any point in the day, spend any amount of time, and it will trick you into thinking this is time well spent. You might have your phone or a desktop application configured to ring with a siren’s call every time someone sends you a message, causing you to pay your inbox a visit and spend more time there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Email is rarely important and never urgent. I guarantee that right this second there is something you could spend your time doing that would produce more value to your customers, your family, or yourself than piddling around the inbox.</p>

<p>Email is a task that is unimportant and necessary to your business. While most people can’t slay the beast, it can be tamed. You can reduce the amount of noise if your inbox, and put a system in place so that you can get through your inbox effectively, and get on with your life.</p>

<p>I’ve lost entire weekdays to my inbox before, and I realized I needed a change. Here’s how I tackle my emails in just 30 minutes a day. It takes some time to get going but getting a good email system in place will pay dividends for life. You’ll have more time to focus on what’s important, and you’ll impress many a middle manager.</p>

<h2>Step 1: Move Towards Inbox Zero</h2>

<blockquote><p>opens inbox.</p>

<p>sees 3,000 messages.</p>

<p><em>{eye twitches}</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Nothing is going to be allowed to live in our inbox anymore. <strong>Look at your inbox as a list of emails that need to be handled, not as a place to store information.</strong> Getting there can be hard, but once you are there, it is easy to stay there.</p>

<h3>The fastest way to inbox zero:</h3>

<ol>
<li>Open your email program of choice.</li>
<li>Select all messages.</li>
<li>Click ‘archive’.</li>
<li>You’re done!</li>
</ol>


<p>Archiving or deleting all emails of a certain age is declaring <strong>email bankruptcy</strong>. It’s drastic, but you can’t tell me it doesn’t work. It’s dangerous as there are some emails in your inbox right that you probably should read and get a response. If you can’t take this step, then you can archive any email that is 15, 30, or 60 or more days old. That’ll make cleaning the whole inbox easier.</p>

<p>I’ll talk about how to deal with the remaining emails at the end. But first let’s look at two techniques you can use right now to cut down on the noise in your inbox.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Kill Your Notifications</h2>

<blockquote><p><em>gets tagged in a photo on Facebook.</em></p>

<p><em>pop-up on Facebook: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>email inbox: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “You’ve got mail!”</em></p>

<p><em><eye twitches></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Are there any apps you check daily? Twitter? Facebook? Productive ones? They have their notification system. Deal with Facebook notifications during a time you have to peruse Facebook. Mark Zuckerberg has taken up enough of your time, Don’t let him have some of your valuable inbox time as well.</p>

<p>Go through your common applications and turn off email notifications. Most of these notifications should have an ‘unsubscribe’ link or links to disable them somewhere in them.</p>

<p>If there are applications that you don’t check regularly, and you need to receive email notifications from them, they are exempt from this process. But if you find yourself deleting a notification for the 12th time, take an extra second, and take the steps necessary to disable it. If it is not easy to disable, you can always set up a filter to delete them automatically for you.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Quarantine Newsletters</h2>

<p>I’m a bit of a newsletter junkie.  While there are plenty of good newsletters filled with valuable information. But that doesn’t mean when I am quickly moving through my inbox I want to take 15 minutes to read an in-depth article, regardless of the value of the content.</p>

<p>The next time you receive a newsletter, you need to ask yourself  a single question:</p>

<h3>Is the newsletter valuable to me?</h3>

<p><strong>If the answer is no, then unsubscribe</strong>. Life is too short to spend it on crummy newsletters.</p>

<p><strong>If the answer is yes, then tag and archive it.</strong> I tag mine “Newsletters to Read” and send them automatically to another folder. When I want to read newsletters, I set aside time for them. If you don’t find yourself willing or able to make time to read newsletters, then they weren’t as valuable as you thought when you subscribed.</p>

<h2>Step 4: Process Your Inbox</h2>

<p>Now it’s time to deal with what’s left. Go through each of your emails from oldest to newest, no skipping. You are going to deal with every single one of them, so there is no point in skipping.</p>

<p>This process will take a little while to get through at first. It gets easier with time, I promise. If you still have hundreds of emails in your inbox, then tackle a few, and come back later.</p>

<p>Once you get to each email, you <em>must</em> decide to do one of the following things with it:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Act on it.</strong> Can this email be dealt with by write a short response? If so, write a short response, hit send and archive the message.</li>
<li><strong>Archive/Delete it.</strong> If the message only needed to read and not acted upon, then read it. If you may need to reference the email later, then archive it. If not, delete it. If you are deleting it, ask yourself if it is a newsletter or notification you can do without, and if so, take the steps to prevent getting it again.</li>
<li><strong>Defer It.</strong> Sometimes emails don’t need immediate attention. If this is the case, You can use Mailbox or Boomerang to ‘snooze’ emails until you can deal with them.</li>
<li><strong>Delegate It.</strong> Delegate your email either to another person, another information repository or another task tracker. For example, I may forward an email to Evernote, or to Asana if it the email mentions a task that I need to come back.</li>
</ul>


<p>Repeat until you are at inbox zero. Now go grab yourself a coffee, you’ve earned it.</p>

<h2>Step 5: Timebox</h2>

<p>Once you have gotten used to the process, you need to set aside time that is exclusively for email and remove email from the other parts of your day. I have two 15-minute periods, at 10am and 4pm.</p>

<p>This strategy is ideal for me as I have to keep a maker’s <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">schedule</a> (long uninterrupted work) instead of a manager’s schedule (small meetings and tasks). If you need more time periods in the day or more time allowed then go for it. I fudge on my schedule when I am in heavy <strong>sales mode</strong>. It’s like beast mode but with less aggression and more cold emailing.</p>

<p>If you used to constantly checking email, it could be hard to drop down to just 30 minutes a day. You can’t go the gym and start with a 300-pound squat, you have to work your way there. Here are some baby steps I recommend to make the transition:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Don’t check email first thing in the morning.</strong> The first hour is a rudder for the rest of your day. Checking email first thing is a great way to throw yourself off course. Focus on spending your first hour being productive, and come back to email afterward.</li>
<li><strong>Turn off phone and desktop notifications.</strong> You want to make checking your email a <em>proactive</em> choice, not a <em>reactive</em> choice. Turn off phone notifications, desktop notifications, and don’t keep a browser tab open in the background.</li>
<li><strong>Don’t check email before bed.</strong> I have never done this and then thought “that was a good decision. I am glad I did that.”</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you’ve done this, you’ve changed your relationship with your inbox. You don’t work on your inbox’s schedule; it works on yours. Email doesn’t control you; you control your email.</p>

<h2>BONUS Step 6: Automation</h2>

<p>These are some additional steps that I use to automate and streamline the time I spend in my email inbox.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Use canned responses.</strong> <a href="http://time.com/12436/quick-gmail-trick-pre-write-email-messages-with-canned-responses/">Canned responses</a> are a Gmail Labs feature. They allow you to save and reuse common responses and messages you send. I use these for common use cases such as follow-ups, initial emails, and even snippets of emails, such as links to my <a href="http://glennstovall.com/case-studies/">portfolio</a> and <a href="http://careers.stackoverflow.com/glennstovall">CV</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Write short responses.</strong> Email is simply a way for people to try and get your time for their agenda. Remember that when you are sending email, you are doing the same, and you should be respecting of other people’s time. Emails should rarely be more than a few sentences.</li>
<li><strong>Take the “<a href="http://unlessiheardifferently.com/">Unless I Hear Otherwise</a>” Approach.</strong> Instead of offering options and opinions, offer a choice with an out. Compare these two emails:</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><em>The slow email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of reasons X, Y, and Z. Which would you prefer?</p>

<p><em>The productive email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of {reasons}.  <strong>Unless I hear otherwise</strong> by close of business, I’ll move forward with option A.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Write More Personal Emails to Your List That Get Open and Convert]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-09T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>My Email Marketing Strategy In a Nutshell</h3>

<p>Email marketing converts better than social media or content marketing. Nathan Barry has a great <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/email-marketing/">write up with the numbers</a>. You can build a list by <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today/">giving people  incentives in exchange for their email address</a>, reaching out to them directly, or offering people updates on as-yet-unreleased new product. But once you have built that list, how do you write emails that people on that list will actually want to read?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Drop The Newsletters and start writing emails</h3>

<p>Newsletters are usually ignored and end up right in the trash bin.  Instead of thinking of your emails to your list as newsletters, I want you to approach them like you would writing an email to one person. When I write email drafts, I will usually start with the line 'Hey Bob,', where Bob is a real person I know. If I write with a more personal tone in mind, it will show in the final result. Your formatting needs to match this more personal tone, so no more fancy email themes..</p>

<h3>7 Steps to Formatting Your Email</h3>

<h4>1.Remove all formatting.</h4>

<p>Your email should look just like you sent it from your GMail or Mailbox account. This means that you don't want any of the formatting that  email list providers offer. However, you don't want to send a plain text email either. Plain text takes away some key formatting tools, such as <strong>bolding</strong>, <em>italicizing</em>, and <a href="#">putting in links</a>.</p>

<h4>2. Write your subject line like you would a regular email.</h4>

<p>Don't title case your headline. Capitalize the first word, and then write the rest lowercase. Using questions in your subject line is a good way to increase open rates, but can become annoying if over used.</p>

<h4>3.Set the From Address to Your Address, and Encourage Replies.</h4>

<p>Emails are conversations, and conversations are a two-way street. The from address should be from your personal address if possible, and if not, one that you check and respond too frequently. Your subscribers should be able to reply to any of your emails and expect a response (it may not be obvious this is the case since the email is automated).</p>

<h4>4.Start with a salutation.</h4>

<p>If possible, capture the first name of people when they sign up for your list. This will allow you to start with a line like 'Hey [first_name]'. A person's name is their favorite word to hear, and it starts your email off on the right foot.</p>

<h4>5.Write short body copy.</h4>

<p>Some people like to send out entire articles in their email list. Personally, I don't like this approach and haven't had much success. If I have a lot to say, I will publish a larger article elsewhere, and include a short description in the email. I like to provide something extra to my subscribers, so I will usually provide additional examples or a personal story in the email.</p>

<h4>6.End with a friendly signature.</h4>

<p>I always sign my emails with "cheers, Glenn". Much like the salutation, This gives the letter a more personal feel.</p>

<h4>7.Often, but not always, include a PS.</h4>

<p>The post script is one of the most read part of the email, after the subject line and the first paragraph. Even if people don't want to read the rest of your email, they will check out the PS. In old letter writing, the 'PS' was where people would include something <em>so good</em> that they just couldn't leave it out. Your PS should only be a couple sentences long, and get straight to the point.</p>

<h3>The 3 Types of Emails to Send</h3>

<p>When writing emails to your list, there are three formats that I use:</p>

<h4>1.The Value Email.</h4>

<p>This email has no ulterior motive. This is simply an email that provides value to your list. You can provide value by offering something educational, useful, or entertaining to your list. <strong>you do not sell to your list.</strong> If someone was nice enough to sign up for your list, they deserve value from you in return. This is where you give it to them.</p>

<h4>2.The Soft Sell Email.</h4>

<p>The soft sell email is identical to the value email, with one small difference: You mention something you are selling as a secondary point in the email. The PS is a great place to do this. You can write a valuable article, then in the PS include a call to action. Now when I say "sale", I don't always mean that you are asking the people on your list to give you money in exchange for goods or services. A "sale" is anytime you are asking them to give up something of value in exchange for something of equal or greater value. When people sign up for your list, that was a sale. They exchanged access to their inbox for valuable information. In addition to selling products, you could ask them to sign up for a free trial, ask them a question, or ask them to attend an event such as a webinar.</p>

<h4>3.The Hard Sell Email.</h4>

<p>These emails have one goal: To get your users to buy something you are selling. Like the soft sell email, that sale could be anything from a transaction to a webinar sign-up. Use these <strong>sparingly</strong>.</p>

<h3>The Frequency of Emails</h3>

<p>I send out emails once a week, sometimes every two weeks. If you email your list more frequently than that, they may become fatigued. Some people push their list harder, and this is something that depends on your audience.</p>

<p>The only time I break this rule is when I am launching a new product or have an upcoming event. I will ramp up the emails to build anticipation for the event, and usually send reminders a week before, a day before, and even an hour before.</p>

<p>When it comes to email frequency, you should also be mindful of the frequency you use the three templates above. The hard sell email is OK sometimes, but if that is all you send, you will not keep your subscribers for long. My general rule of thumb is to keep a 2:1 ratio for helpful, valuable emails, and sales emails. Here is a 6-email rotation I tend to use:</p>

<ul>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Soft sell email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Hard sell email</li>
</ul>


<p>That way, once I have gotten to the point where I am selling someone, I have already provided them a lot of value. This also means that I am only sending out sales emails once every 5 - 6 weeks. It may seem odd to spend a lot of time building a list and then sell to it so infrequently, but by taking this approach those sales emails are much more likely to get responses.</p>

<h3>Segment Your List As Much As Possible</h3>

<p>So far, all of this has been about making your emails more personalized. Doesn't it seem strange to be more 'personal', and then send the same email to your entire list? It's true, and one way to get around this is <em>segmentation.</em> Segmentation means that you break your list up based on past behavior, and sent broadcasts to smaller segments of your list. For example, if you are selling a certain product, it doesn't make sense to keep sending emails to those people asking them to buy that product. Instead, you could only send them valuable emails, ask them for feedback on the product, or sell them something else.</p>

<h3>Email Tools that Provide Segmentation</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a>.</strong> I've mentioned ConvertKit before, as it is the email tool I currently use. They recently revamped their segmenting, and allow you to segment on users based on which email capture form they signed up for.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.getdrip.com">Drip</a>.</strong> Drip has moved from being an email list management tool to a full on marketing automation tool. They provide user tagging, and a lot of triggers that you can use to segment your audience.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.mailchimp.com">MailChimp</a>.</strong> Mailchimp recently released a whole new <a href="http://mailchimp.com/features/automation/">suite of automation tools</a>. These are new and I haven't tried them yet, but it looks promising. MailChimp is what a lot of people use already, so if this is you, you have a whole new set of toys to play with.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.infusionsoft.com">InfusionSoft</a>.</strong> InfusionSoft is the most powerful and most complex tool ons the market. They have a large start up cost (in the 4 figures), but they have a lot of tools and integration they make them the most in-depth marketing automation system out there.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is my entire email marketing strategy in a nutshell. By following these formulas, you can keep your list more engaged, and build a strong audience that is invested in you and your brand.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start Using Drip Email Campaigns Today]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Increase Engagement And Conversions When People Sign Up For Your Email List</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/drip.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>When building a mailing list, engagement is highest within the first two to three weeks of the person joining the list. However, these people usually get the same content that everyone else on your list getting. Wouldn’t it be great if you could send them content that was optimized for this situation. That’s what <strong>drip email campaigns</strong> are for.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What are Drip Email Campaigns?</h3>

<p>Drip email campaigns are email campaigns that are sent out based on when a subscriber has performed an action instead of being scheduled on a calendar date. While a regular email list campaign may be scheduled to go out on June 1st, 2014 at 1pm, A drip email campaign will be scheduled to be sent out 3 days after a sign up.</p>

<p>Drip marketing campaigns are usually several emails in length. We want to reach out to a person multiple times (but too much, don’t be obnoxious) when they have first joined our list.</p>

<h3>Playing the Long Game</h3>

<p>No matter what you are selling, you are always selling people trust to some degree. People need to believe in your product and believe that you are capable of solving their problem before they will be willing to pay you money to do so. You can’t really build a whole lot of trust on social media or on a landing page. However, it takes much less trust to get someone’s email address, and from there you will have several opportunities to reach out to this person and build trust.</p>

<h3>How to Structure Your Campaign</h3>

<p>The most important thing about your campaign is that you need it to be helpful and valuable to your new subscriber. Your posts need to be mostly selfless. If you run a mailing list and all you do is sell to them, then you are doing it wrong, and it will drive people away. By selling directly less, you will build more trust, and make more sales in the end.</p>

<p>My personal rule is that your helpful content should have a minimum 2:1 ratio of being helpful, and being a sales email. Also, you should mix up between “hard sells” and “soft sells”. A hard sell is an email where the entire point is to get the user to complete a transaction. A soft sell is a message that is still valuable, but contains a subtle message.  For example, I may write an email about how to use lifecycle emails to increase conversions, and follow it up with “And by the way, this is something I love helping clients with. hit ‘reply’ if you would like to talk about us working together.”</p>

<p>Following those rules, here is what a drip campaign might look like:</p>

<ol>
<li>An introductory email.</li>
<li>An educational email.</li>
<li>An education email with a soft sell.</li>
<li>1 -2 more educational emails.</li>
<li>A hard sell.</li>
</ol>


<p>You can change this as you see fit, just stick to the 2:1 ratio.</p>

<h3>Your First Campaign</h3>

<p>If you have done any writing before, you can set your first campaign set up  quickly. Go find 4 – 5 of your best email campaigns or blog posts, and spread them out over 2 -4 weeks. You now have a campaign! This way you are giving your new subscribers your best content at a point when they are most engaged, making this some of the most effective email marketing you can do.</p>

<h3>Using Drip Campaigns as an Incentive</h3>

<p>Which do you think is a better call to action to get people to join a mailing list?</p>

<ul>
<li>Sign up for my newsletter.</li>
<li>Enter your email address and I will give you something for free.</li>
</ul>


<p>I recently wrote a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/">case study</a> about how I used a free eBook in order to jump start one of my lists. You can use your drip campaign as the incentive by framing it as a service. For example, you may have a 30-day course that can teach your potential clients how to do something. ConvertKit is a drip marketing tool that does this on their first page. Since the service revolves around building forms to get people to sign up, they have a <a href="https://convertkit.com/">30 day course on creating forms that convert</a>.</p>

<h3>Tools for Drip Campaigns</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Mailchimp Autoresponders</strong> : Mailchimp doesn’t have any tools built specifically for drip marketing campaigns, but they do have autoresponders, which you can use to set one up. You can set an autoresponder to be sent out X days after someone joins a list, so you can create a drip campaign by creating several autoresponders.</li>
<li><strong>Drip</strong>: As you can tell my the name, Drip is designed specifically for creating drip campaigns. It also integrates well with other email list providers, so if you want to use Drip for your campaigns and Mailchimp or AWeber for your list management, you can do that.</li>
<li><strong>ConvertKit</strong>: ConvertKit is what I have been using lately. It has support for list management, drip campaigns, and offering sign-up incentives.</li>
</ul>


<p>By using drip campaigns, you can have a long form message that you can deliver to every single person that expresses interest in whatever it is your offering. If you have ever done sales where you had to have several emails or phone calls back and forth with a potential client, then you how time consuming that can be. Drip campaigns allow you to automate this process with the people that are in a situation where they are most likely to convert.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
