<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opinion | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-03T16:20:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Say No To Entreporn]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/say-no-to-entreporn/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T20:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/say-no-to-entreporn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Reading HackerNews is More Harmful Than You Think</h3>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>There is an insidious type of content out there on the internet, that is easy to waste time on. It’s what I call “entreporn”, and it isn’t only a waste of time to people, it is actively <strong>harmful</strong> to aspiring entrepreneurs.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What is Entreporn?</h3>

<p>I define entrepornography as any article that focuses on start-ups that have had some kind of crazy, fluke amount of success. Reading about snapchat was offered $3 billion dollars by Facebook but had the guts to say no. Some college kid built a web app and made $20,000 in sales while he was passed out from a bender. At least 60% of whatever is on the front page of Hacker News whenever you read this post. These pieces are salacious and exciting. They get us to imagine a world where we can take an idea all the way to top and create a hugely successful venture. It’s truely the american dream!</p>

<h3>What's the Problem</h3>

<p>The problem is that the stories they like to tell are flukes. It inspires people who want to be “The next Facebook”. The problem is that no one is going to be the next Facebook. No one is going to have the same conditions that Mark Zuckerburg did. Even if they did, any company requires a lot of luck, especially to get to the place Facebook is at today. And besides, I never understood why Twitter didn’t get to take “The next Facebook”  crown and keep it.</p>

<p>These articles can’t teach you anything, because they tell stories of companies that aren’t repeatable. I’m not asking that you stop reading articles on the internet, because it would make me quite the hypocritical writer. But also because there is a ton of good, valuable advice out there you could be reading instead.</p>

<h3>Why It's Harmful</h3>

<p>However, the time wasting is not the worst part about this. As I said, I consider entreporn <strong>harmful</strong>. It’s toxic. It, much like regular pornography, gives inexperienced people a skewed view of what reality is like. Entreporn gives people the idea that they can pursue any idea, and hit it big. It gives people the impressions that start ups are like the lottery, except that they are willing to buy a single ticket with thousands of dollars and years of their life.</p>

<p>I don’t want to discourage anyone from being an entrepreneur, in fact I would encourage anyone interested to learn more about it. However, I would encourage these people to learn how to be an entrepreneur in <em>the real world</em>, not the fantasy land that TechCrunch likes to paint. Very few people can build “The next Facebook”, but a <strong>whole lot</strong> of people can build a sustainable, profitable business. and reading these vain articles is actively preventing people from doing so.</p>

<p>I don’t want to read about the guy who got 10,000 subscribers in a weekend. I’ll never be that guy. I want to read about the guy that got 100 and how he did it. That’s educational. That’s actionable. That’s <strong>real</strong>. Startups are not exempt from the being businesses, and the rules of business that have existed for hundreds of years still apply. By learning about how to build your business realistically, you have a much lower risk and higher chance of success.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);console.log('event fired')">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
  
<style type="text/css">
</style>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
