<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: strategy | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/strategy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-17T15:46:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Write More Personal Emails to Your List That Get Open and Convert]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-09T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>My Email Marketing Strategy In a Nutshell</h3>

<p>Email marketing converts better than social media or content marketing. Nathan Barry has a great <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/email-marketing/">write up with the numbers</a>. You can build a list by <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today/">giving people  incentives in exchange for their email address</a>, reaching out to them directly, or offering people updates on as-yet-unreleased new product. But once you have built that list, how do you write emails that people on that list will actually want to read?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Drop The Newsletters and start writing emails</h3>

<p>Newsletters are usually ignored and end up right in the trash bin.  Instead of thinking of your emails to your list as newsletters, I want you to approach them like you would writing an email to one person. When I write email drafts, I will usually start with the line 'Hey Bob,', where Bob is a real person I know. If I write with a more personal tone in mind, it will show in the final result. Your formatting needs to match this more personal tone, so no more fancy email themes..</p>

<h3>7 Steps to Formatting Your Email</h3>

<h4>1.Remove all formatting.</h4>

<p>Your email should look just like you sent it from your GMail or Mailbox account. This means that you don't want any of the formatting that  email list providers offer. However, you don't want to send a plain text email either. Plain text takes away some key formatting tools, such as <strong>bolding</strong>, <em>italicizing</em>, and <a href="#">putting in links</a>.</p>

<h4>2. Write your subject line like you would a regular email.</h4>

<p>Don't title case your headline. Capitalize the first word, and then write the rest lowercase. Using questions in your subject line is a good way to increase open rates, but can become annoying if over used.</p>

<h4>3.Set the From Address to Your Address, and Encourage Replies.</h4>

<p>Emails are conversations, and conversations are a two-way street. The from address should be from your personal address if possible, and if not, one that you check and respond too frequently. Your subscribers should be able to reply to any of your emails and expect a response (it may not be obvious this is the case since the email is automated).</p>

<h4>4.Start with a salutation.</h4>

<p>If possible, capture the first name of people when they sign up for your list. This will allow you to start with a line like 'Hey [first_name]'. A person's name is their favorite word to hear, and it starts your email off on the right foot.</p>

<h4>5.Write short body copy.</h4>

<p>Some people like to send out entire articles in their email list. Personally, I don't like this approach and haven't had much success. If I have a lot to say, I will publish a larger article elsewhere, and include a short description in the email. I like to provide something extra to my subscribers, so I will usually provide additional examples or a personal story in the email.</p>

<h4>6.End with a friendly signature.</h4>

<p>I always sign my emails with "cheers, Glenn". Much like the salutation, This gives the letter a more personal feel.</p>

<h4>7.Often, but not always, include a PS.</h4>

<p>The post script is one of the most read part of the email, after the subject line and the first paragraph. Even if people don't want to read the rest of your email, they will check out the PS. In old letter writing, the 'PS' was where people would include something <em>so good</em> that they just couldn't leave it out. Your PS should only be a couple sentences long, and get straight to the point.</p>

<h3>The 3 Types of Emails to Send</h3>

<p>When writing emails to your list, there are three formats that I use:</p>

<h4>1.The Value Email.</h4>

<p>This email has no ulterior motive. This is simply an email that provides value to your list. You can provide value by offering something educational, useful, or entertaining to your list. <strong>you do not sell to your list.</strong> If someone was nice enough to sign up for your list, they deserve value from you in return. This is where you give it to them.</p>

<h4>2.The Soft Sell Email.</h4>

<p>The soft sell email is identical to the value email, with one small difference: You mention something you are selling as a secondary point in the email. The PS is a great place to do this. You can write a valuable article, then in the PS include a call to action. Now when I say "sale", I don't always mean that you are asking the people on your list to give you money in exchange for goods or services. A "sale" is anytime you are asking them to give up something of value in exchange for something of equal or greater value. When people sign up for your list, that was a sale. They exchanged access to their inbox for valuable information. In addition to selling products, you could ask them to sign up for a free trial, ask them a question, or ask them to attend an event such as a webinar.</p>

<h4>3.The Hard Sell Email.</h4>

<p>These emails have one goal: To get your users to buy something you are selling. Like the soft sell email, that sale could be anything from a transaction to a webinar sign-up. Use these <strong>sparingly</strong>.</p>

<h3>The Frequency of Emails</h3>

<p>I send out emails once a week, sometimes every two weeks. If you email your list more frequently than that, they may become fatigued. Some people push their list harder, and this is something that depends on your audience.</p>

<p>The only time I break this rule is when I am launching a new product or have an upcoming event. I will ramp up the emails to build anticipation for the event, and usually send reminders a week before, a day before, and even an hour before.</p>

<p>When it comes to email frequency, you should also be mindful of the frequency you use the three templates above. The hard sell email is OK sometimes, but if that is all you send, you will not keep your subscribers for long. My general rule of thumb is to keep a 2:1 ratio for helpful, valuable emails, and sales emails. Here is a 6-email rotation I tend to use:</p>

<ul>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Soft sell email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Value email</li>
<li>Hard sell email</li>
</ul>


<p>That way, once I have gotten to the point where I am selling someone, I have already provided them a lot of value. This also means that I am only sending out sales emails once every 5 - 6 weeks. It may seem odd to spend a lot of time building a list and then sell to it so infrequently, but by taking this approach those sales emails are much more likely to get responses.</p>

<h3>Segment Your List As Much As Possible</h3>

<p>So far, all of this has been about making your emails more personalized. Doesn't it seem strange to be more 'personal', and then send the same email to your entire list? It's true, and one way to get around this is <em>segmentation.</em> Segmentation means that you break your list up based on past behavior, and sent broadcasts to smaller segments of your list. For example, if you are selling a certain product, it doesn't make sense to keep sending emails to those people asking them to buy that product. Instead, you could only send them valuable emails, ask them for feedback on the product, or sell them something else.</p>

<h3>Email Tools that Provide Segmentation</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a>.</strong> I've mentioned ConvertKit before, as it is the email tool I currently use. They recently revamped their segmenting, and allow you to segment on users based on which email capture form they signed up for.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.getdrip.com">Drip</a>.</strong> Drip has moved from being an email list management tool to a full on marketing automation tool. They provide user tagging, and a lot of triggers that you can use to segment your audience.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.mailchimp.com">MailChimp</a>.</strong> Mailchimp recently released a whole new <a href="http://mailchimp.com/features/automation/">suite of automation tools</a>. These are new and I haven't tried them yet, but it looks promising. MailChimp is what a lot of people use already, so if this is you, you have a whole new set of toys to play with.</li>
<li><strong><a href="http://www.infusionsoft.com">InfusionSoft</a>.</strong> InfusionSoft is the most powerful and most complex tool ons the market. They have a large start up cost (in the 4 figures), but they have a lot of tools and integration they make them the most in-depth marketing automation system out there.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is my entire email marketing strategy in a nutshell. By following these formulas, you can keep your list more engaged, and build a strong audience that is invested in you and your brand.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breakdown of a Pricing Grid]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T20:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learn Why is The Middle Plan Always Called The "Best Value"</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/bidsketch_pricing_full.png" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>You may have noticed that on many software as a service pricing pages, they tend to look the same. There are always a few plans, usually 3, and they middle is <strong>always</strong> the most popular. This isn’t an accident. This is all designed to get the maximum value out of a customer. Let’s take a look at one company’s pricing model and why it is effective.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch_pricing_full.png"></p>

<p>I got this table from <a href="http://www.bidsketch.com/pricing/">BidSketch’s pricing page</a>. BidSketch is a tool that helps freelancers and agencies write and send winning proposals. This table is important to BidSketch. Literally every single customer, and therefore every single dollar, comes from this page. Nothing in this table is an accident. Let’s take a look at the plan names:</p>

<h3>Customer Segmentation</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-segmentation.png"></p>

<p>you’ll notice that BidSketch doesn’t call it’s plans “small/medium/large”, or “bronze/silver/gold” or anything generic like that. Instead, they know that they have different kinds of customers, and that those customers are willing to pay different rates. They aim at three of their types of clients: individual freelancers, small studios, and large agencies.</p>

<p>Why do they charge agencies more money? Because agencies get more value out of BidSketch than freelancers. The proposals that large agencies are sending out are an order of magnitude larger than the one a freelancer is sending out.</p>

<p>This is the most important part of pricing any service or product: <strong>when the customer gets more value out of your product or service, you need to be getting more value from that customer.</strong> Doing this aligns your incentives with the customer’s. This means that now you and the customer are a team. Since you make money off of your customer being successful, you will do everything you can to help your customer. Since BidSketch knows that if they help their customers make more money by helping them write better proposals, they are going to do everything they can to make the best proposal tool out there? It’s a win-win for everybody.</p>

<h3>Pricing Ratio</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-pricing.png"></p>

<p>Firstly, you’ll notice that BidSketch put their highest price package first. This is an old-school marketing trick. By looking at the initial plan first, the $79 and $29 plans will feel much cheaper in comparison. The highest selling price plan is almost never the highest selling one, it is mostly their for comparison. This is called <em>price anchoring.</em></p>

<p>You also want to have a decent ratio between your prices. If their prices were $29 / $39 / $49, they aren’t getting much extra value out of the plans. In fact, <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ryandelk/micro-conf-final">Ryan Delk at Gumroad</a> has looked at all the sales of digital products, and has found the optimal ratios for tiered pricing:</p>

<h4><em>1x 2.2x 5x</em></h4>

<p>Where ‘X’ is the base cost of your service. You’ll see that BidSketch follows this ratio closely: $79 = 2.7x , $149 = 5.1x . Note that ratio is just an approximation, and you don’t have to follow it exactly.  <em>(I don’t think BidSketch would get the same revenue with a $29 /  $63.80  / $145 model)</em></p>

<h3>Approximating Value</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-features.png"></p>

<p>I said before that the best way to split up your pricing is to align your values with the customer’s. BidSketch could do this directly if they wanted too, and base their pricing on how the total dollar value of proposals that you close each month (payment processors such as <a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a> and <a href="https://www.braintreepayments.com/">Briaintree</a> have the easiest alignment ever. They just get 2.7% of the revenue you bring in). In other cases, you may not have a way of directly knowing how valuable your service is to a client. In that case, you want to approximate the value. You do this by tying your pricing to something that is correlated to value. BidSketch does this in two ways: the number of users, and the amount of storage. Instead of looking a dollar value, they are looking at three things with these features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Number of employees / contractors you have working for you.</li>
<li>The number of proposals you are sending out.</li>
<li>The quality of proposals you are sending out. (i.e. using more photos &amp; videos, hence more storage)</li>
</ul>


<p>A company that has multiple people (agencies, studios) have to be making payroll, which means they are almost always making more money. That’s why you see a lot of software as a service products segment on number of users. One of the things that has held me back from hiring an assistant is I know the minute I have one employee my monthly software bill would shoot up a few hundred dollars a month.</p>

<p>There are two version control services that software developers use: <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> and <a href="https://bitbucket.org/">BitBucket</a>. A version control service is a place where developers can store and collaborate on code. BitBucket increases prices based number of users, but GitHub prices based on number of projects. I feel like GitHub missed the mark on this pricing. Number of projects is a false approximation of value. For example, BidSketch may only have one project file, for their software service product. I, as a consultant, would have a large number of projects since I work with a number of different clients. Why should I, a self employed consultant, be charged more than a company that pulls in millions of revenue every year?</p>

<h3>Good Artists Borrow, Great Artists Steal</h3>

<p>When it comes to pricing, there is no need to get creative.  There is a reason so many software as a service pricing pages look the same. <strong>Because it works.</strong> Every one would not do it if it wasn’t effective. If I was going to create a product aimed ad freelancers and agencies, I would look at competing and complementary products, and set up a very similar model. I may even use BidSketch’s exact same three tiers. The reason is that if I want to get into this space, BidSketch has done me a <strong>huge</strong> favor:</p>

<h4><em>They have found and validated a price that the market will bear.</em></h4>

<p>Usually finding a working pricing model requires lots of research and experimentation. However, to every one who wants to build a proposal tool, BidSketch has done them a huge favor. Thanks BidSketch! Some times people have a product idea, and get discouraged because it’s “been done”. Competition is not always a bad thing. Competition can be a sign that something works. On the other side of that coin, if you come up with a seemingly obvious idea that no one has done yet, it’s worth pausing for a moment and considering why you are the only person to show up to that particular party.</p>

<p>Pricing models don’t need to be original. They need to be effective at converting sales and maximizing customer value. Save your creativity for your actual product.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start Using Drip Email Campaigns Today]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Increase Engagement And Conversions When People Sign Up For Your Email List</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/drip.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>When building a mailing list, engagement is highest within the first two to three weeks of the person joining the list. However, these people usually get the same content that everyone else on your list getting. Wouldn’t it be great if you could send them content that was optimized for this situation. That’s what <strong>drip email campaigns</strong> are for.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What are Drip Email Campaigns?</h3>

<p>Drip email campaigns are email campaigns that are sent out based on when a subscriber has performed an action instead of being scheduled on a calendar date. While a regular email list campaign may be scheduled to go out on June 1st, 2014 at 1pm, A drip email campaign will be scheduled to be sent out 3 days after a sign up.</p>

<p>Drip marketing campaigns are usually several emails in length. We want to reach out to a person multiple times (but too much, don’t be obnoxious) when they have first joined our list.</p>

<h3>Playing the Long Game</h3>

<p>No matter what you are selling, you are always selling people trust to some degree. People need to believe in your product and believe that you are capable of solving their problem before they will be willing to pay you money to do so. You can’t really build a whole lot of trust on social media or on a landing page. However, it takes much less trust to get someone’s email address, and from there you will have several opportunities to reach out to this person and build trust.</p>

<h3>How to Structure Your Campaign</h3>

<p>The most important thing about your campaign is that you need it to be helpful and valuable to your new subscriber. Your posts need to be mostly selfless. If you run a mailing list and all you do is sell to them, then you are doing it wrong, and it will drive people away. By selling directly less, you will build more trust, and make more sales in the end.</p>

<p>My personal rule is that your helpful content should have a minimum 2:1 ratio of being helpful, and being a sales email. Also, you should mix up between “hard sells” and “soft sells”. A hard sell is an email where the entire point is to get the user to complete a transaction. A soft sell is a message that is still valuable, but contains a subtle message.  For example, I may write an email about how to use lifecycle emails to increase conversions, and follow it up with “And by the way, this is something I love helping clients with. hit ‘reply’ if you would like to talk about us working together.”</p>

<p>Following those rules, here is what a drip campaign might look like:</p>

<ol>
<li>An introductory email.</li>
<li>An educational email.</li>
<li>An education email with a soft sell.</li>
<li>1 -2 more educational emails.</li>
<li>A hard sell.</li>
</ol>


<p>You can change this as you see fit, just stick to the 2:1 ratio.</p>

<h3>Your First Campaign</h3>

<p>If you have done any writing before, you can set your first campaign set up  quickly. Go find 4 – 5 of your best email campaigns or blog posts, and spread them out over 2 -4 weeks. You now have a campaign! This way you are giving your new subscribers your best content at a point when they are most engaged, making this some of the most effective email marketing you can do.</p>

<h3>Using Drip Campaigns as an Incentive</h3>

<p>Which do you think is a better call to action to get people to join a mailing list?</p>

<ul>
<li>Sign up for my newsletter.</li>
<li>Enter your email address and I will give you something for free.</li>
</ul>


<p>I recently wrote a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/">case study</a> about how I used a free eBook in order to jump start one of my lists. You can use your drip campaign as the incentive by framing it as a service. For example, you may have a 30-day course that can teach your potential clients how to do something. ConvertKit is a drip marketing tool that does this on their first page. Since the service revolves around building forms to get people to sign up, they have a <a href="https://convertkit.com/">30 day course on creating forms that convert</a>.</p>

<h3>Tools for Drip Campaigns</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Mailchimp Autoresponders</strong> : Mailchimp doesn’t have any tools built specifically for drip marketing campaigns, but they do have autoresponders, which you can use to set one up. You can set an autoresponder to be sent out X days after someone joins a list, so you can create a drip campaign by creating several autoresponders.</li>
<li><strong>Drip</strong>: As you can tell my the name, Drip is designed specifically for creating drip campaigns. It also integrates well with other email list providers, so if you want to use Drip for your campaigns and Mailchimp or AWeber for your list management, you can do that.</li>
<li><strong>ConvertKit</strong>: ConvertKit is what I have been using lately. It has support for list management, drip campaigns, and offering sign-up incentives.</li>
</ul>


<p>By using drip campaigns, you can have a long form message that you can deliver to every single person that expresses interest in whatever it is your offering. If you have ever done sales where you had to have several emails or phone calls back and forth with a potential client, then you how time consuming that can be. Drip campaigns allow you to automate this process with the people that are in a situation where they are most likely to convert.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better Business Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/better-business-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/better-business-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Get Better Information From The Same Data</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/analytics.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>It’s important to track metrics in your business. Tracking metrics means that you can make decisions based on numbers and cold hard facts instead of guessing and gut feelings. But not all metrics are created equal, and not all ways of tracking metrics are creating equal. If you are looking at the wrong numbers, then you could end up making disastrous decisions. Let’s take a look at the best ways to track metrics, and the most important numbers you need to be keeping an eye on.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Metrics by Time</h3>

<p>You want to look at metrics in units of time. “Grand total” type metrics, such as total number of Facebook followers, doesn’t tell you anything about the current standing of your business. In this example, you would want to look at “new Facebook followers per month” instead. This way you can see how you are doing at your key performance indicators <em>right now</em>.</p>

<h3>Metrics by Change</h3>

<p>What’s even better than looking at metrics is weekly or monthly units, is looking at the comparison of those units. Even better than “new Facebook followers per month” would to compare this month’s number to last month’s number, and come up with a new metric, “% change in new Facebook followers”. This is the number where you want to move the meter. This shows the rate of growth inside your company.</p>

<p>This is one of those times in life where calculus is actually useful. By looking at these numbers, you are looking at the velocity and acceleration of your business. If you are driving a car and want to reach your destination faster, you don’t look at how many miles you have traveled, you look at your miles per hour (a metric over time), and put the pedal in the medal in order to increase your miles per hour over time (a metric by change).</p>

<h3>Three Primary Metrics</h3>

<p>There are three primary metrics that every business, no matter how large or small, no matter how tech-savvy or old-school, should be looking at:</p>

<ul>
<li>Leads: The number of potential customers you are making contact with each month.</li>
<li>Conversions: What percentage of those leads are you able to convert into paying customers?</li>
<li>Profit: Is your business making enough money to be viable. Profit is just the child of two other important metrics, Revenue and Expenses, which are both important in their own right.</li>
</ul>


<p>I’m not saying these are the only things worth tracking, but if you don’t know these numbers then this would be a good place to start. It’s better to focus on a few important metrics than many unimportant ones. While keeping up with numbers is a good thing, you don’t want to drown out the signal with a lot of noise.</p>

<h3>Vanity Metrics</h3>

<p>There are a number of metrics that you probably actively avoid tracking in order to prevent you from making bad decisions. If you tracked number of sales of a certain type of product, but the cost of a sale of that product caused you to lose money on it, then you would end up trying to increase the units sold, and eventually end up in the poor house
. Here are some examples of numbers that are not worth wasting your time on:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Registered Users</strong>: Getting users to try a new service once is easy. Getting users to stay is something else altogether.</li>
<li><strong>Pageviews</strong>: Pageviews can be easily manipulated, and are worth very little. It also doesn’t tell you about the quality of the traffic. I would rather have 10 visits from potential clients than 1,000 visits from people from Hacker News who happened to like a blog article.</li>
<li><strong>Likes</strong> Unless your business is heavily focused in the social media space, I wouldn’t put a lot of weight on how many likes, shares, retweets, and so on your company gets. These are like pageviews but another step removed and that much more worthless.</li>
</ul>


<p>These are called vanity metrics because they make you feel good. However, none of these are actionable and don’t have any impact on the bottom line of your business. Don’t get caught up in trying to move these numbers much.</p>

<h3>Further Watching</h3>

<p>If you’d like to learn more about metrics, what to watch and how to watch them, Ben Yoskovitz gave a talk called “Lean Analytics: How to Focus on What Matters” Which is available for free online. I highly recommend it:</p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/70981922">Ben Yoskovitz – Lean Analytics: How to Focus on What Matters</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/user12790628">MicroConf</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Great Customer Service Example]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/a-great-customer-service-example/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/a-great-customer-service-example</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How One Blog Post Made Me A Loyal Customer</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/convertkit.png" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>I have recently been working on using Nathan Barry’s app <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a> to set up some new email marketing tools, and It wasn’t immediately clear to me how to  import users, so I sent him an email asking how to do this. In 15 minutes, I get a response that he had just put this up:</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/convertkit.png"></p>

<p>A <a href="https://convertkit.com/2014/import-email-subscribers/">whole blog post</a>, written just for me! I thought it was an impressive effort, and a very quick turnaround. But this is also a good example of another good customer service strategy:  Using your blog as your manual / help desk.</p>

<p>Not only did Nathan reach out to me personally, he has a piece of content that accomplishes several other goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>It highlights a feature of his application: ConvertKit can import subscribers from your other applications.</li>
<li>It gives him a public piece of content with good keywords, which is good for SEO.</li>
<li>If anyone else has the same issue, they may either find this article, or Nathan can just send them a link. Either way, it automates a part of the customer support process, which saves time.</li>
<li>It impressed one person so much they decided to blog about it :)</li>
</ul>


<p> If you are looking for ways to make your customer support more effective and efficient, you could do a lot worse than doing something like this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
