<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pricing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/pricing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-05T10:16:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Used Writing to Double My Freelancing Rate As A Programmer]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/16/how-i-used-writing-to-double-my-freelancing-rate-as-a-programmer/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-16T11:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/16/how-i-used-writing-to-double-my-freelancing-rate-as-a-programmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<script async src="https://static.medium.com/embed.js"></script>


<p><a class="m-story" data-collapsed="true" href="https://medium.com/@gsto/7b321bedecdc">How I Used Writing to Double My Freelancing Rate As A Programmer</a></p>

<!-- more -->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breakdown of a Pricing Grid]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T20:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learn Why is The Middle Plan Always Called The "Best Value"</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/bidsketch_pricing_full.png" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>You may have noticed that on many software as a service pricing pages, they tend to look the same. There are always a few plans, usually 3, and they middle is <strong>always</strong> the most popular. This isn’t an accident. This is all designed to get the maximum value out of a customer. Let’s take a look at one company’s pricing model and why it is effective.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch_pricing_full.png"></p>

<p>I got this table from <a href="http://www.bidsketch.com/pricing/">BidSketch’s pricing page</a>. BidSketch is a tool that helps freelancers and agencies write and send winning proposals. This table is important to BidSketch. Literally every single customer, and therefore every single dollar, comes from this page. Nothing in this table is an accident. Let’s take a look at the plan names:</p>

<h3>Customer Segmentation</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-segmentation.png"></p>

<p>you’ll notice that BidSketch doesn’t call it’s plans “small/medium/large”, or “bronze/silver/gold” or anything generic like that. Instead, they know that they have different kinds of customers, and that those customers are willing to pay different rates. They aim at three of their types of clients: individual freelancers, small studios, and large agencies.</p>

<p>Why do they charge agencies more money? Because agencies get more value out of BidSketch than freelancers. The proposals that large agencies are sending out are an order of magnitude larger than the one a freelancer is sending out.</p>

<p>This is the most important part of pricing any service or product: <strong>when the customer gets more value out of your product or service, you need to be getting more value from that customer.</strong> Doing this aligns your incentives with the customer’s. This means that now you and the customer are a team. Since you make money off of your customer being successful, you will do everything you can to help your customer. Since BidSketch knows that if they help their customers make more money by helping them write better proposals, they are going to do everything they can to make the best proposal tool out there? It’s a win-win for everybody.</p>

<h3>Pricing Ratio</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-pricing.png"></p>

<p>Firstly, you’ll notice that BidSketch put their highest price package first. This is an old-school marketing trick. By looking at the initial plan first, the $79 and $29 plans will feel much cheaper in comparison. The highest selling price plan is almost never the highest selling one, it is mostly their for comparison. This is called <em>price anchoring.</em></p>

<p>You also want to have a decent ratio between your prices. If their prices were $29 / $39 / $49, they aren’t getting much extra value out of the plans. In fact, <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ryandelk/micro-conf-final">Ryan Delk at Gumroad</a> has looked at all the sales of digital products, and has found the optimal ratios for tiered pricing:</p>

<h4><em>1x 2.2x 5x</em></h4>

<p>Where ‘X’ is the base cost of your service. You’ll see that BidSketch follows this ratio closely: $79 = 2.7x , $149 = 5.1x . Note that ratio is just an approximation, and you don’t have to follow it exactly.  <em>(I don’t think BidSketch would get the same revenue with a $29 /  $63.80  / $145 model)</em></p>

<h3>Approximating Value</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/bidsketch-features.png"></p>

<p>I said before that the best way to split up your pricing is to align your values with the customer’s. BidSketch could do this directly if they wanted too, and base their pricing on how the total dollar value of proposals that you close each month (payment processors such as <a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a> and <a href="https://www.braintreepayments.com/">Briaintree</a> have the easiest alignment ever. They just get 2.7% of the revenue you bring in). In other cases, you may not have a way of directly knowing how valuable your service is to a client. In that case, you want to approximate the value. You do this by tying your pricing to something that is correlated to value. BidSketch does this in two ways: the number of users, and the amount of storage. Instead of looking a dollar value, they are looking at three things with these features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Number of employees / contractors you have working for you.</li>
<li>The number of proposals you are sending out.</li>
<li>The quality of proposals you are sending out. (i.e. using more photos &amp; videos, hence more storage)</li>
</ul>


<p>A company that has multiple people (agencies, studios) have to be making payroll, which means they are almost always making more money. That’s why you see a lot of software as a service products segment on number of users. One of the things that has held me back from hiring an assistant is I know the minute I have one employee my monthly software bill would shoot up a few hundred dollars a month.</p>

<p>There are two version control services that software developers use: <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> and <a href="https://bitbucket.org/">BitBucket</a>. A version control service is a place where developers can store and collaborate on code. BitBucket increases prices based number of users, but GitHub prices based on number of projects. I feel like GitHub missed the mark on this pricing. Number of projects is a false approximation of value. For example, BidSketch may only have one project file, for their software service product. I, as a consultant, would have a large number of projects since I work with a number of different clients. Why should I, a self employed consultant, be charged more than a company that pulls in millions of revenue every year?</p>

<h3>Good Artists Borrow, Great Artists Steal</h3>

<p>When it comes to pricing, there is no need to get creative.  There is a reason so many software as a service pricing pages look the same. <strong>Because it works.</strong> Every one would not do it if it wasn’t effective. If I was going to create a product aimed ad freelancers and agencies, I would look at competing and complementary products, and set up a very similar model. I may even use BidSketch’s exact same three tiers. The reason is that if I want to get into this space, BidSketch has done me a <strong>huge</strong> favor:</p>

<h4><em>They have found and validated a price that the market will bear.</em></h4>

<p>Usually finding a working pricing model requires lots of research and experimentation. However, to every one who wants to build a proposal tool, BidSketch has done them a huge favor. Thanks BidSketch! Some times people have a product idea, and get discouraged because it’s “been done”. Competition is not always a bad thing. Competition can be a sign that something works. On the other side of that coin, if you come up with a seemingly obvious idea that no one has done yet, it’s worth pausing for a moment and considering why you are the only person to show up to that particular party.</p>

<p>Pricing models don’t need to be original. They need to be effective at converting sales and maximizing customer value. Save your creativity for your actual product.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Don't bill hourly]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/31/why-i-dont-bill-hourly/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T09:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/31/why-i-dont-bill-hourly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How pricing models affect project outcomes</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post orignally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>Many web developers and designers charge their clients by the hour. We have done that ourselves in the past. But as of 2014 I’ve decided to completely do away with hourly billing. What’s wrong with billing by the hour?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Distracting Overhead</h3>

<p>When billing by the hour, in which I was really billing in 15 minute increments, that meant that time had to be tracked. It also meant that time had to be included on invoices. The problem with this is two fold; Firstly, all the time spent tracking time is time spent not providing value to clients. The second is that it leads to invoicing based on time, which makes the discussion about how long things take instead of how valuable they are. If we build you a web application that saves your company $10,000 a month, I doubt you care if it took an hour, ten hours, or 100 hours to build. All that matters to you is that you made a profitable investment. Hourly billing distracts from focuses on quality and results.</p>

<h3>The Sporadic Schedule</h3>

<p>Scheduling work based on hours can often lead to sporadic schedules. When I billed hourly, I may work for 2 hours in the morning for Client A, then maybe had planned on working for 4 hours for Client B after lunch, but then Client C calls and has an emergency that ends up taking 2 hours. All of this <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/944128/worker-interrupted-cost-task-switching">task switching isn’t free</a>, it’s another issue that harms productivity. Starting in 2014 the smallest unit of time that we bill for is a day.</p>

<h3>The Perverse Incentives</h3>

<p>The biggest reason I have decided to get rid of hourly billing is the perverse incentives that it gives to both clients and developers. As a developer, billing by the hour encourages me to not be efficient, or even worse, punishes me when I am. If I had estimated that a new feature would take 20 hours to implement, and I get it done in 10, does it make sense that I make less?</p>

<p>For clients, I have found that billing hourly leads to clients asking for cut corners and a lower quality of work. For clients, any time spent making a product better now seems worse since it comes with an additional expense.</p>

<h3>My Solution: Flat Rates and Larger Chunks of Time</h3>

<p>I don’t believe there is any one size fits all solution to pricing in the software industry. When it comes to your project, we’ll work with you to find a pricing structure that works for you. Here are some of the options that we offer:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Flat Rate:</strong> This is reserved for small or well defined projects, which tend to be a rare case. We agree on a deliverable, and that deliverable costs $x. I have services that are available to all clients in this manner, such as <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/rome">Rome</a>, my speedy website creation, and <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/flourish/">Flourish</a>, which helps web applications be sustainable and grow post-launch.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Weekly &amp; Monthly Billing:</strong> Weekly &amp; Monthly Billing is the cousin of flat rate billing. Weekly &amp; Monthly billing means that at the end of the agreed upon week or month, we will have a deliverable complete that costs $x. Weekly &amp; Monthly billing is great for projects that need some flexibility in pricing and have a more agile process.
I believe that this new approach will lead to me operating in a more efficient matter, and enable us to provide a higher quality of product to my clients.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Presenting Value]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T16:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When selling clients on your services, how you position yourself is important. You want clients to see you as an investment, not an expense. In order to accomplish this, you need to make sure you are able to clearly state and justify the value you can bring to a client.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Three Types of Value</h3>

<p>There are three primary types of value you can provide to clients, and all of your sales pitches should anchor to one or more of these points:</p>

<ul>
<li>You make your client money.</li>
<li>You save your client time.</li>
<li>You reduce the client's risk.</li>
</ul>


<p>What value <strong>isn't</strong> is things like "writing code" or "designing web pages". These are just tools you are using to accomplish a goal. When you are talking to potential clients you need to be talking about the goal, not the way you are planning on getting there. A client's primary concern is the end result of your work.</p>

<p>You may also notice that saving the client money is absent from this list, even though it sounds like it should be on there. While it's good if you find a way to save a client money, products and services that save money are a much more difficult sale, as people who are focused on reducing cost are looking for ways to <em>not</em> spend money, which makes them a pretty tough sell.</p>

<h2>Making Money</h2>

<p>Presenting value here is the easiest of the three. If you can find a way to peg your work to numbers that affect the bottom line, then focus on that. Let's say you do A/B testing, and you think that your testing could increase conversions by 10%. If you go to a store that makes $100,000 dollars in sales a year, then your services are easily worth $10,000 to them.</p>

<h2>Saving Time</h2>

<p>This is the one I find myself talking about often, since I work in software development, and love finding ways to automate processes. I've called myself a "Job Destroyer" before. Saving a client (or a client's employees) time can easily be tied to money as well. I doubt a client would willingly share an employee's salary with you, but you can make an educated guess as to the cost of an employee:</p>

<ul>
<li>First, get an estimated salary. You can just guess, or use a service like <a href="http://www.glassdoor.com">glassdoor</a> to approximate the number. In this example, let's say that an employee has a salary of $50,000.</li>
<li>Secondly, we are going <a href="http://web.mit.edu/e-club/hadzima/how-much-does-an-employee-cost.html">multiply that number by 2.7</a>. This is to factor in all of the other costs of that employee. Now we have an employee that costs $135,000 a year.</li>
<li>Now, let's break that down into an hourly rate. The easiest calculation would be to say salary / 2000, or 50 weeks at 40 hours per week. However, I feel like 1500 may be a better estimate if we want to go by <strong>productive</strong> time, since I don't believe anyone is truly and consistently productive for eight hours a day. between those two numbers, we have an hourly range of value of $67.50 - $90.</li>
</ul>


<p>Going by this formula, if you are able to make a 2 hour job take little or no time, then over the course of a year software that could do that would provide up to $9,000 a year in value. If you can scale that to 10 employees, then it's $90,000. This is why being able to save time is so valuable to clients.</p>

<h2>Reducing Risk</h2>

<p>Reducing risk is the most abstract of the three, and can be harder to pin an exact number on. Software projects are inherently risky, and anything you can do to reduce that risk is valuable to the client. You see this in consumer sales all the time money back guarantees. By making that guarantee, the product is more valuable since you know that if you are not satisfied you can get your money back.</p>

<p>As a consultant, there are several ways I show that I can reduce risk to clients:</p>

<ul>
<li>Sending clients weekly reports and/or having weekly meetings, So they are always aware of where the project stands. Freelance web developers and designers have a reputation for being flaky, so this helps address that.</li>
<li>Having a set development process in place. This way clients know that I have a more predictable process with more predictable results.</li>
<li>Having a network of other talented people, and letting the client know that if there is something outside of my scope of skills I can bring someone on to help out with the task.</li>
</ul>


<p>Things like having a portfolio and client testimonials are other ways of reducing risk in the eyes of clients. These send the message that other people have worked with before, gotten results, and are satisfied.</p>

<p>However, these all address the reduction of risk in the process, not in the end result. There are several ways this can be accomplished as well. A couple of examples are doing market and competitor research, to see what the project is facing and making sure it is framed appropriately. Another that I am a big fan of is getting to market earlier and iterating quickly. This allows you to work with real people and gather real data. Any decisions made before launch are in many ways an educated guess, and solutions and plans built on objective data instead of guesses will always have a higher chance of succeeding.</p>

<p>Framing your work in this fashion can help both yourself and your clients. It can help you by not only seeing how to present value, but help you find new ways to provide more value to clients when you work as well. This can also help you land more sales and stand out from the competition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to bill Daily or Weekly]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T16:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/calendar.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When it comes to freelancing, you may think you only have two options when it comes to how you bill your clients: You can bill by the hour, or you can bill by the project. But these aren't your only options, and in many cases they are not your best ones.</p>

<p>Two alternatives to this is billing by the day, or billing by the week. These billing structures are a little more uncommon, but in my experience as a consultant, they have been the most effective and productive. Since these structures are a little bit different, they often require a little bit of explanation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What's In A Day?</h3>

<p>An hour is a definite measure of time. it's 60 minutes. When you bill a client for a hour, they expect to be providing value during those 60 minutes. A day is also a definite measure of time, but if you bill a client for a day they don't expect 24 hours of productivity from you.</p>

<p>You make think that a work day of 8 hours is a more reasonable assumption, but that also isn't the case. Many studies have shown that creative workers are only productive for <a href="http://qz.com/157092/the-case-for-a-six-hour-workday/">5 to 6 hours a day</a>, and that increased hours can in fact lead to decreased productivity. So when it comes to billing by the day, it just means whatever you think a good day's work means to you. It doesn't mean that it has to be all of your time, or that if you bill for a day you can't do any other productive work for another client.</p>

<p>If you have been working in freelancing or consulting and have been keeping track of your hours, you can use that data to determine your day rate.</p>

<h3>Weekly Billing and Deadlines</h3>

<p>Weekly billing tends to work a little bit differently. When you bill by the week, you do so with a goal and a deliverable for the week. Weekly billing is in a way like billing a flat project rate, but you are delivering smaller projects in a smaller time frame.</p>

<p>Weekly billing may seem strange at first, but if you think about it, this is how salaried employees basically work.</p>

<p>With my clients, I set milestones every two weeks, and tell them that I will deliver on those milestones in the time frame. It doesn't matter if I am working 30 hours a week, or 40, or 60, or 5. As long as the results and value are delivered, that is what counts.</p>

<p>The other thing I like about weekly billing is that it makes scheduling my availability much simpler. I can look at my calendar, see that I have worked booked for the next 6 weeks, and have a clear date for when I am available for more work.</p>

<h3>How to Decide on a Pricing Model</h3>

<p>I don't think that any consultant should stick to just one pricing structure, unless you work on a narrow type of project. Different projects and different clients will work better with different billing structures. Here is when I would consider each one:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Hourly Billing:</strong> For jobs where the scope is unknown and flexibility is needed.</li>
<li><strong>Flat Rate Billing:</strong> When the scope of a project can be well defined and the project is small.</li>
<li><strong>Daily Billing:</strong> Works well for one day consulting arrangements, and also for projects that you want to commit to part time (such as 2 - 3 days per week)</li>
<li><strong>Weekly Billing:</strong> My personal favorite. Tends to work well on larger projects, and projects that need flexibility and aren't committed to a hard scope.</li>
</ul>


<p>By thinking about how you price and position your services, you can come up with plans that can make your scheduling better, and help you price your services more aggressively.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT:</strong> Just found this episode of The Freelancer's Show where they discuss <a href="http://www.freelancersshow.com/the-freelancers-show-097-weekly-billing/">weekly billing</a>, Worth a listen if you want to hear more about this subject.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
