<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reverie | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/reverie/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-10T14:05:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned From Thomas Edison's Factory Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T08:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Edison Understood Resiliance AND Electricity</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/edison_fire.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>On December 10th, 1914, Thomas Edison was having dinner with his family. A man rushes to his door and tells Edison that his factory had caught fire. Edison grabs his son Charles and they rush our the door. They head to the factory to see what is going on. When they get there the see a  vivid display of red, green, and blue fires, due to the various chemicals stored in his laboratory.</p>

<p>This could be the end of Thomas Edison. He didn't even have insurance on the building, because it was designed to be fireproof. Edison looks at his son and says:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Go get your mother and all her friends. They'll never see a fire like this again.</p></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Charles protested, to which Edison responded:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's all right. We've just got rid of a lot of old rubbish.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>How was Edison able to look at a career threatening tragedy and take such a light hearted approach to such a catastrophe? Edison understood the philosophy of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism">Stoicism</a>. Stoicism tells us that negative and destructive emotions are the result of errors in judgement.</p>

<h3>The Obstacle is The Way</h3>

<p>The principal teaching of Stoicism is that we should view challenges and stress as opportunities. Instead of seeing the factory as a catastrophic blow to his business, Edison saw an opportunity to start anew. If you are an entrepreneur, you <strong>need</strong> to get comfortable with failure.</p>

<h3>Facing Failure Head On</h3>

<p>Sometimes there will be failures that are your fault, other times they are not. There may be circumstances that you couldn't foresee or plan for. The world is chaotic, and it doesn't owe you anything; it was here first.</p>

<p>You can't let the control of how you react to these scenarios slip from your grasp. Every time you see crisis, you have to try and see opportunity.</p>

<h3>A Personal Story</h3>

<p>Many freelancer's are familiar with the term "feast or famine". It alludes to the fact that with client work, when it rains, it pours. Sometimes lots of sales come through at once, other times they don't. It can be stressful when work is slow. I had been feeling depressed and unmotivated for days facing a recent sales slump. However, by applying the philosophy of stoicism, I can see this in a very different light:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/time_enough.jpg"></p>

<h4>Time Enough At Last</h4>

<p>People often complain about not having enough time to accomplish everything they want. I know I have. That's no longer an excuse. I have a lot of hours to fill up every day with whatever I so choose.</p>

<h4>Going Completely Remote</h4>

<p>A big goal I have for my consulting business is to build a system that is completely remote. While networking locally tends to be the most effective way to build connections, and will always be a part of my business strategy, it can be limiting. The internet opens up the whole wide world, and I would like to build connections with people that live more than 20 miles away from me.</p>

<p>This will give me the freedom to run my business from anywhere in country. Hell, anywhere in the world. This is <strong>huge</strong> not as a business goal, but as a goal for living a happy life.</p>

<h4>A Through Post Mortem</h4>

<p>What have I done right? What I have done wrong? Having all this time gives me an opportunity to look at every part of my business, from marketing, to sales, to deliverables, and see what has gone well, and what hasn't. I'm taking all this free time I have and applying to finding ways to deliver better service and more value to my clients, while building a more sustainable business for myself.</p>

<h4>A Learning Experience</h4>

<p>I have been working on a book this year entitled <em>Professional Freelance</em>. I planned on including chapters on sales and marketing. By having a challenge that many other freelancers face every day gives me an chance to find ways to approach it, learn and invent new solutions, and gather knowledge that I can share with other people and help other people grow their career.</p>

<h3>The Struggle Isn't Real</h3>

<p>When facing hardships, it's good to be reminded that they aren't as bad as they first seem, if we approach them in the correct fashion. What did Edison do after his watched his plant burn to the ground in a spectacular fashion? He got a loan from his friend Henry Ford, and in three weeks he was up and running again. Edison went on to make $10 million dollars in revenue that year (~$200 million in 2014 dollars).</p>

<p>I'll leave you with a video on Stoic Optimism, a TEDx talk by Ryan Holiday:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/e2Zq2VWvmW4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Essentialism Through The Ages]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/10/essentialism-through-the-ages/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/10/essentialism-through-the-ages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Single Philosophy That Drives Artists, Designers, and Entrepreneurs</h3>

<p><img src="/images/articles/simple_long.jpg"></p>

<p>In design, I've always been a fan of minimalism. Minimalism is a philosophy about boiling things down to their essential elements. It's about having a philosophy of "less but better". Great thinkers from all walks of life have touted the benefits of this kind of approach:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><blockquote><p>Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication</p><footer><strong>Leonard Da Vinci</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Everything should be made as simple as possible, but not simpler.</p><footer><strong>Albert Einstein</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Simplicity is the final achievement. After one has played a vast quantity of notes and more notes, it is simplicity that emerges as the crowning reward of art.</p><footer><strong>Fredric Chopin</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Any intelligent fool can make things bigger, more complex, and more violent. It takes a touch of genius – and a lot of courage – to move in the opposite direction.</p><footer><strong>E.F. Schumacher</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Simple can be harder than complex: You have to work hard to get your thinking clean to make it simple. But it's worth it in the end because once you get there, you can move mountains.</p><footer><strong>Steve Jobs</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>There is a universal truth that drives all of these musicians, artists, and visionaries. They all speak of the beauty and elegance of simplicity in all things. As entrepreneurs, we have the power to design not only our businesses, but our entire lives. However, many people end up working long hours, taking on lots of stress, and doing physical and mental harm to ourselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Say No To Entreporn]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/say-no-to-entreporn/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T20:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/say-no-to-entreporn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Reading HackerNews is More Harmful Than You Think</h3>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>There is an insidious type of content out there on the internet, that is easy to waste time on. It’s what I call “entreporn”, and it isn’t only a waste of time to people, it is actively <strong>harmful</strong> to aspiring entrepreneurs.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What is Entreporn?</h3>

<p>I define entrepornography as any article that focuses on start-ups that have had some kind of crazy, fluke amount of success. Reading about snapchat was offered $3 billion dollars by Facebook but had the guts to say no. Some college kid built a web app and made $20,000 in sales while he was passed out from a bender. At least 60% of whatever is on the front page of Hacker News whenever you read this post. These pieces are salacious and exciting. They get us to imagine a world where we can take an idea all the way to top and create a hugely successful venture. It’s truely the american dream!</p>

<h3>What's the Problem</h3>

<p>The problem is that the stories they like to tell are flukes. It inspires people who want to be “The next Facebook”. The problem is that no one is going to be the next Facebook. No one is going to have the same conditions that Mark Zuckerburg did. Even if they did, any company requires a lot of luck, especially to get to the place Facebook is at today. And besides, I never understood why Twitter didn’t get to take “The next Facebook”  crown and keep it.</p>

<p>These articles can’t teach you anything, because they tell stories of companies that aren’t repeatable. I’m not asking that you stop reading articles on the internet, because it would make me quite the hypocritical writer. But also because there is a ton of good, valuable advice out there you could be reading instead.</p>

<h3>Why It's Harmful</h3>

<p>However, the time wasting is not the worst part about this. As I said, I consider entreporn <strong>harmful</strong>. It’s toxic. It, much like regular pornography, gives inexperienced people a skewed view of what reality is like. Entreporn gives people the idea that they can pursue any idea, and hit it big. It gives people the impressions that start ups are like the lottery, except that they are willing to buy a single ticket with thousands of dollars and years of their life.</p>

<p>I don’t want to discourage anyone from being an entrepreneur, in fact I would encourage anyone interested to learn more about it. However, I would encourage these people to learn how to be an entrepreneur in <em>the real world</em>, not the fantasy land that TechCrunch likes to paint. Very few people can build “The next Facebook”, but a <strong>whole lot</strong> of people can build a sustainable, profitable business. and reading these vain articles is actively preventing people from doing so.</p>

<p>I don’t want to read about the guy who got 10,000 subscribers in a weekend. I’ll never be that guy. I want to read about the guy that got 100 and how he did it. That’s educational. That’s actionable. That’s <strong>real</strong>. Startups are not exempt from the being businesses, and the rules of business that have existed for hundreds of years still apply. By learning about how to build your business realistically, you have a much lower risk and higher chance of success.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning To Say No]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/no.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I just looked in the mirror. I had several more gray hairs in my beard than I had before. I had taken on more client work than I could handle, and had been working long nights and weekends. I knew I was tired and stressed, but it was a real wake up call to see the physical effects of burnout, in addition to the mental. It was at that moment I realized something had to change with how I was managing my business. If you are a freelancer, You have to learn how to say no. Your business, just like a product, is going to be designed. If you don't carefully, mindfully design your own business, then other people will do it for you. And they won't have your best interest at heart.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>The Overworked Freelancer</h3>

<p>It's a common story: The freelancer who is working long hours into the night and on weekends. As freelancers, we should be in control. Why do people who are in charge of their own career and lifestyle decide to do such stressful, harmful things to themselves? Taking on too many responsibilities is not just harmful to ourselves, it's harmful to the quality of our work and our relationships with clients, which is the backbone of our business.</p>

<p>It seems counter intuitive, but by doing so much we are getting so much less done. By taking on <em>less</em> work, we are able to provide a better customer experience and deliver better work.</p>

<h3>Fear of Famine</h3>

<p>The reason that most people say yes to any job, no matter the circumstance, is that they are afraid of where the next one will come from. People will take on a job that is detrimental to their career because they are afraid of not having any client work at all. The issue is that again, the most intuitive solution is not the most effective one. If you spent the same number of hours you work you would spend on a toxic client defining and look for clients you like, you could easily get enough work to sustain yourself, and feel a lot better about your work.</p>

<h3>Saying no to Toxic Clients</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, your clients ARE your business. As such, you need to be selective as to whom you allow into your business. Toxic clients are clients that are a drain on your time, and your resources, while providing little in return. If you have clients like this, I would suggest you fire them immediately. Take the time that you would have spent working with them and start spending it finding better clients. I would also work on setting up a qualification process for your potential clients, so that you can prevent toxic clients from meeting with you in the first place. I send out a standard email with a few questions to potential clients, and if they don't have a good budget, or the project seems like something I would not be interested in, Then I politely decline. If they seem like good clients who are just not a good fir for myself in particular, I will pass them along to another one of my contacts who may be a better fit. By doing this, I have more time to spend on client work that I love.</p>

<h3>How to Say No</h3>

<p>It may feel like saying 'No' is rude in a lot of circumstances, but that, much like the fear of famine, is a fear that can reasoned away. If you don't want to take something on, then you can simply say that you are busy or that you don't have the bandwidth for it. If it is a client, then saying "We wouldn't be a good fit" is a magic phrase that gets you out of most engagements. When dealing with no-longer-potential clients, always take the blame on yourself if you can, it will make your rejection much more palpable.</p>

<p>Some people may resent you, but even more will respect you. It shows that your time is valuable and that you won't just give it up to anyone for any reason. It also allows you to play a little "hard to get" with clients, which makes you seem more valuable in their eyes.</p>

<h3>HELL YES or No</h3>

<p>Derek Sivers summed this up perfectly: You should say <a href="http://sivers.org/hellyeah">"Hell YEAH! or No"</a> to any opportunities you are provided. If something doesn't excite you, if a commitment on your time or energy is a maybe in your mind, then you need to say no. It feels good to say yes to people, but this is what leads to feeling too busy, and too stressed. You have to start saying no more often to escape.</p>

<p>But by saying no to these things, we are enabling ourselves to say "Yes" to things we <strong>really</strong> love. Here is a chart from a new book called <a href="http://gregmckeown.com/essentialism-the-disciplined-pursuit-of-less/">"Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less"</a> That sums this philosophy up perfectly. Instead of sending our energy out in a hundred directions, and feeling like we aren't making any progress, By eliminating the nonessential we can focus our energy in a direction that really matters.</p>

<p><img src="/images/essentialism.jpg"></p>

<p>It can be scary, but once you get used to it, the feeling of saying no is incredibly freeing.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Letting Go Of Money Made me More of It]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/14/how-letting-go-of-money-made-me-more-of-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-14T18:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/14/how-letting-go-of-money-made-me-more-of-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><strong>Note:</strong> This Story was originally <a href="https://medium.com/p/6c9c9f08b552/">posted on Medium on October 21, 2013</a>. But since Medium just added a new tool for <a href="https://medium.com/help-center/3eaed64aed8a">Embedding Posts on your own site</a>, I wanted to try it out.</em></p>

<script async src="https://static.medium.com/embed.js"></script>


<p><a class="m-story" data-collapsed="false" href="https://medium.com/p/6c9c9f08b552">How Letting Go of Money Made me More of It</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
