<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-31T09:43:08-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Don't bill hourly]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/31/why-i-dont-bill-hourly/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T09:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/31/why-i-dont-bill-hourly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How pricing models affect project outcomes</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>Many web developers and designers charge their clients by the hour. We have done that ourselves in the past. But as of 2014 I’ve decided to completely do away with hourly billing. What’s wrong with billing by the hour?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Distracting Overhead</h3>

<p>When billing by the hour, in which I was really billing in 15 minute increments, that meant that time had to be tracked. It also meant that time had to be included on invoices. The problem with this is two fold; Firstly, all the time spent tracking time is time spent not providing value to clients. The second is that it leads to invoicing based on time, which makes the discussion about how long things take instead of how valuable they are. If we build you a web application that saves your company $10,000 a month, I doubt you care if it took an hour, ten hours, or 100 hours to build. All that matters to you is that you made a profitable investment. Hourly billing distracts from focuses on quality and results.</p>

<h3>The Sporadic Schedule</h3>

<p>Scheduling work based on hours can often lead to sporadic schedules. When I billed hourly, I may work for 2 hours in the morning for Client A, then maybe had planned on working for 4 hours for Client B after lunch, but then Client C calls and has an emergency that ends up taking 2 hours. All of this <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/944128/worker-interrupted-cost-task-switching">task switching isn’t free</a>, it’s another issue that harms productivity. Starting in 2014 the smallest unit of time that we bill for is a day.</p>

<h3>The Perverse Incentives</h3>

<p>The biggest reason I have decided to get rid of hourly billing is the perverse incentives that it gives to both clients and developers. As a developer, billing by the hour encourages me to not be efficient, or even worse, punishes me when I am. If I had estimated that a new feature would take 20 hours to implement, and I get it done in 10, does it make sense that I make less?</p>

<p>For clients, I have found that billing hourly leads to clients asking for cut corners and a lower quality of work. For clients, any time spent making a product better now seems worse since it comes with an additional expense.</p>

<h3>My Solution: Flat Rates and Larger Chunks of Time</h3>

<p>I don’t believe there is any one size fits all solution to pricing in the software industry. When it comes to your project, we’ll work with you to find a pricing structure that works for you. Here are some of the options that we offer:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Flat Rate:</strong> This is reserved for small or well defined projects, which tend to be a rare case. We agree on a deliverable, and that deliverable costs $x. I have services that are available to all clients in this manner, such as <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/rome">Rome</a>, my speedy website creation, and <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/flourish/">Flourish</a>, which helps web applications be sustainable and grow post-launch.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Weekly &amp; Monthly Billing:</strong> Weekly &amp; Monthly Billing is the cousin of flat rate billing. Weekly &amp; Monthly billing means that at the end of the agreed upon week or month, we will have a deliverable complete that costs $x. Weekly &amp; Monthly billing is great for projects that need some flexibility in pricing and have a more agile process.
I believe that this new approach will lead to me operating in a more efficient matter, and enable us to provide a higher quality of product to my clients.</p></li>
</ul>


<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AARRR! Pirate Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/30/aarrr-pirate-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/30/aarrr-pirate-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How to Track the 5 Numbers That Define Your Company&#8217;s Success</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/pirate.png" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post orignally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>Pirate Metrics refers to an the acronym ‘AARRR’, which stands for five metrics used to track the performance of your business online. The five metrics are Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Referrals, and Revenue. By tracking these metrics, you can get a clearer picture of the health of your business, and figure out where you should focus your efforts. The idea was popularized by <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dmc500hats/startup-metrics-for-pirates-long-version">Dave McClure</a>. These ideas are a framework for how to approach your online business and all of them won’t apply to everyone. Today I’d like to give you an overview of what they are, how to track them, and some ideas on how to improve your performance in each. I hope this will get the gears turning on how to apply them to your business.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both'></div>


<h3>Acquisition</h3>

<p>Acquisition is how many visits you are getting to your site. This is getting people to be aware of your existence, and giving you a chance to sell them on your product.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> Website visits are the easiest thing to track when it comes to your website. Tools like <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics">Google Analytics</a> make this simple.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> How to increase your traffic could vary greatly depending on the type of site you have. Online advertising like Google Adwords, or on networks like Facebook or Reddit, are a direct way to get traffic. You can also try longer term strategies such as SEO and content marketing.</p>

<h3>Activation</h3>

<p>Activation is getting people to complete a call-to-action. This could mean making a sale, or getting users to sign up for a subscription services. It could even be just collecting an email address. In our case, we consider an activation someone using the contact form to get in touch with us and start a conversation. Sometimes it’s as simple as collecting an email address.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> Depends. most e-commerce services have ways of tracking sales, as do most CMSes. For collecting emails for newsletters, tools like Mailchimp have this built in as well.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> Split testing is a good strategy here. On whatever pages you are trying to get people to sign up, test the copy, the style, your call to action, everything.</p>

<h3>Retention</h3>

<p>Retention refers to tracking that people who have become your customer stay your customer. If you have a subscription service, you don’t want people to cancel. If you are making sales, you want people to be repeat customers.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> If you working with customers monthly, you can track how many stay for a certain amount of time, such as 6 months. For sales, you could track how many customers are repeat customers and how often they return. Another approach would be to track the frequency in which people use your service, such as monitoring how often people log in.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> The two biggest factors are the ease of use of your application and customer service. Retention relies on you keeping existing customers happy. Being responsive, testing your interface, and listening to feedback are all good ways to increase retention.</p>

<h3>Referrals</h3>

<p>Word of mouth is the most valuable form of marketing you have. Tracking referrals can give you insight into customer happiness.</p>

<p><strong>How To Track It:</strong> Social Media has made this easier. You can track how many people are mentioning you or your domain on Twitter. Be sure to interact back as well.</p>

<p><strong>How To Improve It:</strong> Make it easy for your clients to talk about you. Give them a clear message, and be sure to make sure to provide links to easily share your content.</p>

<h3>Revenue</h3>

<p>The one everyone cares about and the most explicit one. How much money you are pulling in.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> With your bank account.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> This one is harder to improve on it’s own. It’s usually a result of working on the four above. You can try things like experimenting with your pricing model and service offerings.</p>

<p>All of these metrics will help one another, and usually aren’t in a vacuum. For example, Most things that increase retention will tend to increase referrals. Increasing referrals will increase acquisition. Increasing acquisition can increase activation, which can increase revenue, and so on. If you’d like to talk more about this and want some help with getting these numbers up for your business, or even just finding better ways to track them, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">Let’s talk about it</a>.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I am Killing My Company Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T11:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Personal vs. Professional Blogging, Part II</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/concordant-articles.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Back in March, I wrote and article, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/">Personal vs. Professional Blogging</a>. In that article I explained why I decided to publish my writing on  two blogs: <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com">glennstovall.com</a>, Where I planned on writing content aimed at fellow developers and freelancers. The other site was <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com/articles">Concordant Solutions</a> My &#8220;company brand&#8221; (<em>ugh</em>, I will never be comfortable with that phrase) where I aimed to write content I thought clients would enjoy. That hasn&#8217;t worked. Here is why, and how I plan to fix.</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>No One Connects With a Company</h3>

<p>Unless you are a large company with a lot of authority, Most people aren&#8217;t going to be interested in your company blog. <a href="http://blog.kissmetrics.com/">KISSMetrics</a> is an exception to this rule. People would rather read an article by &#8220;Glenn&#8221;, than by &#8220;Concordant Solutions&#8221;. The second comes across as less authentic.</p>

<h3>It&#8217;s Easier to Manage One Thing Instead of Two</h3>

<p>It&#8217;s better to update blogs regularly. By having two blogs maintaining consistency is twice as hard. It also added mental overhead to every article that I wanted to write, since I had to decide where it would go, and what audience I would try to appeal to. Instead, now I can have one content management system, and one stream of content that is more steady. There were even a couple of situations where I tried to spin content so I could post it twice, which was a waste of time.</p>

<h3>It Helps SEO (At Least I&#8217;m Pretty Sure)</h3>

<p>I&#8217;m not an SEO Guru. Beyond &#8220;Content is king&#8221;, &#8220;Have a good title tag&#8221;, &#8220;No one uses the <code>&lt;meta name='keywords'&gt;</code> tag anymore, I know nothing. This is just from anecdotal observation. This domain has been around longer, gotten more traffic, and had more back links. <em>Anything</em> I publish here does better than anything I have published on my company domain. Viral traffic seems to work like high tide coming in: There is a wave of traffic that comes in quickly, and leaves just as fast. But once it is gone, It leaves the average daily visitors mark a little higher than it found it. Google must think this domain has <em>some</em> value. Why squander it?</p>

<h3>There is More Crossover Appeal Than I Originally Thought</h3>

<p>Most of my clients are small businesses or tech companies, which is not as different of an audience as I thought. Freelancers are by definition also small business owners (even if they don&#8217;t see themselves that way). And people at tech companies in a position to hire me often have a technical background. I said that they might not know what <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/">AngularJS</a> is, but that is not always the case. I can still write content aimed at a subset of my audience, but there is no reason to have two locations to do so.</p>

<h3>At The End of The Day, The Company Blog Was a Failure</h3>

<p>I&#8217;ve maintained <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a> for a year, and I am not afraid to admit that as a marketing tool, it has been a failure. I will say that as a <em>sales</em> tool, It has done some good work. The difference is that while that domain and the content on it has not brought me any new leads, it has been a great tool to help turn leads into clients. Potential clients are usually not going to find your portfolio by googling for it; They are going to see your portfolio because they said &#8220;can I see your portfolio?&#8221; and you mailed them a link.</p>

<p>My company site will still exist for that reason. Any content on there I still deem worthwhile is going to be ported over to this domain over the next couple weeks. The company site  will be a resource for past, present, and future clients. I still intend on it being a valuable sales tool. It just won&#8217;t have an articles section any longer.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Turn Your Services into Products]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/14/how-to-turn-your-services-into-products/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T12:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/14/how-to-turn-your-services-into-products</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I wanted to talk to you about the idea of &#8220;productized consulting&#8221;. Productized can give you a way to package your services in a way that is easier to sell and can be scalable. Here&#8217;s a quick run down of how it works:</p>

<ul>
<li>Take a service you have provided to clients in the past.</li>
<li>Define a fixed scope and price for that service.</li>
<li>Sell that service like you would a physical product or monthly subscription.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://wptheory.net">WPTheory</a> is a good example. Adam Clark  chooses a WordPress theme, install it, customize it, and put up content, in one day. He sells this package for $999. It could be difficult to convince clients to pay you a $1,000 day rate, but by positioning it this way,  Adam is able to do this frequently.</p>

<p>While $1,000/day would be nice, what if you could charge $1,000 <strong>an hour</strong>? That&#8217;s what Joanna Weibe did with their consulting product, <a href="http://copyhackers.com/product/formal-website-copy-review-with-joanna-wiebe/">The no fluff website review</a>. Joanna sends over a 60 minute video about your website, and charges you $997 for the privilege.</p>

<p>Something else that makes Joanna&#8217;s example is that while she is still providing a service, she has turned that service into a more tangible deliverable. Instead of just telling the client the changes or writing them a list, she gives them a meeting, a video, and several usable copy writing samples they can use. You can make a lot of services and meetings more valuable to the client by attaching some form of report or usable item as part of it.</p>

<p>I hope this gets the gears turning for you for some new ways to position your services. I thought about writing up a list of more examples of freelancing as a service, but it turns out the guys at Workshop already did it, and they <a href="http://letsworkshop.com/freelance-as-a-service/">knocked it out of the park</a>.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Self Publisher's Journey]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/06/the-self-publishers-journey/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-06T14:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/06/the-self-publishers-journey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/cover.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>I&#8217;m working on self publishing and eBook in the coming months, and I wanted to document my journey and share it with you. I have enjoyed and been inspired by other writings such as <a href="http://groovehq.com/blog">Alex Turnbull documenting his ongoing journey to get to $100,000 recurring revenue</a>, and Nathan Barry&#8217;s <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/category/the-web-app-challenge/">&#8220;Web App in Six Months Challenge&#8221;</a>. There is nothing like publicly sharing your techniques and struggles in order to both share useful information with other people, and to keep myself accountable.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Story So Far</h3>

<p>I think a lot of freelancers dream of finding ways to make money besides charging for their time. It could be by setting up recurring revenue, productizing their consulting services, or building a product they can sell individually. I decided to try what many before me have, and build a product. Heck, there is an <a href="http://chasingproduct.com">entire podcast</a> dedicated to the subject (which is really good, by the way).</p>

<p>Being a web developer, of course my first thought was to build some form of SaaS application. Enough reading on the internet scared me off of that idea (for now): SaaS applications on average take two years before they bring in enough income to stand on their own, and I know from experience they can take months to develop. I had started a couple of ideas, but could never find the time to finish them. Then I found an article by Amy Hoy called <a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/why-you-should-do-a-tiny-product-first">&#8220;Why you should build a tiny product first&#8221;</a> and it really resonated with me. It got me thinking about products that I could complete in 90 days or less. I liked writing, and based on several freelance sites I had read before, I knew that there was a lot of interest in starting to freelance, but a lot of people didn&#8217;t know where to begin.</p>

<p>The tiny idea was also appealing because it would be a straight up easier way to launch a product. I have worked with enough small businesses and start-ups to know that launching a new business or product is <strong>hard</strong>. Really, REALLY hard. There is no reason to tackle new business ventures on hard mode, and I feel that if there is anything you can do to make things easier on yourself, you should do it. And it is much easier to write a book than build a piece of software, and it is a lot easier to convince someone to pay you $29 once instead of $29/month indefinitely.</p>

<h3>The Freelance Start-up Guide</h3>

<p>It was at this point, around the start of this year,  I decided to work on a book, then titled <strong>The Freelance Start-up Guide</strong>. It was going to be aimed at aspiring freelancers, and help them build a product from scratch. I started writing the book, and set up a mailing list. Initial response was a bit tepid on the mailing list, but there was some interest in the idea.</p>

<h3>The First Big Hurdle</h3>

<p>Around the start of February, I had a huge rush of client work, admittedly, more than I could handle. I knew something had to give, and I informed my tiny mailing list that I had shelved the project indefinitely. I knew at that time that I did not have any extra bandwidth, and had to cut work where ever I could.</p>

<h3>The Real Tiniest Product</h3>

<p>About a month ago, I decided to give building a mailing list a second try. I figured that I could build an audience before I built the product. Even if I didn&#8217;t finish that book, I would still have an audience, and that had value. I signed up for Nathan Barry&#8217;s <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a>, and during his ConvertKit academy, he gave me a valuable piece of advice: You can get a lot more email list subscriptions if you give users an incentive for signing up. I compiled some of my past blog articles, wrote some new content, and released <em><a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">The Freelance Pricing Handbook</a></em>. This is a small, 32 page eBook that I gave away for free. I was able to grow my list from 15 to 100 subscribers overnight. You can read my case study on it&#8217;s release here.</p>

<p>This so far has been the best move I&#8217;ve made. I always liked blogging, but it had been directionless before. Now instead of people reading my article, and that bringing me no value, I could capture readers and have a way to continue engaging with them. This meant that every post I had written in the past and every post I would write in the future was more valuable. Now they weren&#8217;t just articles, they were sales tools.</p>

<h3>Version 2.0: Bootstrap Freelance</h3>

<p>Now it&#8217;s June, and my client work has returned to levels where I don&#8217;t feel completely underwater. I decided that I wanted to pick up the project and continue working on it. At this point, I had almost 65 pages written, and an email list with a couple of hundred people on it, and I didn&#8217;t want to throw all of this away. I renamed the product <em>Bootstrap Freelance</em> and decided to pick the project back up. I decided that instead of just telling people how to get their first client, I wanted to add more content based on lessons I had learned on how to build up their business after that. I&#8217;m nervous about announcing a launch date based on what happened last time, but I am shooting for a release date sometime in August.</p>

<h3>&#8230;And Here We Are</h3>

<p>Now I have roughly 80 pages of a first draft, which is about 2/3rds of what I want it to be. I am working on spending more time working not only on the book, but on marketing before that. For example, setting up a landing page for the product, and starting to public write about the progress of the book. I plan on updating this blog with information about the process, along with helpful information from the book. I am also going to send updates every single Friday to anyone who wants to help me accountable. If you&#8217;d like to keep up with the progress on the book, enter your email address below:</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/588.js?orient=vert"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning To Say No]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/no.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I just looked in the mirror. I had several more gray hairs in my beard than I had before. I had taken on more client work than I could handle, and had been working long nights and weekends. I knew I was tired and stressed, but it was a real wake up call to see the physical effects of burnout, in addition to the mental. It was at that moment I realized something had to change with how I was managing my business. If you are a freelancer, You have to learn how to say no. Your business, just like a product, is going to be designed. If you don&#8217;t carefully, mindfully design your own business, then other people will do it for you. And they won&#8217;t have your best interest at heart.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>The Overworked Freelancer</h3>

<p>It&#8217;s a common story: The freelancer who is working long hours into the night and on weekends. As freelancers, we should be in control. Why do people who are in charge of their own career and lifestyle decide to do such stressful, harmful things to themselves? Taking on too many responsibilities is not just harmful to ourselves, it&#8217;s harmful to the quality of our work and our relationships with clients, which is the backbone of our business.</p>

<p>It seems counter intuitive, but by doing so much we are getting so much less done. By taking on <em>less</em> work, we are able to provide a better customer experience and deliver better work.</p>

<h3>Fear of Famine</h3>

<p>The reason that most people say yes to any job, no matter the circumstance, is that they are afraid of where the next one will come from. People will take on a job that is detrimental to their career because they are afraid of not having any client work at all. The issue is that again, the most intuitive solution is not the most effective one. If you spent the same number of hours you work you would spend on a toxic client defining and look for clients you like, you could easily get enough work to sustain yourself, and feel a lot better about your work.</p>

<h3>Saying no to Toxic Clients</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, your clients ARE your business. As such, you need to be selective as to whom you allow into your business. Toxic clients are clients that are a drain on your time, and your resources, while providing little in return. If you have clients like this, I would suggest you fire them immediately. Take the time that you would have spent working with them and start spending it finding better clients. I would also work on setting up a qualification process for your potential clients, so that you can prevent toxic clients from meeting with you in the first place. I send out a standard email with a few questions to potential clients, and if they don&#8217;t have a good budget, or the project seems like something I would not be interested in, Then I politely decline. If they seem like good clients who are just not a good fir for myself in particular, I will pass them along to another one of my contacts who may be a better fit. By doing this, I have more time to spend on client work that I love.</p>

<h3>How to Say No</h3>

<p>It may feel like saying &#8216;No&#8217; is rude in a lot of circumstances, but that, much like the fear of famine, is a fear that can reasoned away. If you don&#8217;t want to take something on, then you can simply say that you are busy or that you don&#8217;t have the bandwidth for it. If it is a client, then saying &#8220;We wouldn&#8217;t be a good fit&#8221; is a magic phrase that gets you out of most engagements. When dealing with no-longer-potential clients, always take the blame on yourself if you can, it will make your rejection much more palpable.</p>

<p>Some people may resent you, but even more will respect you. It shows that your time is valuable and that you won&#8217;t just give it up to anyone for any reason. It also allows you to play a little &#8220;hard to get&#8221; with clients, which makes you seem more valuable in their eyes.</p>

<h3>HELL YES or No</h3>

<p>Derek Sivers summed this up perfectly: You should say <a href="http://sivers.org/hellyeah">&#8220;Hell YEAH! or No&#8221;</a> to any opportunities you are provided. If something doesn&#8217;t excite you, if a commitment on your time or energy is a maybe in your mind, then you need to say no. It feels good to say yes to people, but this is what leads to feeling too busy, and too stressed. You have to start saying no more often to escape.</p>

<p>But by saying no to these things, we are enabling ourselves to say &#8220;Yes&#8221; to things we <strong>really</strong> love. Here is a chart from a new book called <a href="http://gregmckeown.com/essentialism-the-disciplined-pursuit-of-less/">&#8220;Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less&#8221;</a> That sums this philosophy up perfectly. Instead of sending our energy out in a hundred directions, and feeling like we aren&#8217;t making any progress, By eliminating the nonessential we can focus our energy in a direction that really matters.</p>

<p><img src="http://glennstovall.com/images/essentialism.jpg"></p>

<p>It can be scary, but once you get used to it, the feeling of saying no is incredibly freeing.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Building Blocks of Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/30/the-building-blocks-of-business/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T13:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/30/the-building-blocks-of-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>It’s easy to look at successful tech companies — ones that have dozens of products like Google, tens of thousands of subscribers like Basecamp, or millions of subscribers such as Facebook. But these kinds of successes didn’t happen overnight. They happened one small step at a time.</p></blockquote>

<p>I was recently published in my local paper, The Athens Banner Herald. You can read the full article <a href="http://onlineathens.com/business/2014-05-16/stovall-building-blocks-business">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Freelance Pricing Handbook Launch Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T10:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Whenever I finish a product, I like to write a post-mortem. A post-mortem answers a few important questions: What w went well? What went wrong? What could be done better next time? I usually keep these to myself, but this time I wanted to share. Building an email list is something every business should be doing, and I wanted to share the specific techniques I used in order to increase the size of a list 500% in 2 days.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Goal</h3>

<p>Start building a mailing list, and learn more about effective email marketing in the process. I plan on releasing a book targeted at freelancers hopefully in July, so I would like to start building a list now in order to build trust and have a targeted audience when I am ready to sell.</p>

<h3>The Process</h3>

<p> I signed up for Nathan Barry&#8217;s <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a> Email list software. This includes enrolling in his &#8220;ConvertKit Academy&#8221; Which is an email course along with a few Google Hangout sessions with Nathan where you get a chance to talk about your personal goals.</p>

<p> Nathan heavily suggested that you have some form on incentive to get people to sign up for your list. He mentioned that you could do a free book, and it could just be a compilation of old writings. He also mentioned setting up a drip marketing course, and ConvertKit comes with a template for that. I looked over some past blog posts and decided to go that route.</p>

<h3>Writing The Book</h3>

<p> Writing the book, and I use the term writing loosely, took about a day. It&#8217;s a compilation of a few different blog articles I had written, along with some content from a chapter I already had completed for my larger book profit. I drafted up a table of contents, and edited the content together, and wrote about 4 - 5 pages of new content to fill in gaps.  I made the PDF in Pages on the mac.</p>

<p> Then it came to the editing stage. I sent my current list of about 15 people an email announcing the book and asking if anyone wanted a copy. I also did the same of Twitter. I got a lot of amazing responses of people willing to read my book and offer feedback.</p>

<p> After I took a couple hours to edit the content together, I was ready to launch.</p>

<h3>Launching the book</h3>

<p>  Here were the steps I took in order to launch the book</p>

<ul>
<li>I added the ConvertKit form to several blog posts that I thought were relevant to the audience.</li>
<li>Created a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">new landing page</a></li>
<li>Wrote two announcement posts, one on <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/">My personal domain</a> and on my <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/announcing-freelance-pricing-handbook/">company domain</a></li>
<li>Posted links on Facebook, Twitter, Reddit, and LinkedIn</li>
<li>Sent an email out to my original list about the book being released. Also included a P.S. asking them to share on Facebook &amp; Twitter if they felt so inclined</li>
<li>Asked my <a href="http://www.fourathens.com/">local tech community</a> to take a look and help out on social media if they wanted to.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Results</h3>

<p>  By the end of the week I had 84 new subscribers to my list. This was with 323 visitors and a conversion rate of 25.8%</p>

<p>  According to Google Analytics, My site had ~600 visits this week, mostly coming from direct traffic (which is odd, I feel like there are some referrals that don&#8217;t get tracked properly), then Reddit, then Facebook, in that order.</p>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<p>  Having friends help out on social media seemed like a huge boost. I don&#8217;t think I&#8217;ve gotten that much traffic from Facebook before. I also had a few people say nice things on Twitter, which I quickly embedded on the landing page as testimonials. The best way to expand your audience is to find ways you can leverage the audience of others.</p>

<p>  Also, writing a book, even when that book is just a PDF &#8220;best-of&#8221; of your blog, seems really cool to a lot of people. Content in PDF form is just seen as more valuable, and I think having this product out there gives me more credibility.</p>

<h3>What went wrong</h3>

<p>  I found out after the fact the form didn&#8217;t render correctly on mobile devices, and made it impossible to sign up if you landed on the landing page via a phone. :( That definitely costs me a few conversions. I added a link below that links to a form directly, though perhaps I should find a better way to set up the form so that it renders in a more responsive friendly way.</p>

<h3>What I learned</h3>

<p>  Using incentives to build email lists really does work! My list went from 15 to 100 in a few days. It is also nice to always have something free to offer users in order to provide value for them.</p>

<p>  My next goal is to take these principles and find a way to apply them in a way I can use to target potential clients for my consulting services. I&#8217;m not sure what that is going to look like, but I&#8217;m sure if I keep writing it&#8217;ll make sense eventually.</p>

<p>  If you&#8217;d like the read the book (and join my mailing list for freelancers), you can get the book below:</p>

<p>  <script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>
If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Test Controller Concerns in Rails 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/06/how-to-test-controller-concerns-in-rails-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T15:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/06/how-to-test-controller-concerns-in-rails-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/ruby_on_rails.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveSupport/Concern.html">Concerns</a> are a new feature that was added in Rails 4. They allow to clean up code in your models and controllers. They also allow you to share functionality between models or controllers. However, they can be a bit tricky to test in isolation. In this article I want to show how you can test your controller concerns in isolation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Over Simplified Scenario</h2>

<p>We have a project with several different types of objects that can be sold. Each item is unique and is marked as &#8216;out of stock&#8217; once it is purchased. However, we have several different controllers and different types of purchases that need this functionality. In order to reduce code duplication, we are going to put these in a concern.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/app/controllers/concerns/transaction_processing.rb </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">module</span> <span class="nn">TransactionProcessing</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">extend</span> <span class="ss">ActiveSupport</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Concern</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">included</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">helper_method</span> <span class="ss">:process_sale</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">process_sale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">item</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">item</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">is_in_stock</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kp">false</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">item</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">save!</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If we want to test this concern, we need a controller to include it in. However, it would not be accurately unit testing to do this as there could be code in that controller that could affect the output of our test. Inside of our test, we can create a fake controller with no methods or logic of it&#8217;s own, and then write tests for that. If you are using <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a>, you can call methods directly using the <code>subject</code> object. Here is my example test using RSpec and <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/factory_girl">FactoryGirl</a></p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/spec/controllers/concerns/transaction_processing_spec.rb </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="nb">require</span> <span class="s1">&#39;spec_helper&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">FakesController</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="no">ApplicationController</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="no">TransactionProcessing</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">describe</span> <span class="no">FakesController</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">it</span> <span class="s2">&quot;should mark an item out of stock&quot;</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">item</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">create</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:item</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">is_in_stock</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="kp">true</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">subject</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">process_sale</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">item</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">expect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">item</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">is_in_stock</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to</span> <span class="n">be</span> <span class="kp">false</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And there you go! Easy, isolated tests for your controller concerns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing The Freelance Pricing Handbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> <img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p> Today I&#8217;m proud to announce a new free eBook guide. The book is called the <em>Freelance Pricing Handbook</em>, and it&#8217;s designed to help freelancers find their perfect rate. The most common question I hear from current and aspiring freelancers is &#8220;How much should I charge?&#8221; This book sets out to answer this question.</p>

<p> <!-- more --></p>

<p> This book is designed to be a short and easy read to help you understand how to find your perfect price. In addition to help you find your rate, it also includes different ways to package and bill for your services. How you price and position your services has a bigger impact on your bottom line than the amount of skill you have. This book is designed to make sure you aren&#8217;t undervaluing yourself and are getting paid the rates you deserve.
If you&#8217;d like a copy of the book, enter your email address below and I&#8217;ll email you a copy.</p>

<p>Be sure to let me know what you think!</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Presenting Value]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T16:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When selling clients on your services, how you position yourself is important. You want clients to see you as an investment, not an expense. In order to accomplish this, you need to make sure you are able to clearly state and justify the value you can bring to a client.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Three Types of Value</h3>

<p>There are three primary types of value you can provide to clients, and all of your sales pitches should anchor to one or more of these points:</p>

<ul>
<li>You make your client money.</li>
<li>You save your client time.</li>
<li>You reduce the client&#8217;s risk.</li>
</ul>


<p>What value <strong>isn&#8217;t</strong> is things like &#8220;writing code&#8221; or &#8220;designing web pages&#8221;. These are just tools you are using to accomplish a goal. When you are talking to potential clients you need to be talking about the goal, not the way you are planning on getting there. A client&#8217;s primary concern is the end result of your work.</p>

<p>You may also notice that saving the client money is absent from this list, even though it sounds like it should be on there. While it&#8217;s good if you find a way to save a client money, products and services that save money are a much more difficult sale, as people who are focused on reducing cost are looking for ways to <em>not</em> spend money, which makes them a pretty tough sell.</p>

<h2>Making Money</h2>

<p>Presenting value here is the easiest of the three. If you can find a way to peg your work to numbers that affect the bottom line, then focus on that. Let&#8217;s say you do A/B testing, and you think that your testing could increase conversions by 10%. If you go to a store that makes $100,000 dollars in sales a year, then your services are easily worth $10,000 to them.</p>

<h2>Saving Time</h2>

<p>This is the one I find myself talking about often, since I work in software development, and love finding ways to automate processes. I&#8217;ve called myself a &#8220;Job Destroyer&#8221; before. Saving a client (or a client&#8217;s employees) time can easily be tied to money as well. I doubt a client would willingly share an employee&#8217;s salary with you, but you can make an educated guess as to the cost of an employee:</p>

<ul>
<li>First, get an estimated salary. You can just guess, or use a service like <a href="http://www.glassdoor.com">glassdoor</a> to approximate the number. In this example, let&#8217;s say that an employee has a salary of $50,000.</li>
<li>Secondly, we are going <a href="http://web.mit.edu/e-club/hadzima/how-much-does-an-employee-cost.html">multiply that number by 2.7</a>. This is to factor in all of the other costs of that employee. Now we have an employee that costs $135,000 a year.</li>
<li>Now, let&#8217;s break that down into an hourly rate. The easiest calculation would be to say salary / 2000, or 50 weeks at 40 hours per week. However, I feel like 1500 may be a better estimate if we want to go by <strong>productive</strong> time, since I don&#8217;t believe anyone is truly and consistently productive for eight hours a day. between those two numbers, we have an hourly range of value of $67.50 - $90.</li>
</ul>


<p>Going by this formula, if you are able to make a 2 hour job take little or no time, then over the course of a year software that could do that would provide up to $9,000 a year in value. If you can scale that to 10 employees, then it&#8217;s $90,000. This is why being able to save time is so valuable to clients.</p>

<h2>Reducing Risk</h2>

<p>Reducing risk is the most abstract of the three, and can be harder to pin an exact number on. Software projects are inherently risky, and anything you can do to reduce that risk is valuable to the client. You see this in consumer sales all the time money back guarantees. By making that guarantee, the product is more valuable since you know that if you are not satisfied you can get your money back.</p>

<p>As a consultant, there are several ways I show that I can reduce risk to clients:</p>

<ul>
<li>Sending clients weekly reports and/or having weekly meetings, So they are always aware of where the project stands. Freelance web developers and designers have a reputation for being flaky, so this helps address that.</li>
<li>Having a set development process in place. This way clients know that I have a more predictable process with more predictable results.</li>
<li>Having a network of other talented people, and letting the client know that if there is something outside of my scope of skills I can bring someone on to help out with the task.</li>
</ul>


<p>Things like having a portfolio and client testimonials are other ways of reducing risk in the eyes of clients. These send the message that other people have worked with before, gotten results, and are satisfied.</p>

<p>However, these all address the reduction of risk in the process, not in the end result. There are several ways this can be accomplished as well. A couple of examples are doing market and competitor research, to see what the project is facing and making sure it is framed appropriately. Another that I am a big fan of is getting to market earlier and iterating quickly. This allows you to work with real people and gather real data. Any decisions made before launch are in many ways an educated guess, and solutions and plans built on objective data instead of guesses will always have a higher chance of succeeding.</p>

<p>Framing your work in this fashion can help both yourself and your clients. It can help you by not only seeing how to present value, but help you find new ways to provide more value to clients when you work as well. This can also help you land more sales and stand out from the competition.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 Resources that shaped my career]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/03/10-resources-that-shaped-my-career/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-03T20:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/03/10-resources-that-shaped-my-career</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/library.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>There is amazing amount of resource available on the internet if you know where to look. I&#8217;ve realized that over the past year, there are some articles, pod casts, books, or videos that have had a huge impact on my view and approach to my business. I&#8217;ve had several people ask me how I came to conclusions I have about how I run my business, and how I execute on them. I wanted to share 10 links that are all free, and have all provided me with exceptional value.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Finance</h2>

<h3><a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/consulting_1">How I Went from $100/hr Programming to $XX,000/week consulting &#8211; Patrick McKenzie</a></h3>

<p>If you only read one of the articles on this list, make it this one. In this article Patrick McKenzie lays out how to go from being a programmer to a consultant. I touched on some of these points in my article <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/take-out-the-tech/">Take out the Tech</a>, about how you aren&#8217;t hiring to program, but instead you are hired to solve problems.</p>

<h3><a href="http://vimeo.com/22053820">Fuck You, Pay Me &#8211; Mike Monteiro(Video)</a></h3>

<p>I tell everyone who wants to get into the freelance business they need to watch this video. While some people are put off my Mike&#8217;s brash style of speaking, the information him and his legal counsel give in this talk is indispensable. In this talk, they talk about how to structure contracts that protect both yourself and your client. Spend 45 minutes watching this video, go touch up your contracts, and never deal with late or non paying clients again.</p>

<h3><a href="http://planscope.io/blog/the-definitive-guide-to-project-billing/">The Definitive Guide to Project Billing &#8211; Brennan Dunn</a></h3>

<p>Most people default to two ways to bill projects: hourly and at a flat rate. This article lays out several other options, such as billing daily and weekly.  Billing clients in daily and weekly increments changes the entire conversation, and has been the main thing I have done to  improve my own bottom line. This article does a great job of laying out your options and how they work. I&#8217;ve also talked about <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/dont-bill-hourly/">Why I don&#8217;t bill hourly</a> and <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly/">How to bill Daily and Weekly</a> in other articles.</p>

<h2>Sales</h2>

<h3><a href="http://42insights.com/lead-generation-strategies/">The 5 Types of Lead Generation Strategies, and The Order You Should Implement Them &#8211; Nick Karrasch</a></h3>

<p>to Summarize, Referrals, Outbound, Content Marketing, Advertising, and Partnerships, in that order. The number one question I get from aspiring freelancers is &#8220;How do you find clients?&#8221;. This article gives you 5 actionable, prioritized strategies for finding new leads. Starting with referrals, which are always the most effective. Many freelancers get 100% of their work from referrals, even if they don&#8217;t realize it. Because of this, it can be easy to become complacent, and not do a lot of active marketing, which leads to the feast or famine cycle that many freelancers find themselves in. That&#8217;s what steps 2 - 5 are for. If you are ever worried about finding clients, start working down the list. Actually, due to the average length of a sales pipeline (at least in my experience), start doing these when you are comfortable, and you&#8217;ll find that those moments when you are worried about finding clients will <strong>stop existing</strong>.</p>

<h3><a href="http://paulgraham.com/ds.html">Do Things That Don&#8217;t Scale &#8211; Paul Graham</a></h3>

<p>Another great article by Paul Graham. I have so many clients ask about &#8220;scalability&#8221; long before they have that problem. This article points out that the most effective strategies when you are starting out are ones that you eventually have to drop later on. I had a start-up founder working on a content network ask me &#8220;How can I find authors?&#8221;. I told him that was the wrong question. The right question to ask is &#8220;How do I find <em>one</em> author?&#8221;. It could be going to events, talking to people individually, and then following up via phone and email. Of course this can&#8217;t be done a lot, but it can be done once. And if it can be done once, then it can be done twice, and thrice, and so on.</p>

<h2>Writing</h2>

<h3><a href="http://nathanbarry.com/commitment-changed-career/">The Commitment That Changed My Career &#8211; Nathan Barry</a></h3>

<p>In this article, Nathan Barry talks about how he made a commitment to write 1,000 words every day, and how it reshaped his career. This article showed me both the power and value of writing, and how much progress you can make by making a small commitment every day. Most first drafts of books are 25,000 - 50,000 words, which means you could write one in just one to two months. I&#8217;ve also seen first hand how writing can be a value tool for marketing, communication, and learning. Spending time writing has also been one of the most transforming decisions I&#8217;ve made for my career.</p>

<h3><a href="http://paulgraham.com/essay.html">The Age of The Essay &#8211; Paul Graham</a></h3>

<p>I probably could have filled up all 10 of these with essays by Paul Graham, but I think this the most important one. In this essay, Paul Graham talks about how  the art of writing essays has changed and became perverted over time by being confined to English departments. Our education system has taught us that essays has to structured a certain way, cite sources a certain way, and be about boring literary or historical topics (unless those subjects are your jam). In reality, essays were originally designed not to be a way for you to share information you already have, but to be an educational experience for yourself. This essay showed me that there is value in writing, even if no one reads it. This article is also meta-inspiring because I love how Paul Graham writes.</p>

<h2>Building Products</h2>

<h3><a href="http://brennandunn.com/episode-009-4-ways-to-productize-your-consulting-business/">4 Ways to Productize Your Consulting Business &#8211; Brennan Dunn (Podcast)</a></h3>

<p>Summary: Retainers, Seminars, Paid Newsletters, Coaching. Many freelancers or consultants want to move from selling their time to selling some form of product. In fact, <a href="http://www.chasingproduct.com/">there is a podcast dedicated to the subject</a>. This podcast lays out some ways to make a small shift towards productizing things. Many developers / designers seem to think that product = SaaS application, but it doesn&#8217;t have to be this way. For example, selling scoped monthly retainers is an easy step that most freelancers can do to get into the habit of selling products, and create some recurring revenue for themselves.</p>

<h3><a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/why-you-should-do-a-tiny-product-first">Why You Should Do a Tiny Product First &#8211; Amy Hoy</a></h3>

<p>When people decide that want to try to build a product to sell, it&#8217;s easy to jump into a grandiose idea, that will take a lot of time and resources. I tell clients there is <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/the-value-in-launching-early/">value in launching early</a> because the bigger a project is, the more likely it is to fail. In this article Amy Hoy talks about picking a project that you can complete in 90 days. While I was wrong in my estimate for my project, It still gave me an idea for a smaller product, my book <em>Bootstrap Freelance</em> , Which I&#8217;ll be releasing later this year.</p>

<h2>Productivity</h2>

<h3><a href="http://unicornfree.com/2012/why-blacksmiths-are-better-at-startups-than-you">Why Blacksmiths are Better at Start-ups than You &#8211;Amy Hoy</a></h3>

<p>This article is a swift kick-in-the-rear that a lot of freelancers and start up founders alike need. It is easy to get caught up in the idea of building something great and unique that we ignore what it takes to get there: lots of time and energy spent learning basic skills. Many people these days want to be craftsmen without putting in the hours to truly hone their craft. Many people are looking for the &#8220;growth hack&#8221; that is going to get their start up 10,000 sign ups overnight or the one pricing trick that clients hate so they can quadruple their freelancing rate. They don&#8217;t want to hammer out the basics and get good at them.</p>

<p>All of this information on how to improve your business, your skills, and your life, is readily available on the internet. This is just the tip of the iceberg.  If you liked these I&#8217;d recommend digging deeper into some more of the content put out by some of the people I&#8217;ve mentioned here: <a href="http://planscope.io/blog/">Brennan Dunn</a>, <a href="http://unicornfree.com/">Amy Hoy</a>, <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/">Nathan Barry</a> , <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/greatest-hits/">Patrick McKenzie</a> , and <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/">Paul Graham</a> , are all great authors who have put out a ton of great content for free.</p>

<p>Some people may wonder why people would be willing to divulge so much of the secret of their success online. I think it goes back to the point Amy Hoy made in her blacksmith&#8217;s article: You can be given all of the tools and knowledge in the world, but if you aren&#8217;t willing to put in the work to put them to use and truly learn to hone your craft they won&#8217;t make any difference. Well, this is some of the best tools I have, and I&#8217;m giving them to you. So get out there and make a difference.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Letting Go Of Money Made me More of It]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/14/how-letting-go-of-money-made-me-more-of-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-14T18:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/14/how-letting-go-of-money-made-me-more-of-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><strong>Note:</strong> This Story was originally <a href="https://medium.com/p/6c9c9f08b552/">posted on Medium on October 21, 2013</a>. But since Medium just added a new tool for <a href="https://medium.com/help-center/3eaed64aed8a">Embedding Posts on your own site</a>, I wanted to try it out.</em></p>

<script async src="https://static.medium.com/embed.js"></script>


<p><a class="m-story" data-collapsed="false" href="https://medium.com/p/6c9c9f08b552">How Letting Go of Money Made me More of It</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take Out The Tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/take-out-the-tech/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T15:25:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/take-out-the-tech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/make_fire.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>If you are a freelance developer, designer, photographer, or even a freelance sheep sheerer, it&#8217;s easy to get caught up in what it is you do, versus why it is we actually do it. More important than why we do it, is why people are willing to pay us good money for what we do. In this article I&#8217;d like to take a look at why I decided to re-position my services, and most important of all, get you to stop talking like a nerd because it&#8217;s costing you money and sales.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>No More Nerd Speak</h2>

<p>When I decided to focus more on being a consultant, and not just a &#8220;freelance web developer&#8221;, one of my qualifiers for the kinds of clients I wanted to attract was that a client should not care about the tech stack I was working on. words like  &#8220;WordPress&#8221; and &#8220;Ruby on Rails&#8221; were dirty curse words as far as proposals were concerned. I had several reasons for this:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Client Filtering:</strong> Clients that use words like &#8216;PHP Developer&#8217;, are usually looking for contractors, not consultants. There is nothing wrong with being a contractor, I&#8217;ve done it many times, but it isn&#8217;t in line with my future business goals.</li>
<li><strong>Focusing on Solutions &amp; Value:</strong> There is no problem that has to be solved by a certain language or framework. Some are better suited than others. A client that wants a &#8220;Rails app that does X&#8221; may be better served by a &#8220;Node.js app that does X&#8221; or a Mobile Application that does X&#8221;. They may even be better served by a nice spreadsheet or an actionable plan they can stick to. By taking technical terms out of the conversations, it allows for more focus on the problem, and the solution to be discovered.</li>
<li><strong>Autonomy:</strong> Similar to the point above, I want the autonomy to decide what tool would be the best fit for the jobs I take on, and be able to use them. If a client does not know what tools are used, which they shouldn&#8217;t, then they have no say in the matter.</li>
<li><strong>Client Interest:</strong> Clients don&#8217;t care about this kind of stuff nearly as much we do. Clients are usually very busy people in their businesses and our lives. By leaving out talk of weird, complicated things that they don&#8217;t understand and have no interest in, you are doing your clients a great kindness.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Closing the Text Editor</h2>

<p>One day at work I decided to do a mental exercise. If I close my text editor, how could I still provide value to clients? I wanted to step away from just thinking that &#8220;code = value&#8221; and take a more holistic approach at what I provide to clients.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Communication:</strong> Web developers and designers have a reputation for being unreliable and hard to reach. Being proactive with clients on phone, email, and in person makes them feel more secure about their project, reduces their stress, and prevents misunderstanding that can waste time on both ends of the table.</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Having a solid plan in place and communicating that plan has a lot of benefits. It maintains accountability and expectations on both sides. Providing a clear plan to a client on how you are going to perform work and when they can expect it to be delivered. It shows that you aren&#8217;t just another unreliable, uncommunicative developer like they have probably encountered in the past.</li>
<li><strong>Research:</strong> Who is their target market? What is a good pricing strategy for their new product? How can your client reach their target demographic? Do they like the new feature implemented? Being able to provide answers to questions like this can help guide a client in the right direction, and help your work produce even more value.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&#8217;ve realized to think about deliverable products in a broader sense. A road map for a project is every bit as much of a deliverable as a new feature that has been coded, and should be treated and presented as such. (<strong>Pro-tip:</strong> clients like nicely formatted PDFs that they can share with other people in their company.)</p>

<h2>Don&#8217;t Sell Yourself Short</h2>

<p>Designers, developers, copywriters, etc. are costing themselves money by thinking that only producing their core competency. I&#8217;ve had aspiring freelancers ask me &#8220;Should I bill for phone calls/meetings/emails?&#8221;. I say yes. Some people will say because they are taking up your time, and that since being a freelancer usually equates to selling your time for money, client communication counts. They&#8217;re right, but for the wrong reasons. The reason you bill for those times is <em>because you providing the client with value</em>. Your communications that help you gather information to deliver the exact solution, and ease the clients concern are just as valuable as the core product you produce, <strong>if not more so.</strong></p>

<p>So to other freelancers out there: <strong>Don&#8217;t sell yourself short.</strong> And stop talking so much about how you swing your hammer, and instead about what you can build and why it&#8217;s so valuable.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal vs. Professional Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T14:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/saddington.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I had the pleasure of seeing <a href="http://john.do">John Saddington</a> give a talk about the benefits of blogging at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/transform-athens/">Transform Athens</a> Athens event. The talk was about the benefits of blogging, and while it reinvigorated my interest in writing and publishing. It brought up a tricky question. I have a blog under my personal name, <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com">Glenn Stovall</a> and a company blog, <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Where should I publish? Why should I publish there? What are the pros and cons of blogging under a personal brand vs. a professional brand?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Whatever it Takes to Hit &#8216;Publish&#8217;</h3>

<p>I posed this question to John, and john shares my belief that publishing and shipping should always be the paramount goal. His feelings as to whether you should blog under your name or a company name comes down to doing &#8220;what ever makes you hit the publish button quicker&#8221;. It&#8217;s true that it is a largely personal choice that comes down to personal preferences. While his advice was helpful, it was still a question I had to answer for myself.</p>

<h3>The Tone of the Blogs</h3>

<p>In my post when I announced <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/12/10/announcing-concordant-solutions/">Concordant Solutions</a>, I mentioned my original plan for managing two different blogs. I wanted to cater to two different audiences, and each blog would be focused on one of them. My personal blog would be focused on technical, usually long form articles. It was were I would write to &#8216;fellow nerds&#8217;. My company blog would be aimed at clients. I wouldn&#8217;t write what I wanted to read, I would write what I felt would be interesting to my clients.</p>

<p>Here is the issue I ran into with that approach: my &#8220;company brand&#8221; writing was usually dry and boring. Writing is hard. Writing under a squeaky clean corporate persona is even harder. While I felt I did write things of some value on my company blog, I often felt my writing fell flat.</p>

<p>I wasn&#8217;t happy with my writing, and it wasn&#8217;t getting nearly as many readers. Life is too short to spend it doing things that produce a mediocre result.</p>

<h2>Defining Subject Matter</h2>

<p>My approach to the Concordant Solutions blog was completely wrong. I bought too hard into the belief that <em>you are not your customer</em>, and it skewed my writing. It&#8217;s true, I am not my customer. I don&#8217;t have employees (yet). My customers are not always tech savvy. However, I <strong>am</strong> a business owner. I am not just another freelancer. I am determined on creating a focused, sustainable, growing business. I am a business owner, just like my clients.</p>

<p>I made a fatal mistake of thinking that me and my clients do not have a common interest.  While a lot of my clients have no idea what &#8220;AngularJS&#8221; means, they know what cash flow, ROI, and LTV means. Being honest about your business can help it grow. Regardless of where I publish content, it&#8217;s all still in some form about being honest and transparent with my business, and doing so in a way that help other people accomplish their goals, whether they are technical or financial.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to bill Daily or Weekly]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T16:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/calendar.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When it comes to freelancing, you may think you only have two options when it comes to how you bill your clients: You can bill by the hour, or you can bill by the project. But these aren&#8217;t your only options, and in many cases they are not your best ones.</p>

<p>Two alternatives to this is billing by the day, or billing by the week. These billing structures are a little more uncommon, but in my experience as a consultant, they have been the most effective and productive. Since these structures are a little bit different, they often require a little bit of explanation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What&#8217;s In A Day?</h3>

<p>An hour is a definite measure of time. it&#8217;s 60 minutes. When you bill a client for a hour, they expect to be providing value during those 60 minutes. A day is also a definite measure of time, but if you bill a client for a day they don&#8217;t expect 24 hours of productivity from you.</p>

<p>You make think that a work day of 8 hours is a more reasonable assumption, but that also isn&#8217;t the case. Many studies have shown that creative workers are only productive for <a href="http://qz.com/157092/the-case-for-a-six-hour-workday/">5 to 6 hours a day</a>, and that increased hours can in fact lead to decreased productivity. So when it comes to billing by the day, it just means whatever you think a good day&#8217;s work means to you. It doesn&#8217;t mean that it has to be all of your time, or that if you bill for a day you can&#8217;t do any other productive work for another client.</p>

<p>If you have been working in freelancing or consulting and have been keeping track of your hours, you can use that data to determine your day rate.</p>

<h3>Weekly Billing and Deadlines</h3>

<p>Weekly billing tends to work a little bit differently. When you bill by the week, you do so with a goal and a deliverable for the week. Weekly billing is in a way like billing a flat project rate, but you are delivering smaller projects in a smaller time frame.</p>

<p>Weekly billing may seem strange at first, but if you think about it, this is how salaried employees basically work.</p>

<p>With my clients, I set milestones every two weeks, and tell them that I will deliver on those milestones in the time frame. It doesn&#8217;t matter if I am working 30 hours a week, or 40, or 60, or 5. As long as the results and value are delivered, that is what counts.</p>

<p>The other thing I like about weekly billing is that it makes scheduling my availability much simpler. I can look at my calendar, see that I have worked booked for the next 6 weeks, and have a clear date for when I am available for more work.</p>

<h3>How to Decide on a Pricing Model</h3>

<p>I don&#8217;t think that any consultant should stick to just one pricing structure, unless you work on a narrow type of project. Different projects and different clients will work better with different billing structures. Here is when I would consider each one:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Hourly Billing:</strong> For jobs where the scope is unknown and flexibility is needed.</li>
<li><strong>Flat Rate Billing:</strong> When the scope of a project can be well defined and the project is small.</li>
<li><strong>Daily Billing:</strong> Works well for one day consulting arrangements, and also for projects that you want to commit to part time (such as 2 - 3 days per week)</li>
<li><strong>Weekly Billing:</strong> My personal favorite. Tends to work well on larger projects, and projects that need flexibility and aren&#8217;t committed to a hard scope.</li>
</ul>


<p>By thinking about how you price and position your services, you can come up with plans that can make your scheduling better, and help you price your services more aggressively.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT:</strong> Just found this episode of The Freelancer&#8217;s Show where they discuss <a href="http://www.freelancersshow.com/the-freelancers-show-097-weekly-billing/">weekly billing</a>, Worth a listen if you want to hear more about this subject.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Other Writing Around the Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/other-writing-around-the-web/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T16:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/other-writing-around-the-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/writing.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>I haven&#8217;t spent much time writing content for this blog, but I have been doing some writing on other sites. Here are some of my posts from other sites:</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/4-techniques-developing-ios-android/">4 Techniques for Developing for both iOS and Android</a> Discusses the pros and cons of web apps vs. native apps vs. cross compiling tools such as Titanium</li>
<li><a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/the-value-in-launching-early/">The Value in Launching Early</a> Why pushing your launch date up by cutting features is only going to make you more money.</li>
<li><a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/dont-bill-hourly/">Why We Don&#8217;t Bill Hourly</a> An explination of my logic behind changing my billing techniques in 2014. Protip: Start billing weekly.</li>
<li><a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/aarrr-pirate-metrics-5-numbers-you-need-to-know-about-your-business/">Pirate Metrics, 5 Numbers you Need to Know About Your Business</a>. Writing about the main metrics companies should be looking at.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/p/6c9c9f08b552">How Letting Go of Money Made me More of It</a> One of my personal favorites. Discussing how life lessons from being a profressional online poker player translate into being a consultant.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing Concordant Solutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/12/10/announcing-concordant-solutions/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-10T11:09:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/12/10/announcing-concordant-solutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/santamegaphone.png" width="260"></p>

<p>As a consultant, it&#8217;s important to think of what you are doing as a business, and not just as you as a person. Having said that, I&#8217;ve set up a new company name for my services, <strong>Concordant Solutions</strong>.</p>

<p>The name comes from a Concordant, or agreement. It signifies how by working together with clients I am able to provide value for them that neither one of us could do individually. When people with domain knowledge in an industry come together with people with tech knowledge and the skills to put their ideas into practice, great things happen.</p>

<p>The company also gives me an avenue for market segmentation when it comes to content. I will still have this personal blog, which will be centered around technical content. Concordant Solutions will focus on content aimed at business owners.</p>

<p>If you are interested in supporting me, or learning more about ways you can help your business, Please check out my new company below.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/concordantsolutions">Concordant Solutions on Facebook</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.twitter.com/_Concordant">Concordant Solutions on Twitter</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">ConcordantSolutions.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AngularJS: an Overview]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T12:33:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/angular.png" width="260"></p>

<p>AngularJS is a JavaScript framework made by Google for building complex client-side applications. Angular&#8217;s killer feature is &#8216;directives&#8217; which allow you to extend HTML by creating your own tags and attributes. Angular projects have a somewhat different structure than other JavaScript MVC frameworks, but it can be highly modular and easy to maintain once you understand the structure. Let&#8217;s take a look at the main components of AngularJS and how they work, and why you should strongly consider Angular for your next project.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Philosophy of AngularJS</h3>

<h4>Data First</h4>

<p>If you are familiar with JavaScript libraries like jQuery, using AngularJS will require a bit of a paradigm shift. AngularJS is like jQuery, but backwards. what I mean by that, is that jQuery is mainly focused on DOM manipulation, and then you update data based on that. When writing Angular, you will mostly be updating data, and the DOM will be updated for you, with very little work on your end.</p>

<h4>Highly Testable</h4>

<p>AngularJS was designed to be testable end-to-end. It uses <strong>Dependency Injection</strong> In many of objects so that parts of it can easily be mocked. It is also designed to encourage you to break the functionality of your application into several smaller, more testable parts.</p>

<h4>Declarative HTML</h4>

<p>Angular is designed to extend HTML to make it the language you need for building complex web applications. Adding your own tags and attributes allows you to write simple HTML tags that do very complex things.</p>

<h3>Data Binding</h3>

<p>Let&#8217;s take a look at a very simple AngularJS app, that uses <strong>two-way data binding</strong>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;body</span> <span class="na">ng-app</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&#39;text&#39;</span> <span class="na">ng-model=</span><span class="s">&#39;name&#39;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;h2&gt;</span>{{name}}<span class="nt">&lt;/h2&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let&#8217;s break this down line by line to explain what is happening:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>&lt;body ng-app&gt;</code> : all Angular code must be wrapper in this directive. This declares that everything within this tag will be treated as an angular application.</li>
<li><code>&lt;input type='text' ng-model='name' /&gt;</code> : This is one part of the data binding. Here we are using another directive, ng-model, to bind the input to a string. Note that in this example we also see that attribute directives can have arguments.</li>
<li><code>&lt;h2&gt;{{name}}&lt;/h2&gt;</code> : Whenever you type into the input box, this h2 tag updates automatically. This is the automatic DOM manipulation I mentioned earlier. We were able to do this without writing a single line of JavaScript.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Modules</h3>

<p><strong>Modules</strong> are used to organize the objects in an AngularJS application. Modules can either be used as as the &#8216;core&#8217; of an application, and contain all of the classes used for it, or they can be used to group several objects that have similar functionality. Let&#8217;s create a module for our application:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">angular</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">module</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;myApp&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">[]);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;body</span> <span class="na">ng-app=</span><span class="s">&#39;myApp&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The first argument passed to <code>angular.module</code> is the name of the module. We have passed that name to the <code>ng-app</code> to bind everything contained in that directive to our module. The second argument is an array of other modules your module depends on. This is empty since we currently don&#8217;t have any. Much like directives, AngularJS contains several modules already built that you can include in your projects.</p>

<p>Now that we have a module, we will write our first type of AngularJS object, a <strong>controller</strong>.</p>

<h3>Controllers</h3>

<p>Controllers are tied to particular html elements. They contain data and functions that the html can interact with, and can interact with other service objects, which can handle things such as communicating with the server. Let&#8217;s create a controller and bind it to a div in our application.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">controller</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;mainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">&#39;Default Name&#39;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;body</span> <span class="na">ng-app=</span><span class="s">&#39;myApp&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">ng-controller=</span><span class="s">&#39;mainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&#39;text&#39;</span> <span class="na">ng-model=</span><span class="s">&#39;name&#39;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;h2&gt;</span>{{name}}<span class="nt">&lt;/h2&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Here we&#8217;ve used the <code>ng-controller</code> directive to bind our controller function to a div. Controllers get one argument by default which is called <code>$scope</code>. <code>$scope</code> contains all of the data that the html can interact with. When you reload the page, you will notice that the input now starts with the field filled in with &#8216;Default Name&#8217;. This is because we set that variable in the controller, which is called when the page is loaded.</p>

<p>Functions can also applied to scope and then called inside the HTML. Angular contains several directives for handling various events. Let&#8217;s change our example to include a function that we will call with an <code>ng-click</code> directive. We will add a button to save the name we create and later display the list.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">controller</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;mainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">&#39;Default Name&#39;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">people</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[];</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">savePerson</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">people</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">push</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">&#39;&#39;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;body</span> <span class="na">ng-app=</span><span class="s">&#39;myApp&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">ng-controller=</span><span class="s">&#39;mainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">&#39;text&#39;</span> <span class="na">ng-model=</span><span class="s">&#39;name&#39;</span> <span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;button</span> <span class="na">ng-click=</span><span class="s">&#39;savePerson()&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Save Person<span class="nt">&lt;/button&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nt">&lt;h2&gt;</span>{{name}}<span class="nt">&lt;/h2&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now we can save a list of these people. We can use another directive called <code>ng-repeat</code> To output a list of the people we have saved:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;ul&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;li</span> <span class="na">ng-repeat=</span><span class="s">&#39;person in people&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>{{person}}<span class="nt">&lt;/li&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/ul&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now that we have seen how we can manipulate data inside the JavaScript, let&#8217;s look at how we can manipulate the DOM, by creating our own <strong>directives</strong></p>

<h3>Directives</h3>

<p>You have already seen directives in use in several places inside the application. You can also define your own directives as part of your application. Let&#8217;s create an alertable directive that will allow you to set a message to be alerted whenever you click on the element.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">directive</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;alertable&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(){</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">restrict</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;A&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">link</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">scope</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">element</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">attrs</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">element</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">bind</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;click&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nx">alert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">attrs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">alertable</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And now we an add this to our person list:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>index.html  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;li</span> <span class="na">ng-repeat=</span><span class="s">&#39;person in people&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;span</span> <span class="na">alertable=</span><span class="s">&#39;{{person}}&#39;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>{{person}}<span class="nt">&lt;/span&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/li&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>As you can see, directives return an object that will define the directive. There are several optional arguments that can be passed here, but let&#8217;s look at the two we used here:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>restrict</strong> : This tells your directive what kind of directive it will be. restrict is required and there are four possible arguments that can be passed to it:</p></li>
<li><p><strong>E</strong> : Element. example usage: <code>&lt;my-directive&gt;&lt;/my-directive&gt;</code></p></li>
<li><strong>A</strong> : Attribute. example usage: <code>&lt;div my-directive&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</code></li>
<li><strong>C</strong> : Class. example usage: <code>&lt;div class='my-directive'&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</code></li>
<li><p><strong>M</strong> : Comment. example usage: <code>&lt;!-- directive:my-directive --&gt;</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>link</strong> : The link function is responsible for adding event listeners and updating the dom.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>You can read about some of the other possible options in the <a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/guide/directive">Angular directive documentation</a>.</p>

<h3>Services</h3>

<p>Services are classes that can either contain business logic or handle data. Now we are going to refactor  our previous example and create a service that can handle the data in our list of people.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">factory</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;PersonService&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">PersonService</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{};</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">PersonService</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">people</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[];</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">PersonService</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">addPerson</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">person</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">PersonService</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">people</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">push</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">person</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">};</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">PersonService</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You&#8217;ll notice that services are created slightly differently than controllers. Controllers are just a function, where services are a function that returns an object. This allows you to add private methods to your service if you would like.</p>

<p>Now we need a way for our controller to have access to the service we just created. Since they are in the same module, this is very easy to do. This also involves one of the more &#8220;magical&#8221; features of Angular. To give the controller access to our service, we just have to add it as an argument to our controller, like so:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>app.controller('mainCtrl', function($scope, PersonService){});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>What&#8217;s really surprising is that if you change the order of the arguments to the controller function, <em>it will not change how the controller function operates</em>. So, if we did this instead:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>app.controller('mainCtrl', function(PersonService, $scope){});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Our function would behave in exactly the same way. This is because AngularJS looks at the names of the arguments of a function to decide what to pass to them. Now, you may be concerned that this could break if you were to minify your JavaScript, and you would be right. Luckily, Angular provides an alternate way of declaring functions to prevent issues when minifying your code. It involves passing an array of strings to tell angular what the arguments should be, with the actual function as the last element in the array. So now your controller would look like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>app.controller('mainCtrl', ['$scope', 'PersonService', function($scope, PersonService){}]);</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>When writing services, Angular provides some helpful modules for communicating with the server. Some of the most useful are <a href="">ngHttp</a> and <a href="">ngResource</a>. ngHttp is used to make HTTP requests. ngResource is an extension of ngHttp designed to work exclusively with REST APIs. This is another reason why when you are declaring a service, you are asked for a function that returns an object; We are able to use this function to extend an existing object like ngResource and return it.</p>

<h3>Routing</h3>

<p>Angular also provides support for routing with URLs. Routing is performed by using the <code>config</code> function of the module. Let&#8217;s use this to structure separate pages for our main page, and give each person in our person list a profile page. Here is what the route provider will look like:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>app.js  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">config</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">when</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;/&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">templateUrl</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;templates/home.html&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">controller</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;homePageCtrl&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">when</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;/person/:id&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">templateUrl</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;templates/profile.html&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">controller</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;profileCtrl&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Filters</h3>

<p>Filters are a smaller, but often useful part of AngularJS. Filters are used to transform data when it is displayed to the user. Like directives, you can build them yourself, and Angular also includes several useful ones built-in. Let&#8217;s look at the following HTML:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;span>Price:&lt;/span> 300</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Which will look like this in the browser:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Price: 300</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>We can apply a couple filters to this to make it look different, by using the <code>|</code> operator:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;span>{{ "Price:" | uppercase }}&lt;/span> {{ "300" | currency }}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And our output will now look like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>PRICE: $300.00</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Additional Reading</h3>

<p>I hope you found this helpful, but this is just scratching the surface of what Angular.js is capable of. If you would like to learn more about Angular, here are some resources for further reading:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/">AngularJS Documentation</a> - official documentation, lots of good examples</li>
<li><a href="http://egghead.io">EggHead.io</a> - several short (usually 4 or 5 minute) videos explaining several particular parts of angular.</li>
<li><a href="http://builtwith.angularjs.org/">BuiltWith AngularJS</a> - examples of applications built with Angular</li>
<li><a href="http://sporto.github.io/blog/2013/04/12/comparison-angular-backbone-can-ember/">A Comparison of Angular, Backbone, CanJS and Ember</a> - a great article comparing AngularJS to some</li>
</ul>


<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[reading on wealth and programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/07/reading-on-wealth-and-programming/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T08:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/07/reading-on-wealth-and-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>The world of software development is one that runs on abstractions. Developers are used to working in this world when it comes to software, but when these abstractions start to <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/LeakyAbstractions.html">Leak Out</a> into the real world it can become harder to manage. One of the trickier abstractions is the one between software development and wealth. It is clear that programming provides some sort of value, or else people would not be so eager to pay for it. It is a complex subject, and one I am not equipped to get into in the depth it needs, but instead I wanted to share a couple articles and a book I have read recently that shed some light on the subject.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>How To Make Wealth &#8211; Paul Graham</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/wealth.html">How To Make  Wealth</a></p>

<p>This is an older essay by <a href="http://paulgraham.com/">Paul Graham</a> , a programmer and venture capitalist who co-founded <a href="http://ycombinator.com/">Y Combinator</a>. Paul is an excellent writer, and in this article he does a great job at explaining how programmers are able to create wealth. He also makes an important distinction: That wealth does not necessarily equal money. Money is the medium of exchange in which wealth is transferred. to paraphrase one of his examples, Linus Torvalds helped create Linux and Git. These tools are free and open-source, and even if Linus didn&#8217;t make a dime off of these, he still created wealth. He compares and contrasts the three major ways a programmer can convert the wealth they generate into money. Programmers can be employees for a company, where as an employee you are getting a share of the wealth you and all your co-workers generate in the form of a salary. They can also be contractors and freelancers, where they can sell their wealth directly. There is also working for a start-up, which has the highest returns, but also the biggest risk. As he puts it, a programmer who can generate $1 million in wealth for a start-up will not get $1 million in return, but they could get a 20% chance at getting $10 million for it. There is more risk, but it is a proposition that does offer a lot of expected value.</p>

<h3>Are Coders Worth It? &#8211; James Somers</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.aeonmagazine.com/living-together/james-somers-web-developer-money/">Are Coders Worth It?</a></p>

<p>This article from Aeon Magazine sheds some light on what working as a web developer is like these days. And he is right, times right now are good for skilled programmers. Building a tech start-up is cheaper than ever before. Before when some value may have been created by the infrastructure your company builds, now all of that is a commodity that can easily be bought for cheap and scaled up as necessary. Instead of having to worry about hiring a system administrator to maintain a large server, you can simply spin up an instance of Heroku. Need to manage payment processing or project management? There is a bevy of tools that can be subscribed to for just tens of dollars a month to solve this problem. Developers are the people that can put all of this together and make something valuable. As James puts it, In this gold rush, developers are the shovel.</p>

<h3>Double Your Freelancing Rate &#8211; Brennan Dunn</h3>

<p><a href="http://doubleyourfreelancingrate.com/">Double Your Freelancing Rate</a></p>

<p>Brennan Dunn is a freelancer who has written an excellent book about increasing the amount of money you can make as a freelancer. He brings up two good points that can help freelancers understand their value. One is that freelancers should focus on the value they provide a company.  It is easy to get caught in the trap of believing that the rate you charge should be based on the amount of work you do, or on the skills you have. However, both of these are just means to an end; It is possible to be skilled, work hard, and create something that is of no value to anyone. By focusing instead on the benefit you provide, it can break down this wall of abstraction between you and the client in regards to wealth, and as a freelancer you can make sure that you are getting paid what you are worth.  The second point he makes is that the value we provide is not just in the products that we produce, but in experience we can provide when working with people. To many people, programming is a black box. Many business owners may not understand what is possible, and what kind of resources are involved in certain types of programming. I once spent 3 days writing something for a company that was later sold for $30,000 to a client.  I&#8217;ve also spent months writing code that probably ended up have a real world value of near zero. Part of being a developer is solving problems, and working with clients to understand what you can do for them that provides the best value. I&#8217;d rather write more code for clients like that first example, and less like the second, and I am sure they would prefer that as well.</p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Having a greater understanding of how programming creates wealth is a win for everybody. Programmers who understand this can focus their abilities on activities that generate the most wealth, and can find themselves in more favorable positions by understanding how their work relates to this. Business owners who understand this can also look to work with developers who can provide them with the best value. This is why many freelancers charge a higher rate; There is more to being a developer than just cranking out code, it comes with this ability to solve problems and find ways to create value. Many people who look for very cheap development options aren&#8217;t aware of this, and usually end up paying the price in the future.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn&#8217;t work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
