<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Software That Sells]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-01T14:58:37-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A 9-Step Content Process That Will Grow Your Business]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/07/01/a-9-step-content-process-that-will-grow-your-business/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-01T14:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/07/01/a-9-step-content-process-that-will-grow-your-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People have probably told you that two things every business should be doing is generating content and building a list. The problem with this advice is that it usually comes wit no “how” or a “why”. Writing content as a marketing strategy is a slow burn with abstract benefits. But a solid strategy can bring in more customers, help you build relationships, and help you position yourself as an expert to others. And writing content that does this is not a hard as it looks.</p>

<p>One of the scary factors of creating a content strategy is that publishing consistently is valuable, but that requires a commitment. When you don&#8217;t know <em>what</em> to write about, <em>how</em> to write about it, or how to get readers, it’s easy to feel overwhelmed. Here’s my 9-step process I use to generate content; A Roadmap you can use to start mapping out your content strategy.</p>

<h2>1. Keep A Swipe File</h2>

<p>If you are solving people&#8217;s problems with your work, then you have more than enough jumping off points for pieces of content. Content is providing value at scale. If you are providing content in a one-to-one or one-to-few manner, you can turn that into content to provide that value to potential customers on the internet.</p>

<p>To keep track of these events, I keep a <em>swipe file</em>. My swipe file is a collection of thoughts, notes, and links that could become articles one day. Here are my sources for potential content ideas:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Interesting Conversations.</strong> Did you have an interesting discussion that relates to your business with someone in a sales meeting or even just at the bar? Put it in the swipe file.</li>
<li><strong>Problems You Solved.</strong> Did you solve any interesting problems this week? Put a note in the swipe file. These notes are the source of my technical articles.</li>
<li><strong>Email.</strong> Did you write a good email response to someone or have an interesting discussion? Put it in the swipe file.</li>
<li><strong>Forums and Social Media.</strong> Did you write a good response to someone or have an interesting conversation on Twitter, Facebook, Reddit, or some other forum? Put it in the swipe file.</li>
</ul>


<p>You’ll see from above the easiest way to build content is to <em>have conversations.</em> Writing content is just a one-to-many way to build relationships, so any one-to-one conversation you have is a solid jumping off point.</p>

<h2>2. Make Writing A Habit</h2>

<p>Nathan Barry talks about how the biggest difference maker in his business was <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/commitment-changed-career/">making a commitment to writing 1,000 words a day</a>. If you want to produce a lot of quality content, you need to make it a habit. Make time every day, even if it is only 15 minutes. If you don’t know where to start, that’s why you have a  swipe file. Open it and pick one of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>The note in the swipe file that excites you the most.</li>
<li>If nothing is exciting to you, then just grab the oldest one.</li>
</ul>


<p>Another benefit to a consistent habit is that you can work on ideas while they are still fresh and exciting. If you write an idea and don’t flesh out the idea until six weeks later, you might find that your interest in that topic has waned.</p>

<p>The emotions you feel when you write will transfer over to the people reading it. Bored writers write boring content.</p>

<h2>3. Outline and Brainstorm</h2>

<p>Before you start hammering away at the keys, take a few minutes and figure out what it is you want to say. Sketch out the key points you want to hit and what you want to say about them. Having some idea of where you are going will make steps 4 &amp; 5 a lot easier and more efficient. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind_map">Mind mapping</a> can be useful here.</p>

<h2>4. Choose A Template</h2>

<p>Good content has structure, and you don’t need to reinvent the wheel every time you sit down to write. Songs have a verse-chorus-verse structure that can be repeated infinitely without losing people’s interest. In fact, following a pre-defined formula makes the content <em>more</em> accessible to the reader.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Pain, Dream, Fix.</strong> I got this one from <a href="https://unicornfree.com/2013/how-i-increased-conversion-2-4x-with-better-copywriting">Amy Hoy</a>. Talk about the problem, and then talk about how great things would be if your reader didn’t have that problem, then talk about how they can solve that problem. The pain you an engaging starting point.</li>
<li><strong>Lists.</strong> They can be cheesy, but the internet loves lists. If your content makes sense in a sequential order, then consider taking that approach.</li>
<li><strong>Stories.</strong> If you want to take a more entertainment based route, you can tell stories. Each story has a protagonist (either you or the reader), a conflict, and how they overcame that conflict.</li>
<li><strong>Comparisons.</strong> Write about ‘this vs. that’ and compare and contrast two products or opposing viewpoints.</li>
<li><strong>Essays.</strong> An essay starts with a thesis, then provides evidence to back up that thesis. Paul Graham is a master of this.</li>
<li><strong>Tutorials.</strong> Write a ‘how to X’ article. These are the easiest to write for me. Most of my tutorials are for my benefit.  If I run into a previously solved problem, then I can quickly reference what I wrote previously.</li>
<li><strong>Roundups.</strong> A Roundup is a collection of resources from other places online. This template is useful if you don’t have a lot to say on a subject but want to get something out there.</li>
</ul>


<h2>5. Write A Terrible First Draft</h2>

<p>You should have a clear vision of what you want to say, and how you are going to say it. Now it’s time to get to work. The main goal of your first draft is you put words on paper. The best way to this is to remember to do one thing:</p>

<p><strong>Give yourself permission to suck.</strong></p>

<p>Just write. Don’t edit. Don’t worry about filling in links or notes. If you need to find links or do research to back up your points, leave yourself notes to do that later. The most important thing here is that you are getting words down.</p>

<h2>6. Edit</h2>

<p>I like to give an article some breathing room, so I don’t write an article and publish it on the same day. When you are building a writing habit, you may consider have 2 - 3 writing days and 1 - 2 editing days.</p>

<p>No one produces something great on the first try. That’s why we don’t even attempt it with our terrible first draft. Now it’s time to take the marble slab of our terrible draft and carve out our traffic generating Statue of David.</p>

<p>When editing, we want to keep a few different people in mind.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Edit for your readers.</strong> Read your content, fill in any blanks, and do any ‘TODOs’ you left yourself. Remember when I said you didn’t have to find research links or fill in every section earlier? Time to take care of that.</li>
<li><strong>Edit for your haters.</strong> The internet is not always the nicest place. If you make an assertion, you need to back it up. One unclear or unsubstantiated claim is enough for someone to not give your entire piece any merit.</li>
<li><strong>Edit for your English Teacher.</strong> If there is another thing the internet doesn’t take kindly to, it’s spelling and grammatical errors. These can hurt your authority. I’d recommend reading Strunk &amp; White’s Elements of Style, and using <a href="http://glennstovall.com/recommends/grammarly">Grammarly</a> to automate the process.</li>
</ul>


<h2>7. Optimize</h2>

<p>When Optimizing we focus on the beginning and end of your article. The beginning is your headline, and the end is your call-to-action. These will be the artisan bread that accents the meat and toppings of your delicious content sandwich</p>

<p>The headlines j is to get people to read the rest of your article. Much like the structure of the article, it’s nice to have some templates in place for this. Here are a few I learned from CopyHackers that I use:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Timed premise:</strong> “How to Make A Delicious Sandwich in under 15 minutes.”</li>
<li><strong>Even If:</strong> “How to Make Delicious Sandwiches Even If You Can’t Afford Top-Shelf Ingredients.”</li>
<li><strong>How-To:</strong> “How to Make a Delicious Prosciutto Sandwich”.</li>
<li><strong>Quantity:</strong> “Make 100 Sandwiches Instead of Hiring A Caterer.”</li>
<li><strong>Lists:</strong> “35 Unlikely Sandwich Combinations.”</li>
<li><strong>Why:</strong> “Why You Should Be Eating Peanut Butter Banana Bacon Sandwiches.”</li>
<li><strong>Ultimate:</strong> “The Complete Sandwich Playbook.”</li>
<li><strong>Simile:</strong> “Make Sandwiches Like Alton Brown.”</li>
</ul>


<p>Remember that your headline needs to engage the reader and leave them wanting more. It should spark emotion and curiosity. Try writing a couple and coming up with the best one. It’s also important to note that you don’t want to over-optimize your headlines. Don’t be Upworthy. If your headline is salacious and your content doesn’t deliver, you will leave your potential customers feeling disappointed, frustrated, and lied to.</p>

<p>The call-to-action is what you want readers to do after reading the article. Your CTA doesn’t have to be a hard sell, nor should it be. You want to focus on engaging with the reader further. Here are some ideas:</p>

<ul>
<li>Ask a question and ask people to respond by commenting.</li>
<li>Ask people to join your mailing list.</li>
<li>Offer people a lead magnet or bonus benefit, which is just another way to get them on your mailing list.</li>
<li>Ask people to email you or fill out your contact form.</li>
<li>Ask them to follow up with more information, like a survey.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you have a product, you can include a call to action here, but it depends on what you are selling. I prefer to get people to opt-in to further engagement where I can continue to interact with them and build trust, and try to make the sale later. The important thing is that without a call-to-action, your content is not going to be doing as much work as it should for you.</p>

<h2>8. Publish</h2>

<p>Content sitting in your notebook or on your hard drive isn’t going to do you any good. You have to get that content out there. It doesn’t matter what tools you use, just pick one and go with it. For your content, Your mailing list, WordPress, or SquareSpace are all fine outlets to use.</p>

<p>I’d recommend publishing as regularly if you can. Once a week is ideal; It doesn’t take a huge commitment, and if you are writing every day then having at least one good piece of content per week should be attainable. However, while consistency is important, I favor missing a week over putting out sub-par content.</p>

<h2>9. Publish Again</h2>

<p>You can use content more than once. Here are the publishing channels I put my content on, in order of preference:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/">My Personal Site</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/letters/">My Mailing List</a></li>
<li><a href="medium.com/@gsto">Medium</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/today/author/36107098">LinkedIn Blog</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I space these out over a couple of weeks for each article. Also, every article doesn’t go on every platform; I only publish it when it makes sense. I mentioned earlier how publishing consistently helps you build a following and your expertise. When you can publish each piece of content up to four times instead of just one, publishing content consistently becomes much easier. You get a chance to get in front of more eyeballs and further grow your audience.</p>

<p>If you still aren&#8217;t sure how to start generating content, or why you should do it, leave a question in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Real World Metaprogramming Case Study]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/24/a-real-world-metaprogramming-case-study/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-24T17:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/24/a-real-world-metaprogramming-case-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Metaprogramming is one of the unique features of Ruby. Metaprogramming is an interesting concept, and a tool can save a lot of time. It can also be confusing for developers and difficult to maintain if not used properly. Here is an example of how I used Metaprogramming to solve a real-world problem and save a few hours coding.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Serializers With Duplicate Code</h2>

<p>I’m working on an application that used for managing vacation bookings. The application needs an API to integrate with some business partners. As part of the specification, dates should be returned in the API in a “YYYY-MM-DD” format.</p>

<p>To build the API, I’ll be using <a href="https://github.com/rails-api/active_model_serializers">ActiveRecord::Serializer</a> to customize the JSON output.</p>

<p>Here’s a snippet from the reservation serializer class:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">ReservationSerializer</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="ss">ActiveModel</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Serializer</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">attributes</span> <span class="ss">:starts_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:ends_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:posted_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:reserved_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">starts_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">starts_on</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">ends_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ends_on</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">posted_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">posted_on</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">reserved_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">reserved_on</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This method works because you can override any attribute in a serializer class. The problem is that this is going to be a lot of duplicate code. There are also several other API endpoints that need to deal with dates.</p>

<p>Wouldn’t be nice if we could format dates without writing a bunch of duplicate methods?</p>

<h2>Creating a Super Class That Can Create Methods</h2>

<p>In Ruby, parent classes have the ability to modify its children. We are going to use this ability to define methods on our serializers <em>without</em> writing them by hand.</p>

<p>We’ll start by creating an <code>ApplicationSerializer</code> from which each of out serializers will inherit.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">ApplicationSerializer</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="ss">ActiveModel</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:Serializer</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Inside of this superclass, we are going to define a <code>formatted_date</code> class method that we will use in our subclasses.</p>

<p>Here’s what the final result looks like:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'>   <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nc">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="nf">formatted_date</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">options</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{})</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="n">attribute</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">options</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="ss">:attribute</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="kp">nil</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="nb">format</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">options</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="ss">:format</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">attribute</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">present?</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="n">define_method</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">attribute</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>         <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">attribute</span><span class="o">].</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">format</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let’s break this down:</p>

<ul>
<li>First, we pass an options hash that will take the attribute and the format we will use. We are defaulting to the YYYY-MM-DD format, but this gives other developers the option to override that if needed.</li>
<li>Then, We check that an attribute is passed, and if so, we call the <code>define_method</code> method. We will use this to create methods in our subclass. Note that the created method’s name will be the same as the attribute.</li>
<li>Finally, We pass a block to <code>define_method</code>. This block will become the body of the new method. Note that the block uses the <code>object</code> property, which belongs to the subclass and not ApplicationSerializer.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Creating Our Dynamic Methods</h2>

<p>Inside of our <code>ReservationSerializer</code> class, we change the super class to <code>ApplicationSerializer.</code> Changing the parent class gives us the added ability to create new date attribute methods on the fly. Now writing this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="n">formatted_date</span> <span class="ss">:attribute</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:starts_on</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>is <strong>exactly</strong> the same as writing this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">starts_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">object</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">starts_on</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;%F&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Our Updated Class</h2>

<p> Let’s take a look at our new <code>ReservationSerializer</code>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">ReservationSerializer</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="no">ApplicationSerializer</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">attributes</span> <span class="ss">:starts_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:ends_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:posted_on</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:reserved_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">formatted_date</span> <span class="ss">:attribute</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:starts_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">formatted_date</span> <span class="ss">:attribute</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:ends_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">formatted_date</span> <span class="ss">:attribute</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:posted_on</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">formatted_date</span> <span class="ss">:attribute</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="ss">:reserved_on</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Not only is this cleaner to read and less duplicate code, but we have this functionality available in all of our serializers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Every Entrepreneur Needs to Understand About Risk]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/17/what-every-entrereneur-needs-to-understand-about-risk/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-17T12:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/17/what-every-entrereneur-needs-to-understand-about-risk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All businesses are inherently risky. Human beings are <em>terrible</em>  at understanding and quantifying risk. Since most entrepreneurs tend to be human beings, this causes problems. Without having a clear picture of what risk is, how to identify it, and how to quantify it, making correct decisions about your business can be hard.</p>

<p>The biggest cognitive dissonance is that people confuse variance and risk. For the purposes of this article, I am defining variance as the variety and difference and outcomes of any given probabilistic event. A six-sided die has more variance than a coin since it has six different possible outcomes while a coin has two.</p>

<p>We define risk as the losses incurred based on the outcomes of one of those events. The greater the amount of loss and the greater the chances of that loss occurring increase the amount of risk in any decision.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>How I Ran a Stable Online Poker Business</h2>

<p>My lessons on risk and variance come from my college years where I paid rent with online poker winnings. This job may seem like a huge risk job, but in fact it was as stable as my ability to play winning poker consistently and put in hours. The difference between poker players with the ability to win who did and the one’s that didn’t were the number of hands they could play in a week. As long as I was playing 10,000 hands a week, and my analytics looked good, I would make rent every single month.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers">law of large numbers</a> comes into play.  If you make winning decisions more than losing decisions enough times in a row, the probability that you will be a winner for that period climbs closer to 100%.</p>

<p>The reason playing poker feels risky is because it has a lot of variance. I could have huge wins or huge losses every day. Back then, it seems insane to put in a 5-hour shift of “work” and have my pay for that be -$300. Professional poker player/game theory professor at UCLA Chris Ferguson has a great analogy for this:</p>

<h2>The Variant Game You Can Always Win</h2>

<p>Imagine that you are a much better chess player than me (this is likely not a huge leap from reality). We agree to play a game every day for a year: First, we will play a game of chess, and wager $1 on it. Afterwards, we will flip a coin and wager $10 on it. Even you can beat me at chess 100% of the time, there will be times you will have losing days and losing weeks. However, at the end of the year, the flips balance out, and the chess games are all that determine your success.</p>

<p>The variance of this game is high, but the risk is low. Understanding the basic math principles behind situations like this allow you to get over our human nature of not understanding the situation and allow you to make correct decisions and increase your chances of success significantly.</p>

<h2>How Can Poker Player’s Reduce Risk?</h2>

<p>I used to be an active poster on <a href="http://www.twoplustwo.com/">online poker forums</a> where people would discuss strategy. Once a question was asked “how can I reduce the risk of my game?” After some discussion, a more experienced player pointed out that the player was looking to reduce <em>variance</em>, not <em>risk</em>. They could play it safe and reduce their average winning amount per 1,000 hands, and that would reduce variance. However, by reducing their average winning rate, they were reducing their long-term success and would, in fact, <em>increase</em> the amount of risk they would face. ‘</p>

<p>In fact, attempting to decrease your variance is <strong>guaranteed</strong> to lower a player’s overall win rate. Why is this? All decisions in poker can be broken down into either making a decision that wins money in the long term or decisions that lose money long-term. Optimal poker strategy is to make as many winning decisions and as few losing decisions as possible. These decisions have different amounts of variance. The only way to reduce variance would be to avoid making winning decisions with a high amount of variance, which means making more losing decisions, which means you make less money over time.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/conservative_variance.png"></p>

<p>In short, the best way to reduce risk is to make decisions that are more correct and make them more often.</p>

<h2>Applying These Lessons To Your Business</h2>

<p>On Twitter, I asked a question to my followers:</p>

<blockquote><p>Assuming all other factors are equal, would you rather take a job that pays you $5,000 every month, or a job that has a 50/50 chance of paying you either $12,000/month or $0/month?</p></blockquote>

<p>This question a simplified, although more accurate than I would like to admit allegory to comparing my time as a salaried employee to my work as an independent consultant. We’ll call these the low variance and high variance jobs.</p>

<p>On average, the highly variant job would have an expected value of $72,000/year while the first would pay out $60,000/year. Most people chose the former option, even though that decision is effectively costing them $12,000/year. Because people were anxious about variance, <strong>they chose the far less profitable option.</strong></p>

<p>To put some fears at ease, let’s look at how this would play out. In the first two months, 75% of people that chose the high variance job will have $2,000 more in the bank than the low variance people. By the end of the year, <strong>80.62%</strong> percent of people who took the higher variance job will have made the same amount or more than the people who took the lower variance job.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/12kjob_chart.png"></p>

<h2>Quantifying The Risk of Higher Variance</h2>

<p>Using the $5,000/month job as a baseline, we were able to establish a expected gain from the riskier venture, which is +$12,000 over the course of the year. But can we quantify the risk of having a bad year. What if we are one of the one of roughly five people who underperform?</p>

<p>We will consider any year where we make less than $60,000 a losing scenario. We can figure up the total value of the risk by comparing the amount of money we would miss out on * the likelihood of that event happening. There is a 12.08% chance that we only get paid four times, for a total salary of $48,000 and a loss of $12,000; We’ll quantify that as a risk of $1,405.20. The risk of getting paid zero times is actually <em>less</em> of a risk. Even though that outcome feels scarier, it is so much less likely that it only carries a risk value of $14.65. The results:</p>

<p>Expected value of higher variance job:  <strong>$12,000.00</strong></p>

<p>Expected Risk of higher variance job:    <strong>$3,474.61</strong></p>

<h2>So Why Do People Make The Wrong Decision?</h2>

<p>The reasons I got for this were a mix of fear and personal circumstances. People were afraid of missing a paycheck for a month or two. Someone was even scared of the possibility of missing all twelve. Our brains exaggerate the chance of extremes because they stand out in our minds. For example, in 2001 we had the  <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summer_of_the_Shark">Summer of the Shark</a></em> when there was a whopping <strong>one</strong> fatal shark attack that year.</p>

<p>When you see propositions that could be profitable but risky, that should be a sign to go with your <em>calculator</em>, and not with your <em>gut</em>.</p>

<p>The other reason I heard for taking the less valuable position makes sense. People didn’t have the financial cushion to take even one $0 paycheck. If they didn’t “win” during the first month of the more variant job, they would be in serious trouble. I understand taking a longer term less profitable decision if look at the risk as a 50% chance of serious financial hardship. It also means that the risk is much higher than the $3474 we mentioned earlier, and the risk would outweigh the reward.</p>

<p>This insight leads us to a bit more of a personal finance conclusion:  building a financial cushion that allows you to accept variance will make you more money in the long run. An emergency fund may not seem like an investment, but if it is the difference between you saying “yes” and saying “no” to opportunities, then it will pay off more than most investments.</p>

<p>People talk about “risk tolerance”, but what they typically mean is “variance tolerance”. You can set yourself up to have a greater variance tolerance by being smart about your money, and you can set yourself up mentally by taking a hard look at the numbers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Entrepreneurs Can Learn From Apple About Product Launches]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/09/what-entrepreneurs-can-learn-from-apple-about-product-launches/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-09T08:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/06/09/what-entrepreneurs-can-learn-from-apple-about-product-launches</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Launching a new product can induce a lot of anxiety. If you have been working on your product for some time, it is easy to let the fear of uncertainty about public reaction take over. You might decide to push the launch the back until you can one feature a bit better, a part of the design a bit cleaner, or to fix one more outstanding bug. You end up pushing your launch back to next week, next month, or in the worst case, “one day”.</p>

<p>Apple just finished their <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/6/8/8745353/apple-wwdc-2015-highlights-announcements-recap">2015 WWDC</a>, and there are some valuable lessons startups can learn from Apple’s marketing strategy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>A Launch is NOT A One-Time Event</h3>

<p>Apple hosts big events a couple of times a year for their line of products. They didn’t just launch the iPhone and iOS; they have launches every year for new apps and features. Instead of pushing a launch back so you can finish a new feature, you can instead see that as an opportunity to have a second marketing event in the future.</p>

<h3>A Launch is NOT Perfect</h3>

<p>OS X had a lot of issues when it first released, but that didn’t stop Apple from releasing it to the public. While you don’t want to move forward with a broken app, it’s important to realize that no piece of software is ever going to be perfect. This fact becomes more and truer the more complex a product becomes.</p>

<h3>You Don’t Have to Launch to Everyone All At Once</h3>

<p>Apple’s WWDC aims at building interest among developers so that they can populate the app store. They don’t announce all of their features to their whole audience; They launch once to people invested in the platform who tend to be early adopters. If you have an audience, you can launch to a small subset of people. This strategy gives you a chance to gather important customer feedback before planning your next launch.</p>

<h3>You Can Always Launch Again</h3>

<p>The iPhone didn’t gain traction until its third iteration. However, Apple could not have made it to that successful third version without the failed first two. By launching early, they were able to see what kind of issues people would run into in the wild, and make improvements based on real-world use of their product instead of making guesses in a lab. That kind of information is incredibly valuable.</p>

<h3>So… Just Do It</h3>

<p>In my experience, There is one main determining factor between my clients that have a lot of success and those that don’t: successful clients ship early and launch often, less successful clients don&#8217;t. They spend too long waiting for “perfect” launch conditions.</p>

<p> Whenever you are anxious about launching, consider the alternative. The alternative is letting your product sit quietly on a shelf, not getting customers and bringing in revenue. A bad launch that nets you one client is better than not launching at all.</p>

<p>After all, if the launch doesn’t go well, you can always launch again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drip Quick Tip: How to Change the Confirmation Link Text in Your Welcome Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/28/drip-quick-tip-how-to-change-the-confirmation-link-text-in-your-welcome-email/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-28T17:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/28/drip-quick-tip-how-to-change-the-confirmation-link-text-in-your-welcome-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are using <a href="http://glennstovall.com/recommends/drip">Drip</a> for your marketing automation, you might want to change the copy on the &#8220;Confirm Your Subscription&#8221; Link that gets sent when people fill out a form. This link is an important call-to-action, and this little piece of text can have a big impact on your subscription conversion rate. Drip doesn&#8217;t make it clear how to change this copy, but it is possible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>When you are creating a form, you will the code for the link. It looks like this:</p>

<p>{{ confirmation_link }}</p>

<p>If you want to change the link text, you can use the replace_inner_html function that is available. For example, if you wanted to change your link text to &#8220;Join the club.&#8221; you would do the following:</p>

<p>{{ confirmation_link | replace_inner_html: &#8220;Join the club.&#8221; }}</p>

<p>By using this technique, you can have more control over the experience your subscribers have when they join your list and create more enticing calls-to-action in your emails.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Get Through Your Inbox in Under 30 Minutes a Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-19T06:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your inbox is a trap. It’s a place you can go at any point in the day, spend any amount of time, and it will trick you into thinking this is time well spent. You might have your phone or a desktop application configured to ring with a siren’s call every time someone sends you a message, causing you to pay your inbox a visit and spend more time there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Email is rarely important and never urgent. I guarantee that right this second there is something you could spend your time doing that would produce more value to your customers, your family, or yourself than piddling around the inbox.</p>

<p>Email is a task that is unimportant and necessary to your business. While most people can’t slay the beast, it can be tamed. You can reduce the amount of noise if your inbox, and put a system in place so that you can get through your inbox effectively, and get on with your life.</p>

<p>I’ve lost entire weekdays to my inbox before, and I realized I needed a change. Here’s how I tackle my emails in just 30 minutes a day. It takes some time to get going but getting a good email system in place will pay dividends for life. You’ll have more time to focus on what’s important, and you’ll impress many a middle manager.</p>

<h2>Step 1: Move Towards Inbox Zero</h2>

<blockquote><p>opens inbox.</p>

<p>sees 3,000 messages.</p>

<p><em>{eye twitches}</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Nothing is going to be allowed to live in our inbox anymore. <strong>Look at your inbox as a list of emails that need to be handled, not as a place to store information.</strong> Getting there can be hard, but once you are there, it is easy to stay there.</p>

<h3>The fastest way to inbox zero:</h3>

<ol>
<li>Open your email program of choice.</li>
<li>Select all messages.</li>
<li>Click ‘archive’.</li>
<li>You’re done!</li>
</ol>


<p>Archiving or deleting all emails of a certain age is declaring <strong>email bankruptcy</strong>. It’s drastic, but you can’t tell me it doesn’t work. It’s dangerous as there are some emails in your inbox right that you probably should read and get a response. If you can’t take this step, then you can archive any email that is 15, 30, or 60 or more days old. That’ll make cleaning the whole inbox easier.</p>

<p>I’ll talk about how to deal with the remaining emails at the end. But first let’s look at two techniques you can use right now to cut down on the noise in your inbox.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Kill Your Notifications</h2>

<blockquote><p><em>gets tagged in a photo on Facebook.</em></p>

<p><em>pop-up on Facebook: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>email inbox: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “You’ve got mail!”</em></p>

<p><em><eye twitches></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Are there any apps you check daily? Twitter? Facebook? Productive ones? They have their notification system. Deal with Facebook notifications during a time you have to peruse Facebook. Mark Zuckerberg has taken up enough of your time, Don’t let him have some of your valuable inbox time as well.</p>

<p>Go through your common applications and turn off email notifications. Most of these notifications should have an ‘unsubscribe’ link or links to disable them somewhere in them.</p>

<p>If there are applications that you don’t check regularly, and you need to receive email notifications from them, they are exempt from this process. But if you find yourself deleting a notification for the 12th time, take an extra second, and take the steps necessary to disable it. If it is not easy to disable, you can always set up a filter to delete them automatically for you.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Quarantine Newsletters</h2>

<p>I’m a bit of a newsletter junkie.  While there are plenty of good newsletters filled with valuable information. But that doesn’t mean when I am quickly moving through my inbox I want to take 15 minutes to read an in-depth article, regardless of the value of the content.</p>

<p>The next time you receive a newsletter, you need to ask yourself  a single question:</p>

<h3>Is the newsletter valuable to me?</h3>

<p><strong>If the answer is no, then unsubscribe</strong>. Life is too short to spend it on crummy newsletters.</p>

<p><strong>If the answer is yes, then tag and archive it.</strong> I tag mine “Newsletters to Read” and send them automatically to another folder. When I want to read newsletters, I set aside time for them. If you don’t find yourself willing or able to make time to read newsletters, then they weren’t as valuable as you thought when you subscribed.</p>

<h2>Step 4: Process Your Inbox</h2>

<p>Now it’s time to deal with what’s left. Go through each of your emails from oldest to newest, no skipping. You are going to deal with every single one of them, so there is no point in skipping.</p>

<p>This process will take a little while to get through at first. It gets easier with time, I promise. If you still have hundreds of emails in your inbox, then tackle a few, and come back later.</p>

<p>Once you get to each email, you <em>must</em> decide to do one of the following things with it:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Act on it.</strong> Can this email be dealt with by write a short response? If so, write a short response, hit send and archive the message.</li>
<li><strong>Archive/Delete it.</strong> If the message only needed to read and not acted upon, then read it. If you may need to reference the email later, then archive it. If not, delete it. If you are deleting it, ask yourself if it is a newsletter or notification you can do without, and if so, take the steps to prevent getting it again.</li>
<li><strong>Defer It.</strong> Sometimes emails don’t need immediate attention. If this is the case, You can use Mailbox or Boomerang to ‘snooze’ emails until you can deal with them.</li>
<li><strong>Delegate It.</strong> Delegate your email either to another person, another information repository or another task tracker. For example, I may forward an email to Evernote, or to Asana if it the email mentions a task that I need to come back.</li>
</ul>


<p>Repeat until you are at inbox zero. Now go grab yourself a coffee, you’ve earned it.</p>

<h2>Step 5: Timebox</h2>

<p>Once you have gotten used to the process, you need to set aside time that is exclusively for email and remove email from the other parts of your day. I have two 15-minute periods, at 10am and 4pm.</p>

<p>This strategy is ideal for me as I have to keep a maker’s <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">schedule</a> (long uninterrupted work) instead of a manager’s schedule (small meetings and tasks). If you need more time periods in the day or more time allowed then go for it. I fudge on my schedule when I am in heavy <strong>sales mode</strong>. It’s like beast mode but with less aggression and more cold emailing.</p>

<p>If you used to constantly checking email, it could be hard to drop down to just 30 minutes a day. You can’t go the gym and start with a 300-pound squat, you have to work your way there. Here are some baby steps I recommend to make the transition:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Don’t check email first thing in the morning.</strong> The first hour is a rudder for the rest of your day. Checking email first thing is a great way to throw yourself off course. Focus on spending your first hour being productive, and come back to email afterward.</li>
<li><strong>Turn off phone and desktop notifications.</strong> You want to make checking your email a <em>proactive</em> choice, not a <em>reactive</em> choice. Turn off phone notifications, desktop notifications, and don’t keep a browser tab open in the background.</li>
<li><strong>Don’t check email before bed.</strong> I have never done this and then thought “that was a good decision. I am glad I did that.”</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you’ve done this, you’ve changed your relationship with your inbox. You don’t work on your inbox’s schedule; it works on yours. Email doesn’t control you; you control your email.</p>

<h2>BONUS Step 6: Automation</h2>

<p>These are some additional steps that I use to automate and streamline the time I spend in my email inbox.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Use canned responses.</strong> <a href="http://time.com/12436/quick-gmail-trick-pre-write-email-messages-with-canned-responses/">Canned responses</a> are a Gmail Labs feature. They allow you to save and reuse common responses and messages you send. I use these for common use cases such as follow-ups, initial emails, and even snippets of emails, such as links to my <a href="http://glennstovall.com/case-studies/">portfolio</a> and <a href="http://careers.stackoverflow.com/glennstovall">CV</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Write short responses.</strong> Email is simply a way for people to try and get your time for their agenda. Remember that when you are sending email, you are doing the same, and you should be respecting of other people’s time. Emails should rarely be more than a few sentences.</li>
<li><strong>Take the “<a href="http://unlessiheardifferently.com/">Unless I Hear Otherwise</a>” Approach.</strong> Instead of offering options and opinions, offer a choice with an out. Compare these two emails:</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><em>The slow email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of reasons X, Y, and Z. Which would you prefer?</p>

<p><em>The productive email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of {reasons}.  <strong>Unless I hear otherwise</strong> by close of business, I’ll move forward with option A.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Remove the Hash from Angular Routes in Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/03/16/how-to-remove-the-hash-from-angular-routes-in-rails/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-16T19:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/03/16/how-to-remove-the-hash-from-angular-routes-in-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When building client side applications, your URLs are prepended with a hash. Removing this can make your routes more user friendly and more easily crawled by search engines. Here is how you can remove the hash from your routes in an Angular app built on Ruby on Rails, and use the standard URL structure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Step 0: Our example Application</h2>

<p>We’ll look at a recipe site for our example application. In our application, we’ll have a homepage, a recipe route that shows us all of the recipes, and a route for single recipes. Here is our application configuration:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'> <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">app</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">angular</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">module</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;recipeapp&quot;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">config</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="s2">&quot;$routeProvider&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nx">$routeProvider</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">when</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="nx">templateUrl</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;templates/index.html&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="nx">controller</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;IndexController&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">})</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">when</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;/recipes/, {</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">       templateUrl: &quot;</span><span class="nx">templates</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">recipes</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">html</span><span class="s2">&quot;,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">       controller: &quot;</span><span class="nx">RecipesController</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">     })</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">     .when(&quot;</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">recipes</span><span class="o">/:</span><span class="nx">id</span><span class="s2">&quot;, {</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">       templateUrl: &quot;</span><span class="nx">templates</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">recipe_show</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">html</span><span class="s2">&quot;,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">       controller: &quot;</span><span class="nx">RecipeShowController</span><span class="err">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="p">}]);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step 1: Remove The Hash</h2>

<p>First, we will enable [HTML5 Mode] in our AngularJS application. This will remove the hash from our URLs. Include <code>$locationProvider</code> in your module’s configuration, and set the mode to true.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'> <span class="nx">app</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">config</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="s1">&#39;$routeProvider&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s1">&#39;$locationProvider&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">$locationProvider</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nx">$locationProvider</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">html5mode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="c1">// ...</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}]);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step 2: Configure Rails To Handle Angular Routes</h2>

<p>The above will work for cases when the user navigates from one part of the AngularJS application to another. However, if they try to navigate directly, they will get an error. If the user tries to navigate to <code>/recipes/1</code> directly, or hits refresh on that page, the request is sent to the Ruby on Rails router instead of Angular.</p>

<p>To fix this, we need to capture those requests. In you <code>app/config/routes.rb</code> at the end:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">get</span> <span class="s1">&#39;/\*path&#39;</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">redirect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;/?goto=%{path}&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This will cause any uncaught routes to get redirected as a query string, which will be passed to the Angular router.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Handle Rails Redirects</h2>

<p>Angular needs to know how to handle these routes, so we will add a call to the <code>otherwise()</code> method of <code>$routeProvider</code>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'> <span class="nx">$routeProvider</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">otherwise</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nx">redirectTo</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">current</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">path</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">search</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">search</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">goto</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">return</span> <span class="s1">&#39;/&#39;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">search</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="kr">goto</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">return</span> <span class="s1">&#39;/&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now any URL will get redirected to Angular, which will handle the route. This way you don’t have to maintain two lists of routes, and you can use standard URL formats in your application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[18 Tools I Would Use to Build a SaaS Product Today]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/02/23/18-tools-i-would-use-to-build-a-saas-product-today/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T16:21:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/02/23/18-tools-i-would-use-to-build-a-saas-product-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems like these days everyone is wanting to build a software as a service app. The siren’s call of monthly recurring revenue is hard to ignore.</p>

<p>SaaS products are a complex undertaking. I’ve worked on them before and seen how all the moving parts have to interact. There are plenty of tools, libraries, frameworks, and even <em>other</em> SaaS products out there to help you along the way. Where do you even get started?</p>

<p>If I were to start building a SaaS application today, and I say today because technology is always moving quickly, here are the tools I would use to build a SaaS application. Most of these are focused on the technical aspect of getting the software built, and not on sales and marketing, which is another listicle entirely.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Server Side Development</h2>

<h3>1. Ruby on Rails</h3>

<p>Ruby on Rails is my back end framework of choice. It’s not always the most efficient, and sometimes it gets in your way instead of helping. But the community, suite of tools, and ability to handle common web application problems easily makes it a winner in my book.</p>

<h3>2. PostgreSQL</h3>

<p>PostgreSQL is the default for Ruby on Rails applications, and the best database I’ve ever used. The fact that it has support for JSON objects makes using it over other SQL based solutions like MySQL, and NoSQL solutions like MongoDB a no-brainer decision 99% of the time.</p>

<h2>Client-Side Development</h2>

<h3>3. Bower</h3>

<p>Ruby on Rails has built-in support for package management in the form of bundler and Gemfiles. However, front end packages in the form of gems are often created and maintained by 3rd party developers, which means they are often buggy, out-of-date, incomplete, or non-existant. Bower is more reliable. There are tools, such as the <a href="https://github.com/rharriso/bower-rails"><code>bower-rails</code></a> gem, that help you integrate bower with the Rails asset pipeline.</p>

<h3>4. Foundation by Zurb</h3>

<p>I find <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Foundation</a> by <a href="http://zurb.com/">Zurb</a> to be cleaner and simpler to use than Bootstrap by Twitter. Plus, you get the added in benefit of you unstyled front end looking slightly more unique than other application’s unstyled front ends! They also have a new version of Foundation that is aimed specifically at applications, and not just websites.</p>

<h3>5. AngularJS (maybe)</h3>

<p>Some applications have a structure where the UI is built as a client side web application, and the server is just an API server that handles data operations. This structure is good for some, but not all applications. If the app needs a dedicated client side front end, then <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/">AngularJS</a> is my choice.</p>

<h2>Hosting and Systems Administration</h2>

<h3>6. Heroku</h3>

<p>Heroku is pricey, but worth it. While I pay a steep Heroku bill month-to-month, it gives me more time to focus on creative and decisions, and less on system administration. If you or someone that works for you is handy at  maintaining servers, this may not be the best choice for you. Plus, it “scales”. Startups love things that scale.</p>

<h3>7.Amazon Web Services (Specifically S3)</h3>

<p>I use amazon for hosting my assets, such as images, or even entire static sites. The cost is cheap and flexible. However, if you are using Heroku I find it worthwhile to go with your own setup and not pay their fee.</p>

<h3>8. Namecheap</h3>

<p>Namecheap is thebest place I have found to manage domains and SSL certificates. Both are a requirement for a web based SaaS app.</p>

<h2>Payment</h2>

<h3>9.Stripe</h3>

<p>Stripe is an easy to use payment gateway, both for managing payment, and integrating it as a developer. I even use it to manage invoice payments from my clients.</p>

<h3>10.Payola</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.payola.io/">Payola</a> is a gem used to integrate with Stripe, created by the guy that literally wrote <a href="https://www.masteringmodernpayments.com/">the book on the subject</a>.</p>

<h2>Email</h2>

<h3>11. Drip</h3>

<p><a href="http://glennstovall.com/recommends/drip">Drip</a> is a powerful marketing automation platform that doesn’t cost an arm and a leg. I’d use Drip for both marketing emails to bring customers on board, and also to set up campaigns for situations such as user onboarding and feature adoption.</p>

<h3>12. Mandrill</h3>

<p>Mandrill, a spinoff service of Mailchimp, is great for setting up transactional emails. Drip could be used for this purpose as well, and I’ve yet to experiment to see which one works better. If email is a heavy part of your marketing structure, I would rely on Drip exclusively. If you are sending one-off emails, I would use Mandrill.</p>

<h2>Testing</h2>

<h3>13. RSpec</h3>

<p>RSpec is my personal favorite testing tool for Ruby on Rails. It makes writing tests painless and reduced friction means more tests get written.</p>

<h3>14. Capybara</h3>

<p>Once you have used RSpec for unit testing, Capybara makes sure those individual pieces work together nicely.</p>

<h3>15. Jasmine</h3>

<p>What RSpec accomplishes on the server-side, Jasmine accomplishes on the client-side. It also plays nicely with AngularJS, if you decided to go that route.</p>

<h3>16. Teaspoon</h3>

<p>Teaspoon is a gem that allows you to run client side tests in the same manner you run your server side tests.</p>

<h2>Analytics</h2>

<h3>17. Google Analytics</h3>

<p>A good standard, but not enough by itself these days. Anyone who wants to dig a bit deeper into the behavior of their application or shared my hatred of <code>[keyword not provided]</code> knows what I’m talking about.</p>

<h3>18. Mixpanel</h3>

<p>Mixpanel makes event tracking a breeze and is free when you are first getting started. Are people actually using that new feature you built? Do people actually share with those brightly colored share buttons? Which features convince people to renew their accounts and upgrade? Mixpanel will help you answer that question.</p>

<h3>19. Baremetrics (eventually)</h3>

<p>“One click and you get dozens of valuable metrics from your Stripe account”. Whoever does the copywriting for Baremetrics is right on the nose with their description. Baremetrics isn’t valuable until you have enough paying customers that the data matters, but as soon as you do, I would highly recommend implementing their service.</p>

<p>What would you add to your SaaS toolbelt? <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">Hit me up and let me know</a>. I love geeking out about this kind of thing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Reliable Web Apps Show Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/01/05/building-reliable-web-apps-show-notes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T09:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/01/05/building-reliable-web-apps-show-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/js-test-talk.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>These are notes and links from a presentation I gave to the Developers of Athens on testing client side applications.</p>

<!--more-->


<div style='margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;max-width:25em;'>
<iframe src="http://glennstovall.com//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/43211030" width="476" height="400" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="display:block"></iframe>
</div>


<h2>Tools</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://nodejs.org/download/">NodeJS Download</a></li>
<li><a href="http://gruntjs.com/getting-started">Grunt: JavaScript Task Runner</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jasmine.github.io/">Jasmine: JavaScript Testing Framework</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jquery.com/">jQuery</a></li>
<li><a href="http://phantomjs.org/">PhantomJS</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Addon Libraribes</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/gruntjs/grunt-contrib-jasmine">grunt-contrib-jasmine</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jasmine/jasmine/tree/master/dist">jasmine standalone</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/velesin/jasmine-jquery">jasmine-jquery</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jasmine.github.io/2.1/ajax.html">jasmine-ajax</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Source Code</h2>

<p>The source code for an example application can be found on this page:</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/GSto/reliable-client-side">Example Application</a></p>

<h2>Further Reading</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup/">Yeoman + AngularJS + Foundation: A Modern Front End Setup</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/26/testing-angularjs-with-karma-plus-jasmine/">Testing AngularJS With Karma + Jasmine</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/">AngularJS: An Overview</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 Postmortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/28/2014-postmortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-28T14:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/28/2014-postmortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every Year I take a look back at my business, and do the same exercise I do with every client project: a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmortem_documentation#Elements_of_a_project_post-mortem">postmortem</a>. I ask myself 3 questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>What went well?</li>
<li>What went wrong?</li>
<li>What steps should I take in the future?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is a valuable writing exercise, and I’d strongly encourage you to do the same. This is my postmortem of 2014, as well as a review of how I did on my goals I set for myself at the beginning of the year.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Did I Hit My 2013 Goals?</h2>

<p>I was listening to <a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/episodes/episode-214-our-goals-for-2015">Episode 214 of Startups For The Rest Of Us</a>, where the hosts Rob Walling and Mike Taber look back at their goals they set for the year, and give themselves between 0 and 1 points based on wether or not they felt they achieved that goal. Before I get into my postmortem, I wanted to go through the exact same exercise.</p>

<h3>Goal: Generate a Stream of Product Based Income</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 0 points</h4>

<p>It seems like every year I have a vague goal of launching a product, and I tend not to do it. While I did launch a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/offerings/overnight-site/">Productized Service</a>, I didn’t create any kind of profitable project this year.</p>

<h3>Goal: Better Time Management</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 0.5 points</h4>

<p>I’ll give myself half a point here. While I made some improvements in managing my time, I still feel like there is a lot of room for improvement. Some good steps forward I have made has been more diligent about scheduling my time, and eliminating tasks that kept me busy, but weren’t productive.</p>

<h3>Goal: Keeping an Eye on Business Metrics</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>This was mostly in regards to sales and marketing. I started using <a href="http://bit.ly/1itwiuw">PipeDrive</a> to both systemize and keep track of the numbers on my sales funnel. PipeDrive also allows you to add custom fields to your leads, so I have started tracking 4 data points on each lead that I come into contact with:</p>

<ul>
<li>Size of the company</li>
<li>Company vertical</li>
<li>Project type</li>
<li>Source of lead</li>
</ul>


<p>This way I don’t only see how many leads I am getting, but I can drill down on which leads are the most profitable, which convert the best, and what are the best sources of leads that convert.</p>

<h3>Goal: A More Defined Sales and Marketing Process</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>See PipeDrive above. Now I have a defined sales process, email templates that I use for communicating to leads and prospects at various points in the conversation. This has allowed me to spend less time selling and more time creating value. I also feel that I have a strong framework for writing proposals.</p>

<p>Since I’ve implemented these practices, the number of leads I get have increased, and my conversion rate as more than doubled.</p>

<h3>Goal: Have a Better Pricing Structure</h3>

<h4>Verdict: 1 point</h4>

<p>In addition to raising my rates last year, I have eliminated work billed by the hour with the exception of some legacy clients. I finally implemented this towards the end of the year, and so far the results have been tremendous. I feel happier working not having to punch a time clock, client relationships are better, and I feel I am providing more valuable work.</p>

<p>I did experiment with daily and weekly billing, and that for the most part was a bust in my experience. Some people swear by weekly billing, however I found that many prospects didn’t “get” it, and it was just causing more friction in the sales process.</p>

<h3>Total Score: 3.5 / 5</h3>

<h2>What Went Well in 2014</h2>

<h3>Putting Myself on a Salary to Eliminate Feast and Famine</h3>

<p>In 2013, I would divide up the bounty of each paid invoice into a few different buckets: a percentage for the company coffers, a percentage for Uncle Sam, and a percentage in my pocket. Now, I pay myself a monthly stipend regardless of income. This makes personal budgeting and financial planning easier, reduces stress during the lean months. This also means that I have more cash on hand in my company account that I can invest back into the business.</p>

<h3>Diligent Practice of Inbox Zero &amp; GTD</h3>

<p>Email used to be one of those tasks that was a large time sink for me. Then I started practicing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z9UjeTMb3Yk">inbox zero</a>.  Now I check email twice a day, and each time I am able to get though my inbox quickly. <a href="http://www.mailboxapp.com/">Mailbox</a> is a great app if you’d like to start practicing it.</p>

<p>On that same note, I started implementing the principles of <a href="http://gettingthingsdone.com/">Getting Things Done</a>, which is essentially the principles of inbox zero applied to your to do list. I now have one task management system, and everything I need to do goes into an inbox. The inbox is processed daily, and then tasks are knocked off. Since doing this I’ve had almost nothing fall through the cracks, and I feel less stressed and more on top of things. I use the Mac/iOS app <a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/">Things</a> to manage my to do lists.</p>

<h3>An Online Presence I’m Happy About</h3>

<p>I’ve gone through multiple redesigns of this site, and my company site, Concordant Solutions. I finally <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">decided to only manage one site</a>, and give it a facelift. It’s an ongoing process, but right now I feel like my site is the best it has ever been.</p>

<h3>Writing and Publishing More Content</h3>

<p>I invested a lot more in writing content this year. I’ve had some articles gain some traction, including making the Medium.com top 100 one month. I also published a free eBook that has been downloaded over 1,000 times. Both of them have helped me reach more people, and have started many a great conversation. Here are my most popular posts in 2014:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@gsto/how-i-used-writing-to-double-my-freelancing-rate-as-a-programmer-7b321bedecdc">How I Used Writing to Double my Rate as a Freelancer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">The Freelance Pricing Handbook</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/">5 Ways to Build a $200,000 Consultancy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">Why Multiple Packages in Your Proposals Instantly Increase Conversions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/20140917184430-36107098-how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-opened-and-convert?trk=prof-post">How to Write More Personal Emails to Your List That Get Opened And Convert</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Building an Audience</h3>

<p>While I had good intentions as far as releasing products went, I wanted to start building an audience of people beforehand. While the product idea never came to fruition, I’m glad that I started this. I have had some <em>fantastic</em> conversations, Got invites to be a speaker on a webinar, and get to keep in touch and build relationships with people at scale.</p>

<p>Building an audience also gives everything else I do more purpose. Now writing articles isn’t just about sharing content, it’s an entryway to building relationships.</p>

<h3>Joining a Mastermind</h3>

<p>Being self employed is lonely work. If there is one thing I miss from the employed world (in fact, I think this is the <strong>only</strong> thing), It is having people to relate to what you are doing, and  being able to reach out for help.</p>

<p>This year I joined a mastermind with three other freelancers. Each week we hop on a Google Hangout, and discuss what is going on in our business. It gives each of a chance to get a few extra pairs of eyes on anything we’re working on, and a forum to even about frustrations we wouldn’t otherwise. I’ve learned just as much, if not more from the conversations I’ve had in these mastermind meetings than I have all the books and podcasts I’ve consumed this year.</p>

<h2>What Went Wrong in 2014</h2>

<h3>A Sabbatical That Went Unintentionally Long</h3>

<p>After a couple of large projects and heavy workload, I became burned out towards the middle of the year. I had some money in the bank, and decided to schedule some time off to rest and invest some time in my business. This turned out to be the worst decision I made all year.</p>

<p>Firstly, trying to take time off and invest in my business was a poor plan. It really should have been one or the other. Secondly, It just enough small jobs rolled in that I didn’t really get to relax or make very money, leaving me dealing with the worst of both worlds. Finally, it’s hard to build up momentum after stopping. What was going to be a break of a few weeks ended up being more like a break of a few <em>months</em>, which really put pressure on both my cash flow and sanity.</p>

<p>On the bright side, this was also the moment that led me to do a lot of introspection and make some decisions about what my business was going to look like in the future.</p>

<h3>A Company Brand That Was Dead In The Water</h3>

<p>Last year I formed an LLC and formed a company site called “Concordant Solutions”. Both the site and the brand was a failure in every metric I can think to measure it in. Managing two sites was more time consuming than managing one. Any content I wrote for my company site tended to fall flat, and did not generate leads of any sort. Explaining to people in person that I was “company” that was just one person, and what the hell “Concordant” means became exhausting and distracting.</p>

<p>For now, I’m back to being plain old me. The name Concordant Solutions now only exists in the world of contracts and invoices.</p>

<h3>The 30 Day Publishing Challenge</h3>

<p>In September, I decided to join Colin Devroe in taking a <a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/9527/blogging-every-weekday-for-30-days">challenge to publish something every weekday for 30 days.</a> While I did finish the challenge, (and wrote a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem/">postmortem</a> about that too), I don’t think it was that valuable of an exercise. It led me to publishing a lot of content that wasn’t all that good, and took up a lot of my time.</p>

<p>I think that if you were tempted to do something similar, writing every 30 days would be a much better goal.</p>

<h3>I Didn’t Launch a Product</h3>

<p>This is something that has been on my goal list for a few years, and one I haven’t been able to capitalize on. I started work on a few, but I was usually stopped by the fear that I was launching a product for product’s sake, and not because I was unsure that It would be valuable. This is a fear I need to get over, so I can at least try to launch something to generate a more passive revenue stream.</p>

<h3>Problems With Client Communication and Expectations</h3>

<p>I had some client relationships this year that didn’t go as well as either one of us would have liked.I did a poor job of managing the client relationship and their expectations. Since these experiences I’ve worked hard at streamlining my communication and pricing structure to support a better relationship.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, the relationship between a consultant and their client should be a partnership. However, I think we all do things that tend to frame it instead as an adversarial relationship.</p>

<p>My shift away from hourly billing was based on these principles. When billing based on time, the client has a financial incentive to decrease your contribution to a product, while it gives you a financial incentive to increase it. Right off the bat, this is the kind of adversarial relationship I was unknowingly fostering.</p>

<h2>Steps Moving Forward</h2>

<h3>A More Systemized Business</h3>

<p>This is my primary goal for 2015. This year I learned about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_operating_procedure">standard operating procedures</a>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/E-Myth-Revisited-Michael-E-Gerber-ebook/dp/B000RO9VJK/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;sr=&amp;qid=">how to separate yourself from your business.</a> While I have written some procedures, My coverage is far from complete. The ones I have written have been valuable, and I really want to double down on this.</p>

<p>Standard operating procedures are just step one in building a more scalable, effective business. Even just by themselves, they reduce the mental overhead of making decisions, much like <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/nov/10/obama-zuckerberg-us-president-facebook-founder">wearing the same clothes everyday</a>. But beyond that, they enable you to hand work off or automate. Once you have a defined process, you can hand that work off to a virtual assistant, a subcontractor, or a python script. (Standard operating procedures are basically Python scripts for human beings).</p>

<h3>Strategic Outsourcing</h3>

<p>When I started this business two years ago, if you asked me which parts of my job would be the first to be outsourced, I would not have guessed the actual production work. After all, writing code is <em>what I do</em>. Or at least that is how I used to look at it.</p>

<p>Now, I see that I have much more interest and provide more value in dealing with the “big picture” issues of both my own company and of my clients. Neither one of those requires me to write code.</p>

<p>I don’t plan on removing myself from writing code completely, nor do I plan to be a middle man that farms out work to the lowest bidder on the other side of the world. What I <strong>do</strong> plan on doing is sending well defined parts of projects off to other implementers, and relying more on people that have stronger skills than I do, such as graphic design.</p>

<p>I fully expect this to enable to provide more value to every one of my clients than I have in the past two years.</p>

<h3>Better Positioning</h3>

<p>This year, I made some good steps moving from “guy who writes code” to “guy who solves problems”. This year, I want to hammer out exactly what kinds of problems those are. There is more than enough work available in the world, and being a generalist does more harm than good. In the coming year I hope to have a more clear positioning statement and brand. That might a new job title, it might mean a new company brand. What it definitely means is a marketing strategy that is laser focused on a particular set of problems that a particular set of people have.</p>

<h3>Investing In My Business</h3>

<p>I invested significantly more in my education and in networking than I did last year, and both paid off in spades. Many books I’ve read, groups I’ve joined, and services I’ve used have paid for themselves many times over. This year I’m excited to find more opportunities where I believe I can make my money work for me.</p>

<h3>25% Revenue Growth</h3>

<p>Self-explanitory.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Only 3 Numbers That Matter To A Freelancer's Bottom Line]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/16/the-only-3-numbers-that-matter-to-a-freelancers-bottom-line/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T12:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/12/16/the-only-3-numbers-that-matter-to-a-freelancers-bottom-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>And 5 Tips to Improve Each One</h3>

<p>The end of the year will be here soon. It&#8217;s a time to reflect on how the past year went, and plan for the next year. There are three numbers that are the determining factors for your bottom line. By understanding these numbers, you will know what metrics you need to move in order to get the business results you want. By doubling just one of three numbers, you&#8217;ll double you revenue, without doubling your workload. So instead of saying &#8220;I want to make more money next year&#8221;, by the end of this email I want you to say <strong>how</strong> you plan to make more money next year.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Metric #1: Number of Leads</h2>

<p>You want to measure this as number of leads per month or per quarter. A <strong>lead</strong> is defined as any person who has expressed interest and capability in purchasing your services. If you respond to a listing on a job board, that is not a lead. However, if the person you contacted responds to you and wants to continue the conversation, that is a lead. If you are consistently turning some of leads into customers, then more leads will always equal more customers, which equals more revenue.</p>

<h2>Metric #2: Conversion Rate</h2>

<p>Your <strong>conversion rate</strong> is the percentage of leads that you convert into customers. Don&#8217;t get discouraged if this number is low. I consider 10% to be a good conversion rate, and anything above that to be excellent. By increasing your conversion rate, you can increase the number of customers that you bring in, without increasing the amount of time you spend on sales. If you need 3 customers a month to make enough money, and your conversion rate is 5%, then you need to start conversations with 60 potential leads a month. If your conversion rate is 10%, then you only need 30.</p>

<p> <em>(If you don&#8217;t use a CRM to track your leads and conversion, I would highly recommend getting one. There are hundreds to choose from, but I like <a href="http://bit.ly/1itwiuw">PipeDrive</a>)</em></p>

<h2>Metric #3: Customer Lifetime Value</h2>

<p><strong>Customer lifetime value</strong> (often shortened to &#8216;LTV&#8217;) is the average amount that a customer pays you as long as you two do business together. If you don&#8217;t know what this number is, you can calculate it by adding up the total amount each client has payed you for all invoices, and then find the average. For example, let&#8217;s say you bill weekly at $2,000 per week. Your last quarter looks like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Client A: 3 weeks of work:   $6,000</li>
<li>Client B: 5 weeks of work:  $10,000</li>
<li>Client C: 2 week of work:    $4,000</li>
<li>Your customer LTV:       $6,667</li>
</ul>


<p>The more you make per customer, then the less customers you need to make revenue.Once you know these numbers, you can project your income for 2015. The formula looks like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$leads_per_month * $conversion_rate * $customer_ltv * 12 = $annual_revenue. </span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>So, let&#8217;s say you made around $50,000. Your year might look like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>8 leads per month * 10% conversion rate * $5000 LTV * 12 = $48,000</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<p>So, what if next year you want to make closer to $100,000? Instead of setting an arbitrary goal, now you can focus on moving the needle on a particular metric. If you wanted to double you revenue, you either need to figure out how to get more leads, increase your conversion rate, or increase the average amount a customer pays you.</p>

<h3>Tips for Increasing Leads</h3>

<ul>
<li>Adding an email capture to your website, start building a newsletter, and bring in clients that way.</li>
<li>Send more emails out on job boards that you frequent.</li>
<li>Give a seminar or a talk to prospective customers.</li>
<li>Double down on whatever is currently working for you. If you meet people in person, go to even more events.</li>
<li>Get more referrals, by asking for them. Reach out to past clients and current colleagues.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Tips for Increasing Your Conversion Rate</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">Add packaging to your proposals</a>, in order to give clients more ways to say yes.</li>
<li>What have clients said before about why they decided to hire you? Work that into your emails and conversations.</li>
<li>Do clients trust you? Add some convincing work to your portfolio, or get testimonials from past clients.</li>
<li>Add calls to action to all of your client emails. Always make it clear how a client should proceed to move towards working with you.</li>
<li>Get comfortable saying this sentence to prospects: &#8220;So, what is going to take to get you to become a client of mine?&#8221;</li>
</ul>


<h3>Tips for Increasing Customer Lifetime Value</h3>

<ul>
<li>Raising your rate. Easy-peasy.</li>
<li>Find ways to provide more value for your clients. For example, if you are a developer, providing documentation for other developers or an &#8221;instruction manual&#8217; to your client can be a value add that you should price for accordingly.- Offer auxilery services. If you design sites, you could also learn to handle some of the copy writing or data entry for the client.</li>
<li>Sell retainers. Find a way you can provide value to your clients on a monthly basis, and sell clients on those services.</li>
<li>Up-sell. The best time to add someone to the beginning of your sales pipeline is right after a completed project. If you can think of another project that would be beneficial to the client, or a retainer mentioned above, that would be the perfect time to sell them on it.</li>
</ul>


<p>What are your goals for 2015? And <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">what could I do to help you achieve them?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Decide Between Squarespace and a Web Designer]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/11/14/how-to-decide-between-squarespace-and-a-web-designer/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T00:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/11/14/how-to-decide-between-squarespace-and-a-web-designer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/squarespace_vs_designer.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>You have a new idea you want to explore. Or maybe you are about to open the doors on your new brick and mortar business. Either way, you need a new website. I used to advise clients against &#8220;do it yourself website builders&#8221;,
such as <a href="http://www.squarespace.com/">Squarespace</a>, <a href="http://www.weebly.com/">Weebly</a>, and <a href="http://www.wix.com/">Wix</a>. But in the past few years, the tools have evolved into a solution that is a good fit for a lot of people.So, when should you use a tool like SquareSpace, and when is a professional web designer worth the investment?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Our Two Options</h2>

<p>There are a lot of options out there for hosting your own site, and for building your own site. To keep this article simple, I am going to compare two particular approaches: using <a href="http://www.squarespace.com/">Squarespace</a> to build your site, and hiring a designer to build a custom hosted site using <a href="https://wordpress.com/">WordPress</a></p>

<h2>When To Use Squarespace</h2>

<h3>When you just need something simple.</h3>

<p>If all you need is a homepage, a couple images, and a contact form, then using SquaresSpace will suit your needs just fine. Squarespace has limited functionality, but it isn&#8217;t much of a limitation if you don&#8217;t need to go beyond it.</p>

<h3>When the site you are building is temporary.</h3>

<p> If you are making a site for an event, or for a limited time offering, then I wouldn&#8217;t invest too much time or money into it. In those cases, a quick page on SquareSpace, or possibly a landing page service such as <a href="http://leadpages.net">LeadPages</a> would suit your needs better.</p>

<h3>When you need your site up TODAY.</h3>

<p> If you hire a designer to build your site for you, there is the process of getting a contract signed, figuring out money, defining the design and scope, etc. With Squarespace, you can have a site up and running in just a couple of hours.</p>

<h3>When the ROI doesn&#8217;t make sense.</h3>

<p> How much money is your website going to make you this year? This is an important consideration when building your site. Web designers can be expensive. If you don&#8217;t think your website will bring in at least $5,000 in revenue to your business, I would go for squarespace.</p>

<h1>When to Hire a Designer</h1>

<h3>When you need the consulting and expertise.</h3>

<p> The most important part of hiring a professional is not the final product they deliver, it&#8217;s the expertise that goes into it. Any web developer or designer should have the experience to help guide you along the way, and make sure you know how to best wield the tool they are building for you.</p>

<h3>You need complex functionality (or you might one day).</h3>

<p> While Squarespace is good for simple sites, if you have more complex needs, then you may want to consider hosting your own solution. The power of WordPress is that it is almost infinitely customizable and extendable. Even if you don&#8217;t need much right out of the gate, if you plan on adding functionality down the line, you should consider starting with a hosted solution, in order to prevent the additional cost of migrating from one platform to another.</p>

<h3>You need user rights management.</h3>

<p> Who is going to be writing the content for your website? If it is just you, then Squarespace will work fine. However, if you have employees or interns that will be working on the site, and you want them to be able to contribute without giving them the keys to everything, you will need a more robust solution such as WordPress. WordPress allows you to give users different levels of rights, so you can invite people to contribute without giving them ability to change things such as design.</p>

<h3>When you find a worthwhile investment.</h3>

<p> Hiring a designer, and building custom functionality are more costly, but is it an investment that will pay off for your business? If you find a designer or have functionality that you believe will generate more revenue for your business, then it is one of the best investments you can make in your company. Your website is like a marketer that never sleeps. If you build the right one it can be an investment that keeps on giving.</p>

<p> That&#8217;s why I offer my <a href="http://glennstovall.com/offerings/overnight-site">overnight site</a>  service. I&#8217;ve streamlined the process as much as I could, so that can deliver results to clients at a price that makes it an investment, and not an expense. I&#8217;m always game to hear about your idea, and I have no problem telling you to not hire me and use Squarespace if it makes more sense for your business. But if does make sense to bring in some professional guidance, or you would rather spend time doing more valuable things for your business and let me worry about it, then I hope we can <a href="http://glennstovall.com/offerings/overnight-site">work together</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Ways To Build A $200,000 Consultancy]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/5waysto_key.png" width="260"></p>

<p>I recently read an article entitled <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">5 ways to build a $100 million dollar business</a>. It discusses different business models that vary on the number and size of your customer base. Some businesses work with a few enterprise scale clients, while others work with a larger number of smaller customers. Patrick Mackenzie mentioned on Twitter that <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/521878305151000577">&#8220;The math here is equally applicable if you are trying to build, say, a $200k a year business&#8221;</a>.A $200k/yr consultancy is a goal that seems both attractive and attainable, so I decided try and answer the question &#8220;How can you build a $200,000 consultancy?&#8221;</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Find 1 Client That Pays You $200,000 (The Elephant)</h3>

<p>I&#8217;ve been a part of projects where a single engagement has had a price tag of $200,000 or more. I think this scenario is a little unlikely. If you can find one of these clients, then you can find more, and you are on your way to becoming a $1mm+ consultancy. It would also be very risky for a company to put all of it&#8217;s eggs in one basket like this.</p>

<h3>Find 10 Clients That Pay You $20,000 (The Deer)</h3>

<p>There are a few examples of consultancies that make this kind of money. One is custom application development services that can handle ten projects in a year. Most of the client work I find is in this range. Another example is high end consulting engagements. People like <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/">Patrick Mackenzie</a> and <a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com/">Brennan Dunn</a> charge anywhere from $10,000 - $30,000 for a week of their services. They could work 10 engagements a year and hit this $200,000 benchmark.</p>

<h3>Find 100 Clients That Pay You $2,000 (The Rabbits)</h3>

<p>With this setup, your consultancy would have to have a service that scales very well. One way to accomplish this would be to find a way to service multiple clients at one time. Hosting courses or seminars is a way you could accomplish this. For example, Big Nerd Ranch offers <a href="https://training.bignerdranch.com/classes/advanced-ios-bootcamp">programming courses that cost $4,200</a>. At this point, the focus of the work changes. This is less of a consulting model and more of an information product model. There are plenty of gigs out there that pay $2,000 for smaller jobs, which are fine but those are hard to scale.</p>

<h3>Find 1,000 Customers That Pay You $200 (The Mice)</h3>

<p>At this level, you need a product that you can resell. It could be a course that requires little to no interaction for $200 (For example, a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/comprehensive-ruby-on-rails/?dtcode=Q73iZAp1GbIa">UDemy</a> course), or it could be some form of subscription product, which would cost just shy of $20/month. For software developers, you may be able to build a premium software framework or plugin that can sell for this amount. The <a href="http://www.magentocommerce.com/magento-connect/">Magento Connect marketplace</a> is a good example of people going this model. I can&#8217;t think of any kind of repeatable service model that works at this scale.</p>

<h3>Find 10,000 Customers That Pay You $20 (The Files)</h3>

<p>You are a product business at this point. You could sell ebooks, themes, plugins, or something of that nature. You really can&#8217;t call it a consultancy at this point. For this kind of business, it looks like the math doesn&#8217;t scale don&#8217;t quite so well at this point.</p>

<h3>Applying This To Your Business</h3>

<p>Do you want to work on $2,000 or $200,000 projects? Before you say &#8220;$200,000, duh.&#8221; Think about the pros and cons of fewer clients vs. more, and smaller clients vs. large. Fewer larger clients means a more rigorous, in-depth sales process, and a higher risk if you lose a client.</p>

<p>What kind of consultancy do you want to run, and how are you going to scale it? You can scale not only by getting more clients, but by getting bigger ones as well. If you think about the kind of business you <strong>want</strong> to be running, then you can start making deliberate steps to get there.</p>

<p><small>Image by <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">Christoph Janz</a></small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[30 Day Publishing Challenge Postmortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T14:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is final day #30 of the <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/">30 Day publishing challenge</a>. Whenever I finish a project, I write a postmortem. I ask myself three questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>What went well?</li>
<li>What went wrong?</li>
<li>What can I do better next time?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is a breakdown of the lessons learned from publishing a whole lot of content for a month.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What Went Well</h2>

<h4>I Have Almost Double The Content on My Site</h4>

<p>More content tends to mean more search engine traffic, and more content to share. According to Google Analytics, my search engine traffic is up 4%, and social media shares are up 300%.</p>

<h4>I Learned How to Build A Strong Habit</h4>

<p>I have tried many weekly or monthly challenges in the past, and I tend to not do well at them. I&#8217;m not sure why this time was different, but I was able to stick it out for the entire 30 days. It gave me more confidence it taking on these kinds of challenges.</p>

<h4>I Make Fewer Spelling Errors</h4>

<p>And overall, I feel like my ability to put words on the page has improved. In addition to all of the articles and pages, I also put out a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/">60-page case study on building your audience</a>. It didn&#8217;t go over as well as I would have liked, but putting 10,000 words about a single topic felt really good.</p>

<p>The key to getting better at anything is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_(learning_method">deliberate practice</a>#Deliberate_practice), and this challenge gave me an opportunity to practice my writing skills.</p>

<h4>I Had to Get More Creative</h4>

<p>I usually keep a list of article ideas that I can reach too whenever I need to write something. That list is barren after this challenge. However, it did force me to find some new ways to create content, and force me to put ideas on paper that were always sitting around waiting for &#8216;one day&#8217;.</p>

<h2>What Went Wrong</h2>

<h4>I Published Some Sub-par Content</h4>

<p>Being constrained to publishing something everyday means that some content went out the door before I felt it was ready. I&#8217;m not as proud of some of the content as I should have been. This also meant they I published several shorter articles, when I usually tend to like writing longer form content.</p>

<h4>My Writing Wasn&#8217;t Focused</h4>

<p>I believe you should publish content with some kind of goal in mind. By being forced to write everyday, I wrote about a variety of topics: <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup/">front end development</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">freelancing</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert/">email marketing</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire/">stoicism</a> and even <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/05/niche-blogging/">writing itself</a>. It leads to an unfocused site of content.</p>

<p>On the other hand, <a href="http://jamesclear.com/">James Clear</a> writes about bodybuilding, entrepreneurship, and photography, so maybe that isn&#8217;t so bad.</p>

<h4>I Was Distracted</h4>

<p>I spent a bit more time on this than I should have. While I believe my content strategy is part of my larger business plan, I did invest too much during the month in writing. Once I got to day 17, the challenge became like a drug. I <em>had</em> to finish it at that point, sometimes at the detriment of more important work.</p>

<h2>What To Do Better Next Time</h2>

<h4>Write Instead of Publish Everyday</h4>

<p>I believe that writing is a valuable asset. It has helped me grow my business. The habit I built was also beneficial. Instead of being required to put something out there, In the future I want to focus on putting out fewer, more useful pieces.</p>

<h4>More Focus</h4>

<p>When you write frequently, you learn a lot about how to write. When you publish frequently, you learn a lot about how people react to what it is that you write. During this month I have learned what people like, and what people don&#8217;t. This is going to affect what I publish about in the future. This month was playing around; now it&#8217;s time to put some real effort in writing content that I hope you&#8217;ll find valuable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Good Copywriters Borrow, Great Copywriters Steal]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/29/good-copywriters-borrow/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-29T15:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/29/good-copywriters-borrow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/thief.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve spent a lot of time writing this year, and especially this month with the <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/">30 day publishing challenge</a>. Something I have discovered is that writing is not as hard as it looks. You may think that you have to write for inspiration to strike, and if doesn&#8217;t, you can complain about &#8220;writer&#8217;s block&#8221;.</p>

<p>Writer&#8217;s block just means you aren&#8217;t looking heard enough. There is inspiration for copy everywhere. Pablo Picasso always said &#8220;Good artists borrow, great artists steal&#8221;. When you don&#8217;t know what to say about your company or your product, then it&#8217;s time to go on a caper and find some messages you can use in your copy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Steal From Your Customers</h3>

<p>Keep notes on interactions you have with past, present, and future customers. Your copy writing needs to be in your customer&#8217;s language, not your own. If you have collected testimonials, that can be a great place to start. Sales meetings, request for proposals, and job board postings are all also good places.</p>

<p>This will also help you create higher converting copy. People like when they read something and think &#8220;wow, they really get me!&#8221; By speaking your customers language, and addressing points you got straight from the horse&#8217;s mouth, you will be more in tune with your customer&#8217;s needs.</p>

<h3>Steal From Your Competitors</h3>

<p>Look at the sites of a few of your competitors, there are three things you want to pay attention to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Their headings and subheadings.</li>
<li>Their calls-to-action.</li>
<li>Anything else that makes you stop and go &#8220;Hmm!&#8221;.</li>
</ul>


<p>You don&#8217;t want to take these lines verbatim, but instead get an overall feel for how other people are approaching the market. You can make a spreadsheet of these three things to keep track.</p>

<p>This will also help you make sure that you are saying something unique. You don&#8217;t have to be the best in your market, just different. You could even make your headline the opposite of your competitors. If they focus on being the biggest, you can focus on being a smaller, more personal brand, for example.</p>

<h3>Steal From Other People&#8217;s Feedback</h3>

<p>Amazon reviews are another great source for ideas. Search for books related to your services, and see what people are talking about. Look at 5-star reviews to get an idea of what people like, and 1-star reviews to see what problems people have and what you should avoid.</p>

<h3>Further Reading</h3>

<p>The idea of this approach is to turn writing from a creative practice into a scientific one; From a passive way of writing to an <strong>active</strong> way. Joanna Weibe of CopyHackers has a great article on this idea: <a href="http://copyhackers.com/2012/09/headline-formulas-and-the-science-of-high-converting-copywriting/">Headline Formulas and the Science of CRO Copy writing</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing AngularJS With Karma + Jasmine]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/26/testing-angularjs-with-karma-plus-jasmine/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-26T15:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/26/testing-angularjs-with-karma-plus-jasmine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/angular.png" width="260"></p>

<p>In a previous article about <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup/">Yeoman, AngularJS, and Foundation</a>, I talked about setting up a complete front end application scaffold with Yeoman, AngularJS, and Foundation. Now I want to look at how to test the AngularJS part of your application.</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h2>The Tools</h2>

<h3>Karma</h3>

<p><a href="http://karma-runner.github.io/0.12/index.html">Karma</a> is a test runner for NodeJS. You can use it to simulate multiple devices. What Karma isn&#8217;t is a testing framework itself. It is designed to work with multiple testing frameworks, such as <a href="http://jasmine.github.io/">Jasmine</a>, <a href="http://qunitjs.com/">QUnit</a>, or <a href="http://visionmedia.github.io/mocha/">Mocha</a>.</p>

<h3>Jasmine</h3>

<p>I&#8217;m using Jasmine for a couple of reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>I looked into Jasmine and QUnit before, and I have never seen two tools as similar. Their syntax is different, but how they function is <em>identical</em> last time I checked. Months ago I flipped a coin, it was &#8216;tails&#8217;, and I implemented Jasmine on a client project. No real reason to change.</li>
<li>I haven&#8217;t looked into Mocha. It might be better, or worse, or also identical. I don&#8217;t know. If <strong>you</strong> have an opinion, <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com/contact">let me know</a>.</li>
<li>It&#8217;s installed by default by Yeoman &#8230; sort of.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Step 1: Fix The Missing Dependencies</h2>

<p>For some reason, the <code>generator-angular</code> generator comes with some, but not all of the tools we&#8217;ll need for running tests with Karma and Jasmine, so we need to fix that before we get started. Run the following lines on the command line:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>npm install grunt-karma --save-dev
</span><span class='line'>npm install karma-phantomjs-launcher --save-dev
</span><span class='line'>npm install karma-jasmine --save-dev</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Step 2: Test the Tests</h2>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>grunt test</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This should ensure that everything is installed correctly. If you running a clean install from Yeoman, then it should run that test. You can look at the file /test/spec/controllers/MainCtrl.js for an example of what a test looks like.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Create A Simple Test</h2>

<p>Here is an example test, just to get you comfortable with the Jasmine testing Syntax. Create a file at <code>test/spec/app.js</code>, and write the following code:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="s1">&#39;use strict&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">describe</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;javascript&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">it</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;should know 2 + 2 is 4&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">expect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">toEqual</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I enjoy jasmine&#8217;s matchers and syntax because it reads like english.</p>

<p><code>describe()</code> is how you group your tests into suites. You can nest <code>describe()</code> calls as many levels deep as youwish, though any more than two and it gets really difficult to read and manage. <code>it()</code> is how you run tests. The first argument is the description, the second is the test itself. <code>expect()</code> is where you test your assumptions in the test, and <code>toEqual()</code> is your matcher. you can also add <code>not()</code> before any more matcher to test the opposite:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="c1">//it&#39;s 2014, not 1984 ... I think</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">it</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;should know 2 + 2 is not 5&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">expect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">not</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">toEqual</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If you want to know what other matchers are available to you with Jasmine, here is a handy <a href="http://www.cheatography.com/citguy/cheat-sheets/jasmine-js-testing/">Jasmine Cheat Sheet</a></p>

<h2>Step 4: Now For a Real Test</h2>

<p>By default, Yeoman comes with a controller test, you can see how it works there:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">describe</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;Controller: MainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1">// load the controller&#39;s module</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">beforeEach</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">module</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;ngFoundationApp&#39;</span><span class="p">));</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">MainCtrl</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">scope</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1">// Initialize the controller and a mock scope</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">beforeEach</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">inject</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">$controller</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">$rootScope</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">scope</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">$rootScope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">$new</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">MainCtrl</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">$controller</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;MainCtrl&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">$scope</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">scope</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}));</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">it</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;should attach a list of awesomeThings to the scope&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">expect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">scope</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">awesomeThings</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">toBe</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Here you see some of the other handy features, such as <code>beforeEach()</code>. <code>beforeEach()</code> takes a function as an argument, and calls it before each test.</p>

<h2>Dependency Injection and Testing</h2>

<p>When you start writing tests you will begin to see why <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_injection">Dependency Injection</a> is so valuable. When you create services in Angular, you want to pass them as arguments instead of creating them directly. This way, you can create mock versions of anything for testing.</p>

<p>Here is an example test from a client project:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">it</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;should use tasks to set price if that is the invoice_method selected&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$injector</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">invoke</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">Project</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">Feature</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">mock</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nx">Project</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">mock_project</span><span class="p">()).</span><span class="nx">prepare</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">mock</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">invoice_method</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s1">&#39;task&#39;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">mock</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">estimate</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">tasks</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">mock_task</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="s1">&#39;tID&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;time&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;rate&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;billable&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">}),</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">mock_task</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="s1">&#39;tID&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;time&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;rate&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">&#39;billable&#39;</span> <span class="o">:</span> <span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">}),</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">mock</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">updatePrice</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">expect</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">mock</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">estimate</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">price</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">toEqual</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I created functions that would return mock objects such as <code>mock_project()</code> and <code>mock_task()</code>. This way, I can test the <code>Project</code> object without the <code>Task</code> object. This way, all of my tests are completely self-contained, the waygood unit tests should be.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talking Productized Consulting with Nick Disabato[Video]]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T04:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/23/talking-productized-consulting-with-nick-disabato-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Origin Story of Draft Revise</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/nickd.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>In this interview I am talking with Nick Disabato, Owner of <a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft</a>, Author of <a href="http://cadence.cc/">Cadence &amp; Slang</a>,, and <a href="https://draft.nu/revise/">Draft Revise</a>, a recurring split testing service that Nick offers to clients. In this interview, Nick talks about creating a new service offering from scratch, How he got his first customers, and how Draft Revise has changed his business.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>




<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Lib91re3onM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Show Notes</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://draft.nu/">Draft, a small interaction design consultancy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/nickd">Nick Disabato on Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nickd.org">Nickd.org</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yeoman + AngularJS + Foundation: A Modern Front End Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T14:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/angular.png" width="260"></p>

<p>With the combination of modern browsers and mobile devices having support for HTML5, CSS3, and new JavaScript APIs, front end development has become a lot more complex and exciting. There has been an explosion of tools as of late, and it can be daunting to know where to get started. Here are the tools and process I use in order to build a new front end application from scratch.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Tools</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Yeoman</strong> : For scaffolding our web application.</li>
<li><strong>Bower</strong> : For front-end dependency management.</li>
<li><strong>Grunt</strong> : Command line tool for development.</li>
<li><strong>AngularJS</strong> : JavaScript framework based on the principals of dependency injection.</li>
<li><strong>Foundation</strong>: Responsive SCSS Framework to speed up design.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Step 1: Install Yeoman and a Generator</h3>

<p>We&#8217;ll be using <a href="http://yeoman.io/">Yeoman</a> to handle all of our scaffolding. Yeoman will create the initial files and folder structure for you, so that you don&#8217;t have too. Yeoman uses generators, which are different templates it will use when creating your initial app. Yeoman is managed via npm. If you don&#8217;t have node and npm installed, you can get the <a href="http://nodejs.org/download/">NodeJS installer here</a>. I prefer building web applications with <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/">AngularJS</a>, so we&#8217;ll be installing a generator for an Angular application.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>npm install -g yo
</span><span class='line'>npm install -g generator-angular</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Step 2: Create The Scaffolding</h3>

<p>Now that we have our tools installed, it&#8217;s time to create our initial application. We&#8217;ll create a new directory and run the generator:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>mkdir example-app
</span><span class='line'>cd example-app
</span><span class='line'>yo angular</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If you have everything installed correctly, Yeomen should start building your application. Select &#8216;yes&#8217; when it asks you if you want to install compass, then select no when it asks if you if you want to install Bootstrap. After a couple of minutes, you folder structure should look like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Gruntfile.js
</span><span class='line'>/app
</span><span class='line'>bower.json
</span><span class='line'>bower_components
</span><span class='line'>node_modules
</span><span class='line'>package.json
</span><span class='line'>/test</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Step 3: Install Dependencies</h3>

<p>Now we need to run our package managers to install dependencies. First, we will run NPM in order to install development dependencies, then <a href="http://bower.io/">Bower</a> to install front end dependencies:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>npm install
</span><span class='line'>bower install</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Step 4: Test The Servers</h3>

<p>Run the server and make sure everything is working OK:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>grunt serve</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once this runs, navigate to <code>localhost:9000</code>. You should see the yeoman placeholder page.</p>

<h3>Step 5: Clean out the Crud.</h3>

<p>Yeoman adds a lot of content that is not needed. For example, it has multiple routes, controllers, and views already created for you. You can leave this in or comment it out if you want to keep an example, but I like to clear all of this out before I start working. Here is a quick checklist, so you don&#8217;t miss anything.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>app/index.html</code> - Remove most of the code in the body, but be sure to leave the div with the <code>ng-view</code> property.</li>
<li><code>app/views/main.html</code> - Remove the excess HTML.</li>
<li><code>app/scripts/app.js</code> - Remove the routes that you aren&#8217;t using. I get rid of the extra &#8216;about&#8217; route, and delete all the related files.</li>
<li>remove <code>app/controllers/about.js</code></li>
<li>remove <code>app/views/about.html</code></li>
<li>remove <code>spec/controllers/about.js</code></li>
<li><code>app/styles/main.scss</code> - Remove all of the unused styles.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Step 6: Install Foundation</h3>

<p>I prefer <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Zurb&#8217;s Foundation</a> to <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/2.3.2/">Twitter&#8217;s Bootstrap</a>. In my opinion, it&#8217;s easier to use and has cleaner markup. Since we are using Bower, this process is simple. Run the following command from the root directory of your project:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>bower install foundation --save</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The <code>save</code> flag will update your <code>bower.json</code> file. If you want to use any of the JavaScript functionality of Foundation, add the following to your app.js file after <code>use strict</code>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">document</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">foundation</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And Done!</p>

<p>Now you have a front end application ready for development, with a whole suite of tools and frameworks installed.</p>

<p>If you would like a PDF version of this article, you can get it below:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start A Consultancy In 16 Hours From Kai Davis]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T07:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/18/how-to-start-a-consultantcy-in-16-hours-from-kai-davis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>An Actionable Plan From The Side Hustle Nation</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/kai-davis.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>My friend <a href="http://kaidavis.com/">Kai Davis</a> was recently on the side hustle nation podcast. The episode is <a href="http://www.sidehustlenation.com/start-side-hustle-consulting-business-gets-paid/">How to Start a Side Hustle Consulting Business that Gets Paid</a>. One particular nugget of gold from this podcast: When asked what he would do if he had to start all over, Kai responds with how he would start a new consultancy in 16 hours.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Hours 1-3: Identify A Target Audience</h3>

<p>Decide which market you want to focus on. This could be segmented geographically, or by industry type. If you aren&#8217;t sure where to begin, try looking at local business directories. Your local chamber of commerce is a good place to start. You could even look in a phone book if you manage to find one.</p>

<h3>Hours 4 - 8: Book Four Calls (But Not Sales Calls)</h3>

<p>Start reaching out to people who you think might be potential clients. Ask them to sit down with you over lunch or coffee, or just hop on the phone with you to discuss their business. People love talking about themselves, and even strangers will be more receptive to this than you would believe. Your goal here isn&#8217;t to sell them anything, this meeting is research. You want to find the <em>pain points</em> that your potential clients have.</p>

<h3>Hours 9 - 12: Begin Crafting A Service</h3>

<p>Now that you know what problems people in your target audience are having, how can you solve them? Look for ways you can apply your current skills and knowledge to these problems, or how to apply new skills that you could pick up in a reasonable amount of time. If you don&#8217;t find a good fit, that&#8217;s OK, you may just have to try again. You don&#8217;t marry the first person you date, and you don&#8217;t want to pursue the first job idea that comes to mind.</p>

<h3>Hours 13 - 16: Offer Your Solution</h3>

<p>Now you have connections to your market, and understanding of their problems, and a solution to those problems. Go back to your original contacts and offer your solution. Now you&#8217;re in business!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exactly How I Got My First 500 Subscribers: Announcing a New Case Study And Seminar]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/16/exactly-how-i-got-my-first-500-subscribers-annoucing-a-new-case-study-and-seminar/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-16T14:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/16/exactly-how-i-got-my-first-500-subscribers-annoucing-a-new-case-study-and-seminar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Learn The Exact Techniques I Used to Build An Audience From Scratch</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://glennstovall.com/images/articles/audience_building_cover.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Four months ago, I decided to start building an mailing list. I wanted to build new relationships in my field and expand my network. Overtime I built the list to over 500 subscribers. After some conversations, I saw that other people were interested in how I did it. I sat down to write down a case study. I wanted to be as exact and transparent as possible. It got a little out of hand, but at the end I believe I&#8217;ve crafted a valuable guide for anyone who wants to start growing their audience.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Final Result</h3>

<p>This case study ended up being much longer than I anticipated. I wanted to be as specific as possible, so that other people could repeat what worked, as well as learn from my mistakes. In addition, I wanted to be transparent. I believe that the best way to teach is to teach <strong>everything</strong>. After I had collected all of my experiences, I went on to research what other people had done to grow their audience.</p>

<p>The result was over 60 pages of content, in what I originally thought might just be a blog article. I&#8217;ve put everything I&#8217;ve learned in a PDF, and you can grab it at the end of this article.</p>

<h3>Talking About Audience Building Live: September 30th</h3>

<p>After putting together this report, I thought it would be fun to talk to others about this in person. So, in addition to publishing this report, I am hosting a <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/09-30-building-audiences">live seminar in Athens, GA on Tuesday, September 30th</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
