<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: challenge | Essentialist Software Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/challenge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-05T16:02:26-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Will You Take The 30 day Publishing Challenge?]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-03T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Come Ship More Content in September With Me</h3>

<p>I heard about this challenge that a friend of a friend is doing: blog every weekday for 30 days. Here's <a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/9527/blogging-every-weekday-for-30-days">the original post</a>. Here's the post where I <a href="http://mattdsmith.com/30-day-blog-challenge/">heard about it</a>. I know writing is a valuable skill. Blogging can help you build your reach, prove your authority, and give you an way to provide value to your potential clients and customers by providing them with educational content.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>However, I want to modify this challenge a bit, just because I kind of hate the term "blogging". Blogging is just one way to deliver content, there are several others. Instead, I want to take on the "30-day publishing challenge". Under my rules, any of the following will count as my writing for the day:</p>

<h3>What Counts</h3>

<ul>
<li>Publishing a new blog post. This includes my personal site or sites such as Medium.</li>
<li>Publishing a new letter to people on my mailing list (yep, this is my Day 1)</li>
<li>Publishing a new page or re-writing an existing page on my personal or company site.</li>
<li>Publishing another form of long-form content, such as an email course, eBook, or PDF.
Here are things that don't count:</li>
</ul>


<h3>What Doesn't Count</h3>

<ul>
<li>Republishing existing content in a new form (I've been looking into using Quora's and LinkedIn's publishing platforms to get more reach)</li>
<li>Super short-form content (tweets, tumbles, facebook posts, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>Since I'm bending the rules a bit, I'm going to publish something every 30 days instead of just on weekdays. This also means that for the weekends I'll probably write three things on Friday and space them out over the weekend.</p>

<p>So you up to taking the challenge? If  <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com/contact">drop me a line</a>. I'd love to follow along with what you are doing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
