<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: motivation | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/motivation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-29T15:18:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned From Thomas Edison's Factory Fire]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T08:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Edison Understood Resiliance AND Electricity</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/edison_fire.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>On December 10th, 1914, Thomas Edison was having dinner with his family. A man rushes to his door and tells Edison that his factory had caught fire. Edison grabs his son Charles and they rush our the door. They head to the factory to see what is going on. When they get there the see a  vivid display of red, green, and blue fires, due to the various chemicals stored in his laboratory.</p>

<p>This could be the end of Thomas Edison. He didn't even have insurance on the building, because it was designed to be fireproof. Edison looks at his son and says:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Go get your mother and all her friends. They'll never see a fire like this again.</p></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Charles protested, to which Edison responded:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's all right. We've just got rid of a lot of old rubbish.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>How was Edison able to look at a career threatening tragedy and take such a light hearted approach to such a catastrophe? Edison understood the philosophy of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism">Stoicism</a>. Stoicism tells us that negative and destructive emotions are the result of errors in judgement.</p>

<h3>The Obstacle is The Way</h3>

<p>The principal teaching of Stoicism is that we should view challenges and stress as opportunities. Instead of seeing the factory as a catastrophic blow to his business, Edison saw an opportunity to start anew. If you are an entrepreneur, you <strong>need</strong> to get comfortable with failure.</p>

<h3>Facing Failure Head On</h3>

<p>Sometimes there will be failures that are your fault, other times they are not. There may be circumstances that you couldn't foresee or plan for. The world is chaotic, and it doesn't owe you anything; it was here first.</p>

<p>You can't let the control of how you react to these scenarios slip from your grasp. Every time you see crisis, you have to try and see opportunity.</p>

<h3>A Personal Story</h3>

<p>Many freelancer's are familiar with the term "feast or famine". It alludes to the fact that with client work, when it rains, it pours. Sometimes lots of sales come through at once, other times they don't. It can be stressful when work is slow. I had been feeling depressed and unmotivated for days facing a recent sales slump. However, by applying the philosophy of stoicism, I can see this in a very different light:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/articles/time_enough.jpg"></p>

<h4>Time Enough At Last</h4>

<p>People often complain about not having enough time to accomplish everything they want. I know I have. That's no longer an excuse. I have a lot of hours to fill up every day with whatever I so choose.</p>

<h4>Going Completely Remote</h4>

<p>A big goal I have for my consulting business is to build a system that is completely remote. While networking locally tends to be the most effective way to build connections, and will always be a part of my business strategy, it can be limiting. The internet opens up the whole wide world, and I would like to build connections with people that live more than 20 miles away from me.</p>

<p>This will give me the freedom to run my business from anywhere in country. Hell, anywhere in the world. This is <strong>huge</strong> not as a business goal, but as a goal for living a happy life.</p>

<h4>A Through Post Mortem</h4>

<p>What have I done right? What I have done wrong? Having all this time gives me an opportunity to look at every part of my business, from marketing, to sales, to deliverables, and see what has gone well, and what hasn't. I'm taking all this free time I have and applying to finding ways to deliver better service and more value to my clients, while building a more sustainable business for myself.</p>

<h4>A Learning Experience</h4>

<p>I have been working on a book this year entitled <em>Professional Freelance</em>. I planned on including chapters on sales and marketing. By having a challenge that many other freelancers face every day gives me an chance to find ways to approach it, learn and invent new solutions, and gather knowledge that I can share with other people and help other people grow their career.</p>

<h3>The Struggle Isn't Real</h3>

<p>When facing hardships, it's good to be reminded that they aren't as bad as they first seem, if we approach them in the correct fashion. What did Edison do after his watched his plant burn to the ground in a spectacular fashion? He got a loan from his friend Henry Ford, and in three weeks he was up and running again. Edison went on to make $10 million dollars in revenue that year (~$200 million in 2014 dollars).</p>

<p>I'll leave you with a video on Stoic Optimism, a TEDx talk by Ryan Holiday:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/e2Zq2VWvmW4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Audience_building_cover" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
        </span>
          <p>This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/803/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','Build an Audience Case Study','standard']);">

    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/812/227/standard/building-audience-cover.png?1411055942" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">How to Build an Audience From Scratch</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">This 60-page case study teaches you everything you need to know to start building an online following.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/'>Learn More...</a></p>


      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="803" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      <label class='ck_checkbox' style='display:none;'>
        <input class="optIn ck_course_opted" name='course_opted' type="checkbox" id="optIn" checked />
        I'd like to receive a free 30 day course by email.
      </label>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Start Building Your Audience
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
