<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-31T09:43:08-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I am Killing My Company Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T11:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Personal vs. Professional Blogging, Part II</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/concordant-articles.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Back in March, I wrote and article, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/">Personal vs. Professional Blogging</a>. In that article I explained why I decided to publish my writing on  two blogs: <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com">glennstovall.com</a>, Where I planned on writing content aimed at fellow developers and freelancers. The other site was <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com/articles">Concordant Solutions</a> My "company brand" (<em>ugh</em>, I will never be comfortable with that phrase) where I aimed to write content I thought clients would enjoy. That hasn't worked. Here is why, and how I plan to fix.</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>No One Connects With a Company</h3>

<p>Unless you are a large company with a lot of authority, Most people aren't going to be interested in your company blog. <a href="http://blog.kissmetrics.com/">KISSMetrics</a> is an exception to this rule. People would rather read an article by "Glenn", than by "Concordant Solutions". The second comes across as less authentic.</p>

<h3>It's Easier to Manage One Thing Instead of Two</h3>

<p>It's better to update blogs regularly. By having two blogs maintaining consistency is twice as hard. It also added mental overhead to every article that I wanted to write, since I had to decide where it would go, and what audience I would try to appeal to. Instead, now I can have one content management system, and one stream of content that is more steady. There were even a couple of situations where I tried to spin content so I could post it twice, which was a waste of time.</p>

<h3>It Helps SEO (At Least I'm Pretty Sure)</h3>

<p>I'm not an SEO Guru. Beyond "Content is king", "Have a good title tag", "No one uses the <code>&lt;meta name='keywords'&gt;</code> tag anymore, I know nothing. This is just from anecdotal observation. This domain has been around longer, gotten more traffic, and had more back links. <em>Anything</em> I publish here does better than anything I have published on my company domain. Viral traffic seems to work like high tide coming in: There is a wave of traffic that comes in quickly, and leaves just as fast. But once it is gone, It leaves the average daily visitors mark a little higher than it found it. Google must think this domain has <em>some</em> value. Why squander it?</p>

<h3>There is More Crossover Appeal Than I Originally Thought</h3>

<p>Most of my clients are small businesses or tech companies, which is not as different of an audience as I thought. Freelancers are by definition also small business owners (even if they don't see themselves that way). And people at tech companies in a position to hire me often have a technical background. I said that they might not know what <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/06/27/angularjs-an-overview/">AngularJS</a> is, but that is not always the case. I can still write content aimed at a subset of my audience, but there is no reason to have two locations to do so.</p>

<h3>At The End of The Day, The Company Blog Was a Failure</h3>

<p>I've maintained <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a> for a year, and I am not afraid to admit that as a marketing tool, it has been a failure. I will say that as a <em>sales</em> tool, It has done some good work. The difference is that while that domain and the content on it has not brought me any new leads, it has been a great tool to help turn leads into clients. Potential clients are usually not going to find your portfolio by googling for it; They are going to see your portfolio because they said "can I see your portfolio?" and you mailed them a link.</p>

<p>My company site will still exist for that reason. Any content on there I still deem worthwhile is going to be ported over to this domain over the next couple weeks. The company site  will be a resource for past, present, and future clients. I still intend on it being a valuable sales tool. It just won't have an articles section any longer.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Self Publisher's Journey]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/06/the-self-publishers-journey/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-06T14:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/06/the-self-publishers-journey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/cover.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>I'm working on self publishing and eBook in the coming months, and I wanted to document my journey and share it with you. I have enjoyed and been inspired by other writings such as <a href="http://groovehq.com/blog">Alex Turnbull documenting his ongoing journey to get to $100,000 recurring revenue</a>, and Nathan Barry's <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/category/the-web-app-challenge/">"Web App in Six Months Challenge"</a>. There is nothing like publicly sharing your techniques and struggles in order to both share useful information with other people, and to keep myself accountable.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Story So Far</h3>

<p>I think a lot of freelancers dream of finding ways to make money besides charging for their time. It could be by setting up recurring revenue, productizing their consulting services, or building a product they can sell individually. I decided to try what many before me have, and build a product. Heck, there is an <a href="http://chasingproduct.com">entire podcast</a> dedicated to the subject (which is really good, by the way).</p>

<p>Being a web developer, of course my first thought was to build some form of SaaS application. Enough reading on the internet scared me off of that idea (for now): SaaS applications on average take two years before they bring in enough income to stand on their own, and I know from experience they can take months to develop. I had started a couple of ideas, but could never find the time to finish them. Then I found an article by Amy Hoy called <a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/why-you-should-do-a-tiny-product-first">"Why you should build a tiny product first"</a> and it really resonated with me. It got me thinking about products that I could complete in 90 days or less. I liked writing, and based on several freelance sites I had read before, I knew that there was a lot of interest in starting to freelance, but a lot of people didn't know where to begin.</p>

<p>The tiny idea was also appealing because it would be a straight up easier way to launch a product. I have worked with enough small businesses and start-ups to know that launching a new business or product is <strong>hard</strong>. Really, REALLY hard. There is no reason to tackle new business ventures on hard mode, and I feel that if there is anything you can do to make things easier on yourself, you should do it. And it is much easier to write a book than build a piece of software, and it is a lot easier to convince someone to pay you $29 once instead of $29/month indefinitely.</p>

<h3>The Freelance Start-up Guide</h3>

<p>It was at this point, around the start of this year,  I decided to work on a book, then titled <strong>The Freelance Start-up Guide</strong>. It was going to be aimed at aspiring freelancers, and help them build a product from scratch. I started writing the book, and set up a mailing list. Initial response was a bit tepid on the mailing list, but there was some interest in the idea.</p>

<h3>The First Big Hurdle</h3>

<p>Around the start of February, I had a huge rush of client work, admittedly, more than I could handle. I knew something had to give, and I informed my tiny mailing list that I had shelved the project indefinitely. I knew at that time that I did not have any extra bandwidth, and had to cut work where ever I could.</p>

<h3>The Real Tiniest Product</h3>

<p>About a month ago, I decided to give building a mailing list a second try. I figured that I could build an audience before I built the product. Even if I didn't finish that book, I would still have an audience, and that had value. I signed up for Nathan Barry's <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a>, and during his ConvertKit academy, he gave me a valuable piece of advice: You can get a lot more email list subscriptions if you give users an incentive for signing up. I compiled some of my past blog articles, wrote some new content, and released <em><a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">The Freelance Pricing Handbook</a></em>. This is a small, 32 page eBook that I gave away for free. I was able to grow my list from 15 to 100 subscribers overnight. You can read my case study on it's release here.</p>

<p>This so far has been the best move I've made. I always liked blogging, but it had been directionless before. Now instead of people reading my article, and that bringing me no value, I could capture readers and have a way to continue engaging with them. This meant that every post I had written in the past and every post I would write in the future was more valuable. Now they weren't just articles, they were sales tools.</p>

<h3>Version 2.0: Bootstrap Freelance</h3>

<p>Now it's June, and my client work has returned to levels where I don't feel completely underwater. I decided that I wanted to pick up the project and continue working on it. At this point, I had almost 65 pages written, and an email list with a couple of hundred people on it, and I didn't want to throw all of this away. I renamed the product <em>Bootstrap Freelance</em> and decided to pick the project back up. I decided that instead of just telling people how to get their first client, I wanted to add more content based on lessons I had learned on how to build up their business after that. I'm nervous about announcing a launch date based on what happened last time, but I am shooting for a release date sometime in August.</p>

<h3>...And Here We Are</h3>

<p>Now I have roughly 80 pages of a first draft, which is about 2/3rds of what I want it to be. I am working on spending more time working not only on the book, but on marketing before that. For example, setting up a landing page for the product, and starting to public write about the progress of the book. I plan on updating this blog with information about the process, along with helpful information from the book. I am also going to send updates every single Friday to anyone who wants to help me accountable. If you'd like to keep up with the progress on the book, enter your email address below:</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/588.js?orient=vert"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal vs. Professional Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T14:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/saddington.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I had the pleasure of seeing <a href="http://john.do">John Saddington</a> give a talk about the benefits of blogging at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/transform-athens/">Transform Athens</a> Athens event. The talk was about the benefits of blogging, and while it reinvigorated my interest in writing and publishing. It brought up a tricky question. I have a blog under my personal name, <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com">Glenn Stovall</a> and a company blog, <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Where should I publish? Why should I publish there? What are the pros and cons of blogging under a personal brand vs. a professional brand?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Whatever it Takes to Hit 'Publish'</h3>

<p>I posed this question to John, and john shares my belief that publishing and shipping should always be the paramount goal. His feelings as to whether you should blog under your name or a company name comes down to doing "what ever makes you hit the publish button quicker". It's true that it is a largely personal choice that comes down to personal preferences. While his advice was helpful, it was still a question I had to answer for myself.</p>

<h3>The Tone of the Blogs</h3>

<p>In my post when I announced <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/12/10/announcing-concordant-solutions/">Concordant Solutions</a>, I mentioned my original plan for managing two different blogs. I wanted to cater to two different audiences, and each blog would be focused on one of them. My personal blog would be focused on technical, usually long form articles. It was were I would write to 'fellow nerds'. My company blog would be aimed at clients. I wouldn't write what I wanted to read, I would write what I felt would be interesting to my clients.</p>

<p>Here is the issue I ran into with that approach: my "company brand" writing was usually dry and boring. Writing is hard. Writing under a squeaky clean corporate persona is even harder. While I felt I did write things of some value on my company blog, I often felt my writing fell flat.</p>

<p>I wasn't happy with my writing, and it wasn't getting nearly as many readers. Life is too short to spend it doing things that produce a mediocre result.</p>

<h2>Defining Subject Matter</h2>

<p>My approach to the Concordant Solutions blog was completely wrong. I bought too hard into the belief that <em>you are not your customer</em>, and it skewed my writing. It's true, I am not my customer. I don't have employees (yet). My customers are not always tech savvy. However, I <strong>am</strong> a business owner. I am not just another freelancer. I am determined on creating a focused, sustainable, growing business. I am a business owner, just like my clients.</p>

<p>I made a fatal mistake of thinking that me and my clients do not have a common interest.  While a lot of my clients have no idea what "AngularJS" means, they know what cash flow, ROI, and LTV means. Being honest about your business can help it grow. Regardless of where I publish content, it's all still in some form about being honest and transparent with my business, and doing so in a way that help other people accomplish their goals, whether they are technical or financial.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-11T10:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/blog_with_octopress.png" width="260">
If you're reading this, then I've successfully got my octopress blog up and running on Github pages. Why the switch to octopress?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Writing with Octopress</h2>

<p>I love being able to write in emacs using markdown. It feels simple. It feels easy. It feels right.</p>

<h2>Deploying with Github</h2>

<p>This also allows me to host with github pages for free, and use git for deployment. So many headaches just went away for me when it comes to writing.</p>

<h2>Version Control based writing.</h2>

<p>I can take the same approach to writing as I can with coding, publishing fast, fixing mistakes as they are found, and changing content as need be. What you are currently reading isn't the first version of the post, and likely not the last.
I also like the idea of 'open source' writing. If anyone has anything they would like to add or change, feel free to send a pull request to this repo, and I'll take it under consideration.</p>

<h2>The Right Plugins</h2>

<p>There aren't many plugins or themes available for octopress (yet), but it has all the things that are needed to get good content going. That's what I love about it, it is all content based. The default theme is a beautiful starting off point, it's clear and responsive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
