<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://gsto.github.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gsto.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-05T16:50:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://gsto.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal vs. Professional Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://gsto.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T14:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gsto.github.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/saddington.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I had the pleasure of seeing <a href="http://john.do">John Saddington</a> give a talk about the benefits of blogging at a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/transform-athens/">Transform Athens</a> Athens event. The talk was about the benefits of blogging, and while it reinvigorated my interest in writing and publishing. It brought up a tricky question. I have a blog under my personal name, <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com">Glenn Stovall</a> and a company blog, <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Where should I publish? Why should I publish there? What are the pros and cons of blogging under a personal brand vs. a professional brand?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Whatever it Takes to Hit 'Publish'</h3>

<p>I posed this question to John, and john shares my belief that publishing and shipping should always be the paramount goal. His feelings as to whether you should blog under your name or a company name comes down to doing "what ever makes you hit the publish button quicker". It's true that it is a largely personal choice that comes down to personal preferences. While his advice was helpful, it was still a question I had to answer for myself.</p>

<h3>The Tone of the Blogs</h3>

<p>In my post when I announced <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2013/12/10/announcing-concordant-solutions/">Concordant Solutions</a>, I mentioned my original plan for managing two different blogs. I wanted to cater to two different audiences, and each blog would be focused on one of them. My personal blog would be focused on technical, usually long form articles. It was were I would write to 'fellow nerds'. My company blog would be aimed at clients. I wouldn't write what I wanted to read, I would write what I felt would be interesting to my clients.</p>

<p>Here is the issue I ran into with that approach: my "company brand" writing was usually dry and boring. Writing is hard. Writing under a squeaky clean corporate persona is even harder. While I felt I did write things of some value on my company blog, I often felt my writing fell flat.</p>

<p>I wasn't happy with my writing, and it wasn't getting nearly as many readers. Life is too short to spend it doing things that produce a mediocre result.</p>

<h2>Defining Subject Matter</h2>

<p>My approach to the Concordant Solutions blog was completely wrong. I bought too hard into the belief that <em>you are not your customer</em>, and it skewed my writing. It's true, I am not my customer. I don't have employees (yet). My customers are not always tech savvy. However, I <strong>am</strong> a business owner. I am not just another freelancer. I am determined on creating a focused, sustainable, growing business. I am a business owner, just like my clients.</p>

<p>I made a fatal mistake of thinking that me and my clients do not have a common interest.  While a lot of my clients have no idea what "AngularJS" means, they know what cash flow, ROI, and LTV means. Being honest about your business can help it grow. Regardless of where I publish content, it's all still in some form about being honest and transparent with my business, and doing so in a way that help other people accomplish their goals, whether they are technical or financial.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://gsto.github.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-11T10:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gsto.github.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/blog_with_octopress.png" width="260">
If you're reading this, then I've successfully got my octopress blog up and running on Github pages. Why the switch to octopress?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Writing with Octopress</h2>

<p>I love being able to write in emacs using markdown. It feels simple. It feels easy. It feels right.</p>

<h2>Deploying with Github</h2>

<p>This also allows me to host with github pages for free, and use git for deployment. So many headaches just went away for me when it comes to writing.</p>

<h2>Version Control based writing.</h2>

<p>I can take the same approach to writing as I can with coding, publishing fast, fixing mistakes as they are found, and changing content as need be. What you are currently reading isn't the first version of the post, and likely not the last.
I also like the idea of 'open source' writing. If anyone has anything they would like to add or change, feel free to send a pull request to this repo, and I'll take it under consideration.</p>

<h2>The Right Plugins</h2>

<p>There aren't many plugins or themes available for octopress (yet), but it has all the things that are needed to get good content going. That's what I love about it, it is all content based. The default theme is a beautiful starting off point, it's clear and responsive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
