<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-17T04:10:25-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[30 Day Publishing Challenge Postmortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T14:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/02/30-day-publishing-challenge-postmortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is final day #30 of the <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/">30 Day publishing challenge</a>. Whenever I finish a project, I write a postmortem. I ask myself three questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>What went well?</li>
<li>What went wrong?</li>
<li>What can I do better next time?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is a breakdown of the lessons learned from publishing a whole lot of content for a month.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What Went Well</h2>

<h4>I Have Almost Double The Content on My Site</h4>

<p>More content tends to mean more search engine traffic, and more content to share. According to Google Analytics, my search engine traffic is up 4%, and social media shares are up 300%.</p>

<h4>I Learned How to Build A Strong Habit</h4>

<p>I have tried many weekly or monthly challenges in the past, and I tend to not do well at them. I'm not sure why this time was different, but I was able to stick it out for the entire 30 days. It gave me more confidence it taking on these kinds of challenges.</p>

<h4>I Make Fewer Spelling Errors</h4>

<p>And overall, I feel like my ability to put words on the page has improved. In addition to all of the articles and pages, I also put out a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/products/building-audiences/">60-page case study on building your audience</a>. It didn't go over as well as I would have liked, but putting 10,000 words about a single topic felt really good.</p>

<p>The key to getting better at anything is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_(learning_method">deliberate practice</a>#Deliberate_practice), and this challenge gave me an opportunity to practice my writing skills.</p>

<h4>I Had to Get More Creative</h4>

<p>I usually keep a list of article ideas that I can reach too whenever I need to write something. That list is barren after this challenge. However, it did force me to find some new ways to create content, and force me to put ideas on paper that were always sitting around waiting for 'one day'.</p>

<h2>What Went Wrong</h2>

<h4>I Published Some Sub-par Content</h4>

<p>Being constrained to publishing something everyday means that some content went out the door before I felt it was ready. I'm not as proud of some of the content as I should have been. This also meant they I published several shorter articles, when I usually tend to like writing longer form content.</p>

<h4>My Writing Wasn't Focused</h4>

<p>I believe you should publish content with some kind of goal in mind. By being forced to write everyday, I wrote about a variety of topics: <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/22/yeoman-plus-angularjs-plus-foundation-a-modern-front-end-setup/">front end development</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/">freelancing</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/09/how-to-write-more-personal-emails-to-your-list-that-get-open-and-convert/">email marketing</a>, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/11/lessons-learned-from-thomas-edisons-factory-fire/">stoicism</a> and even <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/05/niche-blogging/">writing itself</a>. It leads to an unfocused site of content.</p>

<p>On the other hand, <a href="http://jamesclear.com/">James Clear</a> writes about bodybuilding, entrepreneurship, and photography, so maybe that isn't so bad.</p>

<h4>I Was Distracted</h4>

<p>I spent a bit more time on this than I should have. While I believe my content strategy is part of my larger business plan, I did invest too much during the month in writing. Once I got to day 17, the challenge became like a drug. I <em>had</em> to finish it at that point, sometimes at the detriment of more important work.</p>

<h2>What To Do Better Next Time</h2>

<h4>Write Instead of Publish Everyday</h4>

<p>I believe that writing is a valuable asset. It has helped me grow my business. The habit I built was also beneficial. Instead of being required to put something out there, In the future I want to focus on putting out fewer, more useful pieces.</p>

<h4>More Focus</h4>

<p>When you write frequently, you learn a lot about how to write. When you publish frequently, you learn a lot about how people react to what it is that you write. During this month I have learned what people like, and what people don't. This is going to affect what I publish about in the future. This month was playing around; now it's time to put some real effort in writing content that I hope you'll find valuable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Good Copywriters Borrow, Great Copywriters Steal]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/29/good-copywriters-borrow/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-29T15:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/29/good-copywriters-borrow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/thief.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>I've spent a lot of time writing this year, and especially this month with the <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/">30 day publishing challenge</a>. Something I have discovered is that writing is not as hard as it looks. You may think that you have to write for inspiration to strike, and if doesn't, you can complain about "writer's block".</p>

<p>Writer's block just means you aren't looking heard enough. There is inspiration for copy everywhere. Pablo Picasso always said "Good artists borrow, great artists steal". When you don't know what to say about your company or your product, then it's time to go on a caper and find some messages you can use in your copy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Steal From Your Customers</h3>

<p>Keep notes on interactions you have with past, present, and future customers. Your copy writing needs to be in your customer's language, not your own. If you have collected testimonials, that can be a great place to start. Sales meetings, request for proposals, and job board postings are all also good places.</p>

<p>This will also help you create higher converting copy. People like when they read something and think "wow, they really get me!" By speaking your customers language, and addressing points you got straight from the horse's mouth, you will be more in tune with your customer's needs.</p>

<h3>Steal From Your Competitors</h3>

<p>Look at the sites of a few of your competitors, there are three things you want to pay attention to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Their headings and subheadings.</li>
<li>Their calls-to-action.</li>
<li>Anything else that makes you stop and go "Hmm!".</li>
</ul>


<p>You don't want to take these lines verbatim, but instead get an overall feel for how other people are approaching the market. You can make a spreadsheet of these three things to keep track.</p>

<p>This will also help you make sure that you are saying something unique. You don't have to be the best in your market, just different. You could even make your headline the opposite of your competitors. If they focus on being the biggest, you can focus on being a smaller, more personal brand, for example.</p>

<h3>Steal From Other People's Feedback</h3>

<p>Amazon reviews are another great source for ideas. Search for books related to your services, and see what people are talking about. Look at 5-star reviews to get an idea of what people like, and 1-star reviews to see what problems people have and what you should avoid.</p>

<h3>Further Reading</h3>

<p>The idea of this approach is to turn writing from a creative practice into a scientific one; From a passive way of writing to an <strong>active</strong> way. Joanna Weibe of CopyHackers has a great article on this idea: <a href="http://copyhackers.com/2012/09/headline-formulas-and-the-science-of-high-converting-copywriting/">Headline Formulas and the Science of CRO Copy writing</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Niche Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/05/niche-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-05T14:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/05/niche-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Personal vs. Professional Blogging part III</h3>

<p>Should you write under your personal name, or under a company brand? I've addressed this question in other articles. At first, I planned on starting two blogs (<a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/">part I</a>). I tried that for a while and realized that I was spending a lot of time trying to build two audiences when I could just be building one. The time invested was not paying off. So, I decided to combine my two blogs, and write everything under my personal name (<a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">part II</a>). Today I'm covering a third option: Instead of writing under your name or your company, you write about a particular subject on a niche blog.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Niche Blogging</h3>

<p>A niche blog is a blog that is centered around a certain  topic, instead of around you or your company. The goal of a niche blog is to educate and inform its audience. For example, if your potential customers ran a SaaS business, you would have a site that was dedicated to writing articles to help SaaS owners.</p>

<h3>Using Niches to Sell Products</h3>

<p>Brennan Dunn recently made a shift to writing a subject focused site instead of a personal or company one. Over the past couple years, Brennan had a podcast which lived on his personal domain <a href="http://brennandunn.com">brennandunn.com</a>. Whenever he wrote an article, he would publish it on the blog of his software product, <a href="http://www.planscope.io">Planscope</a>.</p>

<p>Brennan recently decided to change how he was publishing content. He created a new site <a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com">doubleyourfreelancing.com</a>, and moved all of his content over to that site. His content is based around selling to freelancers, and this site is all about growing your freelancing business. He got the name from one of his most popular products, <em>Double Your Freelancing Rate</em>.</p>

<h3>Using Niche Writing to Get Clients</h3>

<p>By building a site around a certain subject, you position yourself as an authority in that subject. A friend of mine, Denny Cave, works exclusively on the LightCMS platform. He has a site called <a href="http://www.lightignite.com">LightIgnite</a> , which is all about developing on the LightCMS platform. By doing this, he puts himself in the position of being <strong>THE</strong> LightCMS guy, and this brings him a lot of client work.</p>

<h3>Are You Changing Your Blogging Strategy Again?</h3>

<p>No. This time, I'm not changing how I am doing anything, But I think that this is a strategy worth talking about, and worth considering if you are looking for a new way to publish your content, grow an audience, and make more sales.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Will You Take The 30 day Publishing Challenge?]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-03T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/03/30-day-blogging-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Come Ship More Content in September With Me</h3>

<p>I heard about this challenge that a friend of a friend is doing: blog every weekday for 30 days. Here's <a href="http://cdevroe.com/blog/9527/blogging-every-weekday-for-30-days">the original post</a>. Here's the post where I <a href="http://mattdsmith.com/30-day-blog-challenge/">heard about it</a>. I know writing is a valuable skill. Blogging can help you build your reach, prove your authority, and give you an way to provide value to your potential clients and customers by providing them with educational content.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>However, I want to modify this challenge a bit, just because I kind of hate the term "blogging". Blogging is just one way to deliver content, there are several others. Instead, I want to take on the "30-day publishing challenge". Under my rules, any of the following will count as my writing for the day:</p>

<h3>What Counts</h3>

<ul>
<li>Publishing a new blog post. This includes my personal site or sites such as Medium.</li>
<li>Publishing a new letter to people on my mailing list (yep, this is my Day 1)</li>
<li>Publishing a new page or re-writing an existing page on my personal or company site.</li>
<li>Publishing another form of long-form content, such as an email course, eBook, or PDF.
Here are things that don't count:</li>
</ul>


<h3>What Doesn't Count</h3>

<ul>
<li>Republishing existing content in a new form (I've been looking into using Quora's and LinkedIn's publishing platforms to get more reach)</li>
<li>Super short-form content (tweets, tumbles, facebook posts, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>Since I'm bending the rules a bit, I'm going to publish something every 30 days instead of just on weekdays. This also means that for the weekends I'll probably write three things on Friday and space them out over the weekend.</p>

<p>So you up to taking the challenge? If  <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com/contact">drop me a line</a>. I'd love to follow along with what you are doing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[John Saddington: Blogging and Your Future]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/john-saddington-blogging-and-your-future/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T16:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/john-saddington-blogging-and-your-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Video: John Saddington Talks About How Blogging Changed His Life</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/saddington.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p><a href="http://john.do/">John Saddington</a> gave a talk in February for <a href="http://www.meetup.com/transform-athens/">Transform Athens</a> called “Blogging and your Future”. It was an inspiring talk. I don’t think any talk has gotten me to move to action more so than this one. It was published on Youtube and had a view count way lower than it deserved, so I wanted to share it here:</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>"Blogging And Your Future" by John Saddington</h3>

<iframe width="853" height="480" src="http://glennstovall.com//www.youtube.com/embed/ELJMXr7RWF8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>I’m a big proponent of writing as a tool for not only marketing, but for education and communication as well. I’ve written some more on writing in a couple of other places. I’ve talked on my personal blog about <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/personal-blogging-vs-professional-blogging/">why I share some things on my personal site and some here on my company site</a>. I’ve also written on here on how you shouldn’t stop at blogging, but how you should form an entire <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/01/from-blogging-to-content-strategy/">content strategy</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Since posting this article, I've since changed my mind on the opinions shared above. All my blogging content is available here on glennstovall.com Read the follow up here: <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">Why I am killing my company blog</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
