<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: proposals | Essentialist Software Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/proposals/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-04T11:20:01-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Multiple Packages In Your Proposals Instantly Increase Conversions]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-15T09:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/15/why-multiple-packages-in-your-proposals-instantly-increase-conversions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The 3 Tiered Approach That Closes More Sales</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/baseball.png" width="260"></p>

<p>When a freelancer submits a proposal, they will often only include one offer. They will set the deliverable, and the price, and throw their proposal over the wall. When you do this, you give the client a binary option: Hire you or don't.</p>

<p>By giving the client a few different options, you are changing the conversation into one that is more likely to end with the client hiring you.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Selling Services is More like Selling Products Than You Might Think</h3>

<p>Many of the selling principles that I mention in this article are going to be identical to the once I addressed in <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/breakdown-of-a-pricing-grid/">Breakdown of a Pricing Grid</a>. There is more common ground in selling products and selling service than most people realize. When you submit a proposal, you are selling a product to a very specific customer, and you are only selling it once.</p>

<h3>Offers And Solutions</h3>

<p>All proposals that you write follow a simple narrative. "How are you going to get the client from point A to point B?". Point A is why they starting talking to you in the first place. This is a pain point they are having, or a moment they decided that they needed to change something in their business. A <strong>solution</strong> is "point B". The solution is tomorrow. The solution is the inverse of the problem. The <strong>offer</strong> is how you are proposing to get the client from point A to point B. There are multiple ways you can get a client from point A to point B, and these are going to be the basis of the packages you offer.</p>

<h3>The 3 Packages You Should Include In Your Proposal</h3>

<p>Let's say you are at bat in a baseball game. The problem is that you are not on base. The solution is that you want to get on base. There are several ways you can get there. The following is the 3 package template I use in my proposals: The bunt, The line drive, and the home run (now the image at the top of this post makes sense!). Approaching the proposal this way gets me thinking about multiple ways I can solve a client's problem, and helps me and my clients find the offer that fits their needs and wants the best.</p>

<h3>The Bunt</h3>

<p>The lowest package you should offer should be the absolute minimum you can do to get the client to where they want to be. I also call this the <strong>half-complete package</strong>. Based on previous communications with the client, this offer is usually <strong>less</strong> than what they originally asked for. This package is useful because customers that may not have taken your core offering may take you up on this one, turning non-clients into small clients.</p>

<h3>The Line Drive</h3>

<p>This package will be the most in line with what the client requested. In the middle package, I include everything that the client has asked for or that I no are 100% crucial to a successful project. I call this one the <strong>complete package</strong>.</p>

<h3>The Home Run</h3>

<p>Once I have a handle on what the client is looking for, I ask myself "How can I go above and beyond what they asked for?". There is where I come up with the final, most expensive package. I call this one the <strong>complete plus package</strong>. This package is a place where I can up-sell the client, and show my expertise.</p>

<h3>Multiple Packages Give You Built In Up-sells</h3>

<p>The complete plus package is a straight-up up-sell. You took the clients needs and offered to meet their expectations and then some. No matter which package your client buys, you will still have a chance to up-sell them. If they purchase the smallest package, you can always go back and offer to complete more work for them. You have already presenting the client with several offerings, and these can be valuable tools later on in the client relationship.</p>

<h3>Change The Conversation</h3>

<p>The biggest advantage to this approach is that instead of the client thinking "Do I accept this proposal or not?", They now have options. They think "Which option on this proposal do I choose?".</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
