<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: marketing automation | Essentialist Software Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/marketing-automation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-04T14:06:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drip Quick Tip: How to Change the Confirmation Link Text in Your Welcome Email]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/28/drip-quick-tip-how-to-change-the-confirmation-link-text-in-your-welcome-email/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-28T17:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/28/drip-quick-tip-how-to-change-the-confirmation-link-text-in-your-welcome-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are using <a href="http://glennstovall.com/recommends/drip">Drip</a> for your marketing automation, you might want to change the copy on the "Confirm Your Subscription" Link that gets sent when people fill out a form. This link is an important call-to-action, and this little piece of text can have a big impact on your subscription conversion rate. Drip doesn't make it clear how to change this copy, but it is possible.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>When you are creating a form, you will the code for the link. It looks like this:</p>

<p>
{{ confirmation_link }}
</p>

<p>If you want to change the link text, you can use the replace_inner_html function that is available. For example, if you wanted to change your link text to "Join the club." you would do the following:</p>

<p>
{{ confirmation_link | replace_inner_html: "Join the club." }}
</p>

<p>By using this technique, you can have more control over the experience your subscribers have when they join your list and create more enticing calls-to-action in your emails.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start Using Drip Email Campaigns Today]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/start-using-drip-email-campaigns-today</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Increase Engagement And Conversions When People Sign Up For Your Email List</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/drip.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>When building a mailing list, engagement is highest within the first two to three weeks of the person joining the list. However, these people usually get the same content that everyone else on your list getting. Wouldn’t it be great if you could send them content that was optimized for this situation. That’s what <strong>drip email campaigns</strong> are for.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What are Drip Email Campaigns?</h3>

<p>Drip email campaigns are email campaigns that are sent out based on when a subscriber has performed an action instead of being scheduled on a calendar date. While a regular email list campaign may be scheduled to go out on June 1st, 2014 at 1pm, A drip email campaign will be scheduled to be sent out 3 days after a sign up.</p>

<p>Drip marketing campaigns are usually several emails in length. We want to reach out to a person multiple times (but too much, don’t be obnoxious) when they have first joined our list.</p>

<h3>Playing the Long Game</h3>

<p>No matter what you are selling, you are always selling people trust to some degree. People need to believe in your product and believe that you are capable of solving their problem before they will be willing to pay you money to do so. You can’t really build a whole lot of trust on social media or on a landing page. However, it takes much less trust to get someone’s email address, and from there you will have several opportunities to reach out to this person and build trust.</p>

<h3>How to Structure Your Campaign</h3>

<p>The most important thing about your campaign is that you need it to be helpful and valuable to your new subscriber. Your posts need to be mostly selfless. If you run a mailing list and all you do is sell to them, then you are doing it wrong, and it will drive people away. By selling directly less, you will build more trust, and make more sales in the end.</p>

<p>My personal rule is that your helpful content should have a minimum 2:1 ratio of being helpful, and being a sales email. Also, you should mix up between “hard sells” and “soft sells”. A hard sell is an email where the entire point is to get the user to complete a transaction. A soft sell is a message that is still valuable, but contains a subtle message.  For example, I may write an email about how to use lifecycle emails to increase conversions, and follow it up with “And by the way, this is something I love helping clients with. hit ‘reply’ if you would like to talk about us working together.”</p>

<p>Following those rules, here is what a drip campaign might look like:</p>

<ol>
<li>An introductory email.</li>
<li>An educational email.</li>
<li>An education email with a soft sell.</li>
<li>1 -2 more educational emails.</li>
<li>A hard sell.</li>
</ol>


<p>You can change this as you see fit, just stick to the 2:1 ratio.</p>

<h3>Your First Campaign</h3>

<p>If you have done any writing before, you can set your first campaign set up  quickly. Go find 4 – 5 of your best email campaigns or blog posts, and spread them out over 2 -4 weeks. You now have a campaign! This way you are giving your new subscribers your best content at a point when they are most engaged, making this some of the most effective email marketing you can do.</p>

<h3>Using Drip Campaigns as an Incentive</h3>

<p>Which do you think is a better call to action to get people to join a mailing list?</p>

<ul>
<li>Sign up for my newsletter.</li>
<li>Enter your email address and I will give you something for free.</li>
</ul>


<p>I recently wrote a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/">case study</a> about how I used a free eBook in order to jump start one of my lists. You can use your drip campaign as the incentive by framing it as a service. For example, you may have a 30-day course that can teach your potential clients how to do something. ConvertKit is a drip marketing tool that does this on their first page. Since the service revolves around building forms to get people to sign up, they have a <a href="https://convertkit.com/">30 day course on creating forms that convert</a>.</p>

<h3>Tools for Drip Campaigns</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Mailchimp Autoresponders</strong> : Mailchimp doesn’t have any tools built specifically for drip marketing campaigns, but they do have autoresponders, which you can use to set one up. You can set an autoresponder to be sent out X days after someone joins a list, so you can create a drip campaign by creating several autoresponders.</li>
<li><strong>Drip</strong>: As you can tell my the name, Drip is designed specifically for creating drip campaigns. It also integrates well with other email list providers, so if you want to use Drip for your campaigns and Mailchimp or AWeber for your list management, you can do that.</li>
<li><strong>ConvertKit</strong>: ConvertKit is what I have been using lately. It has support for list management, drip campaigns, and offering sign-up incentives.</li>
</ul>


<p>By using drip campaigns, you can have a long form message that you can deliver to every single person that expresses interest in whatever it is your offering. If you have ever done sales where you had to have several emails or phone calls back and forth with a potential client, then you how time consuming that can be. Drip campaigns allow you to automate this process with the people that are in a situation where they are most likely to convert.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
