<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: consulting | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/consulting/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-05T02:03:37-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Presenting Value]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T16:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/19/presenting-value-to-clients</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/wealth.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When selling clients on your services, how you position yourself is important. You want clients to see you as an investment, not an expense. In order to accomplish this, you need to make sure you are able to clearly state and justify the value you can bring to a client.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Three Types of Value</h3>

<p>There are three primary types of value you can provide to clients, and all of your sales pitches should anchor to one or more of these points:</p>

<ul>
<li>You make your client money.</li>
<li>You save your client time.</li>
<li>You reduce the client's risk.</li>
</ul>


<p>What value <strong>isn't</strong> is things like "writing code" or "designing web pages". These are just tools you are using to accomplish a goal. When you are talking to potential clients you need to be talking about the goal, not the way you are planning on getting there. A client's primary concern is the end result of your work.</p>

<p>You may also notice that saving the client money is absent from this list, even though it sounds like it should be on there. While it's good if you find a way to save a client money, products and services that save money are a much more difficult sale, as people who are focused on reducing cost are looking for ways to <em>not</em> spend money, which makes them a pretty tough sell.</p>

<h2>Making Money</h2>

<p>Presenting value here is the easiest of the three. If you can find a way to peg your work to numbers that affect the bottom line, then focus on that. Let's say you do A/B testing, and you think that your testing could increase conversions by 10%. If you go to a store that makes $100,000 dollars in sales a year, then your services are easily worth $10,000 to them.</p>

<h2>Saving Time</h2>

<p>This is the one I find myself talking about often, since I work in software development, and love finding ways to automate processes. I've called myself a "Job Destroyer" before. Saving a client (or a client's employees) time can easily be tied to money as well. I doubt a client would willingly share an employee's salary with you, but you can make an educated guess as to the cost of an employee:</p>

<ul>
<li>First, get an estimated salary. You can just guess, or use a service like <a href="http://www.glassdoor.com">glassdoor</a> to approximate the number. In this example, let's say that an employee has a salary of $50,000.</li>
<li>Secondly, we are going <a href="http://web.mit.edu/e-club/hadzima/how-much-does-an-employee-cost.html">multiply that number by 2.7</a>. This is to factor in all of the other costs of that employee. Now we have an employee that costs $135,000 a year.</li>
<li>Now, let's break that down into an hourly rate. The easiest calculation would be to say salary / 2000, or 50 weeks at 40 hours per week. However, I feel like 1500 may be a better estimate if we want to go by <strong>productive</strong> time, since I don't believe anyone is truly and consistently productive for eight hours a day. between those two numbers, we have an hourly range of value of $67.50 - $90.</li>
</ul>


<p>Going by this formula, if you are able to make a 2 hour job take little or no time, then over the course of a year software that could do that would provide up to $9,000 a year in value. If you can scale that to 10 employees, then it's $90,000. This is why being able to save time is so valuable to clients.</p>

<h2>Reducing Risk</h2>

<p>Reducing risk is the most abstract of the three, and can be harder to pin an exact number on. Software projects are inherently risky, and anything you can do to reduce that risk is valuable to the client. You see this in consumer sales all the time money back guarantees. By making that guarantee, the product is more valuable since you know that if you are not satisfied you can get your money back.</p>

<p>As a consultant, there are several ways I show that I can reduce risk to clients:</p>

<ul>
<li>Sending clients weekly reports and/or having weekly meetings, So they are always aware of where the project stands. Freelance web developers and designers have a reputation for being flaky, so this helps address that.</li>
<li>Having a set development process in place. This way clients know that I have a more predictable process with more predictable results.</li>
<li>Having a network of other talented people, and letting the client know that if there is something outside of my scope of skills I can bring someone on to help out with the task.</li>
</ul>


<p>Things like having a portfolio and client testimonials are other ways of reducing risk in the eyes of clients. These send the message that other people have worked with before, gotten results, and are satisfied.</p>

<p>However, these all address the reduction of risk in the process, not in the end result. There are several ways this can be accomplished as well. A couple of examples are doing market and competitor research, to see what the project is facing and making sure it is framed appropriately. Another that I am a big fan of is getting to market earlier and iterating quickly. This allows you to work with real people and gather real data. Any decisions made before launch are in many ways an educated guess, and solutions and plans built on objective data instead of guesses will always have a higher chance of succeeding.</p>

<p>Framing your work in this fashion can help both yourself and your clients. It can help you by not only seeing how to present value, but help you find new ways to provide more value to clients when you work as well. This can also help you land more sales and stand out from the competition.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.</p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);console.log('event fired')">
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
  
<style type="text/css">
</style>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
If the form above doesn't work, you can get it [here](https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook).
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take Out The Tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/take-out-the-tech/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T15:25:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/03/05/take-out-the-tech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/make_fire.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>If you are a freelance developer, designer, photographer, or even a freelance sheep sheerer, it's easy to get caught up in what it is you do, versus why it is we actually do it. More important than why we do it, is why people are willing to pay us good money for what we do. In this article I'd like to take a look at why I decided to re-position my services, and most important of all, get you to stop talking like a nerd because it's costing you money and sales.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>No More Nerd Speak</h2>

<p>When I decided to focus more on being a consultant, and not just a "freelance web developer", one of my qualifiers for the kinds of clients I wanted to attract was that a client should not care about the tech stack I was working on. words like  "WordPress" and "Ruby on Rails" were dirty curse words as far as proposals were concerned. I had several reasons for this:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Client Filtering:</strong> Clients that use words like 'PHP Developer', are usually looking for contractors, not consultants. There is nothing wrong with being a contractor, I've done it many times, but it isn't in line with my future business goals.</li>
<li><strong>Focusing on Solutions &amp; Value:</strong> There is no problem that has to be solved by a certain language or framework. Some are better suited than others. A client that wants a "Rails app that does X" may be better served by a "Node.js app that does X" or a Mobile Application that does X". They may even be better served by a nice spreadsheet or an actionable plan they can stick to. By taking technical terms out of the conversations, it allows for more focus on the problem, and the solution to be discovered.</li>
<li><strong>Autonomy:</strong> Similar to the point above, I want the autonomy to decide what tool would be the best fit for the jobs I take on, and be able to use them. If a client does not know what tools are used, which they shouldn't, then they have no say in the matter.</li>
<li><strong>Client Interest:</strong> Clients don't care about this kind of stuff nearly as much we do. Clients are usually very busy people in their businesses and our lives. By leaving out talk of weird, complicated things that they don't understand and have no interest in, you are doing your clients a great kindness.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Closing the Text Editor</h2>

<p>One day at work I decided to do a mental exercise. If I close my text editor, how could I still provide value to clients? I wanted to step away from just thinking that "code = value" and take a more holistic approach at what I provide to clients.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Communication:</strong> Web developers and designers have a reputation for being unreliable and hard to reach. Being proactive with clients on phone, email, and in person makes them feel more secure about their project, reduces their stress, and prevents misunderstanding that can waste time on both ends of the table.</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Having a solid plan in place and communicating that plan has a lot of benefits. It maintains accountability and expectations on both sides. Providing a clear plan to a client on how you are going to perform work and when they can expect it to be delivered. It shows that you aren't just another unreliable, uncommunicative developer like they have probably encountered in the past.</li>
<li><strong>Research:</strong> Who is their target market? What is a good pricing strategy for their new product? How can your client reach their target demographic? Do they like the new feature implemented? Being able to provide answers to questions like this can help guide a client in the right direction, and help your work produce even more value.</li>
</ul>


<p>I've realized to think about deliverable products in a broader sense. A road map for a project is every bit as much of a deliverable as a new feature that has been coded, and should be treated and presented as such. (<strong>Pro-tip:</strong> clients like nicely formatted PDFs that they can share with other people in their company.)</p>

<h2>Don't Sell Yourself Short</h2>

<p>Designers, developers, copywriters, etc. are costing themselves money by thinking that only producing their core competency. I've had aspiring freelancers ask me "Should I bill for phone calls/meetings/emails?". I say yes. Some people will say because they are taking up your time, and that since being a freelancer usually equates to selling your time for money, client communication counts. They're right, but for the wrong reasons. The reason you bill for those times is <em>because you providing the client with value</em>. Your communications that help you gather information to deliver the exact solution, and ease the clients concern are just as valuable as the core product you produce, <strong>if not more so.</strong></p>

<p>So to other freelancers out there: <strong>Don't sell yourself short.</strong> And stop talking so much about how you swing your hammer, and instead about what you can build and why it's so valuable.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.</p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);console.log('event fired')">
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
  
<style type="text/css">
</style>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
If the form above doesn't work, you can get it [here](https://app.convertkit.com/concordant/freelance-pricing-handbook).
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
