<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: metrics | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/metrics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-09T09:01:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better Business Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/better-business-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T19:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/08/04/better-business-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Get Better Information From The Same Data</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/analytics.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>It’s important to track metrics in your business. Tracking metrics means that you can make decisions based on numbers and cold hard facts instead of guessing and gut feelings. But not all metrics are created equal, and not all ways of tracking metrics are creating equal. If you are looking at the wrong numbers, then you could end up making disastrous decisions. Let’s take a look at the best ways to track metrics, and the most important numbers you need to be keeping an eye on.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Metrics by Time</h3>

<p>You want to look at metrics in units of time. “Grand total” type metrics, such as total number of Facebook followers, doesn’t tell you anything about the current standing of your business. In this example, you would want to look at “new Facebook followers per month” instead. This way you can see how you are doing at your key performance indicators <em>right now</em>.</p>

<h3>Metrics by Change</h3>

<p>What’s even better than looking at metrics is weekly or monthly units, is looking at the comparison of those units. Even better than “new Facebook followers per month” would to compare this month’s number to last month’s number, and come up with a new metric, “% change in new Facebook followers”. This is the number where you want to move the meter. This shows the rate of growth inside your company.</p>

<p>This is one of those times in life where calculus is actually useful. By looking at these numbers, you are looking at the velocity and acceleration of your business. If you are driving a car and want to reach your destination faster, you don’t look at how many miles you have traveled, you look at your miles per hour (a metric over time), and put the pedal in the medal in order to increase your miles per hour over time (a metric by change).</p>

<h3>Three Primary Metrics</h3>

<p>There are three primary metrics that every business, no matter how large or small, no matter how tech-savvy or old-school, should be looking at:</p>

<ul>
<li>Leads: The number of potential customers you are making contact with each month.</li>
<li>Conversions: What percentage of those leads are you able to convert into paying customers?</li>
<li>Profit: Is your business making enough money to be viable. Profit is just the child of two other important metrics, Revenue and Expenses, which are both important in their own right.</li>
</ul>


<p>I’m not saying these are the only things worth tracking, but if you don’t know these numbers then this would be a good place to start. It’s better to focus on a few important metrics than many unimportant ones. While keeping up with numbers is a good thing, you don’t want to drown out the signal with a lot of noise.</p>

<h3>Vanity Metrics</h3>

<p>There are a number of metrics that you probably actively avoid tracking in order to prevent you from making bad decisions. If you tracked number of sales of a certain type of product, but the cost of a sale of that product caused you to lose money on it, then you would end up trying to increase the units sold, and eventually end up in the poor house
. Here are some examples of numbers that are not worth wasting your time on:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Registered Users</strong>: Getting users to try a new service once is easy. Getting users to stay is something else altogether.</li>
<li><strong>Pageviews</strong>: Pageviews can be easily manipulated, and are worth very little. It also doesn’t tell you about the quality of the traffic. I would rather have 10 visits from potential clients than 1,000 visits from people from Hacker News who happened to like a blog article.</li>
<li><strong>Likes</strong> Unless your business is heavily focused in the social media space, I wouldn’t put a lot of weight on how many likes, shares, retweets, and so on your company gets. These are like pageviews but another step removed and that much more worthless.</li>
</ul>


<p>These are called vanity metrics because they make you feel good. However, none of these are actionable and don’t have any impact on the bottom line of your business. Don’t get caught up in trying to move these numbers much.</p>

<h3>Further Watching</h3>

<p>If you’d like to learn more about metrics, what to watch and how to watch them, Ben Yoskovitz gave a talk called “Lean Analytics: How to Focus on What Matters” Which is available for free online. I highly recommend it:</p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/70981922">Ben Yoskovitz – Lean Analytics: How to Focus on What Matters</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/user12790628">MicroConf</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AARRR! Pirate Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/30/aarrr-pirate-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T12:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/30/aarrr-pirate-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>How to Track the 5 Numbers That Define Your Company's Success</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/pirate.png" width="260"></p>

<p><small class='notice'><em>This post orignally appeared on <a href="http://www.concordantsolutions.com">Concordant Solutions</a>. Read <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/07/29/why-i-am-killing-my-company-blog/">why it moved</a>.</em></small></p>

<p>Pirate Metrics refers to an the acronym ‘AARRR’, which stands for five metrics used to track the performance of your business online. The five metrics are Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Referrals, and Revenue. By tracking these metrics, you can get a clearer picture of the health of your business, and figure out where you should focus your efforts. The idea was popularized by <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dmc500hats/startup-metrics-for-pirates-long-version">Dave McClure</a>. These ideas are a framework for how to approach your online business and all of them won’t apply to everyone. Today I’d like to give you an overview of what they are, how to track them, and some ideas on how to improve your performance in each. I hope this will get the gears turning on how to apply them to your business.</p>

<!-- more -->




<div style='clear:both'></div>


<h3>Acquisition</h3>

<p>Acquisition is how many visits you are getting to your site. This is getting people to be aware of your existence, and giving you a chance to sell them on your product.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> Website visits are the easiest thing to track when it comes to your website. Tools like <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics">Google Analytics</a> make this simple.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> How to increase your traffic could vary greatly depending on the type of site you have. Online advertising like Google Adwords, or on networks like Facebook or Reddit, are a direct way to get traffic. You can also try longer term strategies such as SEO and content marketing.</p>

<h3>Activation</h3>

<p>Activation is getting people to complete a call-to-action. This could mean making a sale, or getting users to sign up for a subscription services. It could even be just collecting an email address. In our case, we consider an activation someone using the contact form to get in touch with us and start a conversation. Sometimes it’s as simple as collecting an email address.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> Depends. most e-commerce services have ways of tracking sales, as do most CMSes. For collecting emails for newsletters, tools like Mailchimp have this built in as well.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> Split testing is a good strategy here. On whatever pages you are trying to get people to sign up, test the copy, the style, your call to action, everything.</p>

<h3>Retention</h3>

<p>Retention refers to tracking that people who have become your customer stay your customer. If you have a subscription service, you don’t want people to cancel. If you are making sales, you want people to be repeat customers.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> If you working with customers monthly, you can track how many stay for a certain amount of time, such as 6 months. For sales, you could track how many customers are repeat customers and how often they return. Another approach would be to track the frequency in which people use your service, such as monitoring how often people log in.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> The two biggest factors are the ease of use of your application and customer service. Retention relies on you keeping existing customers happy. Being responsive, testing your interface, and listening to feedback are all good ways to increase retention.</p>

<h3>Referrals</h3>

<p>Word of mouth is the most valuable form of marketing you have. Tracking referrals can give you insight into customer happiness.</p>

<p><strong>How To Track It:</strong> Social Media has made this easier. You can track how many people are mentioning you or your domain on Twitter. Be sure to interact back as well.</p>

<p><strong>How To Improve It:</strong> Make it easy for your clients to talk about you. Give them a clear message, and be sure to make sure to provide links to easily share your content.</p>

<h3>Revenue</h3>

<p>The one everyone cares about and the most explicit one. How much money you are pulling in.</p>

<p><strong>How to Track It:</strong> With your bank account.</p>

<p><strong>How to Improve It:</strong> This one is harder to improve on it’s own. It’s usually a result of working on the four above. You can try things like experimenting with your pricing model and service offerings.</p>

<p>All of these metrics will help one another, and usually aren’t in a vacuum. For example, Most things that increase retention will tend to increase referrals. Increasing referrals will increase acquisition. Increasing acquisition can increase activation, which can increase revenue, and so on. If you’d like to talk more about this and want some help with getting these numbers up for your business, or even just finding better ways to track them, <a href="http://glennstovall.com/contact">Let’s talk about it</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
