<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: freelance | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://gsto.github.com/blog/categories/freelance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gsto.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-19T08:25:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://gsto.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to bill Daily or Weekly]]></title>
    <link href="http://gsto.github.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T16:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gsto.github.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/calendar.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When it comes to freelancing, you may think you only have two options when it comes to how you bill your clients: You can bill by the hour, or you can bill by the project. But these aren't your only options, and in many cases they are not your best ones.</p>

<p>Two alternatives to this is billing by the day, or billing by the week. These billing structures are a little more uncommon, but in my experience as a consultant, they have been the most effective and productive. Since these structures are a little bit different, they often require a little bit of explanation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What's In A Day?</h3>

<p>An hour is a definite measure of time. it's 60 minutes. When you bill a client for a hour, they expect to be providing value during those 60 minutes. A day is also a definite measure of time, but if you bill a client for a day they don't expect 24 hours of productivity from you.</p>

<p>You make think that a work day of 8 hours is a more reasonable assumption, but that also isn't the case. Many studies have shown that creative workers are only productive for <a href="http://qz.com/157092/the-case-for-a-six-hour-workday/">5 to 6 hours a day</a>, and that increased hours can in fact lead to decreased productivity. So when it comes to billing by the day, it just means whatever you think a good day's work means to you. It doesn't mean that it has to be all of your time, or that if you bill for a day you can't do any other productive work for another client.</p>

<p>If you have been working in freelancing or consulting and have been keeping track of your hours, you can use that data to determine your day rate.</p>

<h3>Weekly Billing and Deadlines</h3>

<p>Weekly billing tends to work a little bit differently. When you bill by the week, you do so with a goal and a deliverable for the week. Weekly billing is in a way like billing a flat project rate, but you are delivering smaller projects in a smaller time frame.</p>

<p>Weekly billing may seem strange at first, but if you think about it, this is how salaried employees basically work.</p>

<p>With my clients, I set milestones every two weeks, and tell them that I will deliver on those milestones in the time frame. It doesn't matter if I am working 30 hours a week, or 40, or 60, or 5. As long as the results and value are delivered, that is what counts.</p>

<p>The other thing I like about weekly billing is that it makes scheduling my availability much simpler. I can look at my calendar, see that I have worked booked for the next 6 weeks, and have a clear date for when I am available for more work.</p>

<h3>How to Decide on a Pricing Model</h3>

<p>I don't think that any consultant should stick to just one pricing structure, unless you work on a narrow type of project. Different projects and different clients will work better with different billing structures. Here is when I would consider each one:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Hourly Billing:</strong> For jobs where the scope is unknown and flexibility is needed.</li>
<li><strong>Flat Rate Billing:</strong> When the scope of a project can be well defined and the project is small.</li>
<li><strong>Daily Billing:</strong> Works well for one day consulting arrangements, and also for projects that you want to commit to part time (such as 2 - 3 days per week)</li>
<li><strong>Weekly Billing:</strong> My personal favorite. Tends to work well on larger projects, and projects that need flexibility and aren't committed to a hard scope.</li>
</ul>


<p>By thinking about how you price and position your services, you can come up with plans that can make your scheduling better, and help you price your services more aggressively.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT:</strong> Just found this episode of The Freelancer's Show where they discuss <a href="http://www.freelancersshow.com/the-freelancers-show-097-weekly-billing/">weekly billing</a>, Worth a listen if you want to hear more about this subject.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
