<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: freelance | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/freelance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-13T23:29:24-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Ways To Build A $200,000 Consultancy]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T05:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/10/15/5-ways-to-build-a-200000-consultancy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/5waysto_key.png" width="260"></p>

<p>I recently read an article entitled <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">5 ways to build a $100 million dollar business</a>. It discusses different business models that vary on the number and size of your customer base. Some businesses work with a few enterprise scale clients, while others work with a larger number of smaller customers. Patrick Mackenzie mentioned on Twitter that <a href="https://twitter.com/patio11/status/521878305151000577">"The math here is equally applicable if you are trying to build, say, a $200k a year business"</a>.A $200k/yr consultancy is a goal that seems both attractive and attainable, so I decided try and answer the question "How can you build a $200,000 consultancy?"</p>

<!-- more -->


<div style='clear:both;'></div>


<h3>Find 1 Client That Pays You $200,000 (The Elephant)</h3>

<p>I've been a part of projects where a single engagement has had a price tag of $200,000 or more. I think this scenario is a little unlikely. If you can find one of these clients, then you can find more, and you are on your way to becoming a $1mm+ consultancy. It would also be very risky for a company to put all of it's eggs in one basket like this.</p>

<h3>Find 10 Clients That Pay You $20,000 (The Deer)</h3>

<p>There are a few examples of consultancies that make this kind of money. One is custom application development services that can handle ten projects in a year. Most of the client work I find is in this range. Another example is high end consulting engagements. People like <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/">Patrick Mackenzie</a> and <a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com/">Brennan Dunn</a> charge anywhere from $10,000 - $30,000 for a week of their services. They could work 10 engagements a year and hit this $200,000 benchmark.</p>

<h3>Find 100 Clients That Pay You $2,000 (The Rabbits)</h3>

<p>With this setup, your consultancy would have to have a service that scales very well. One way to accomplish this would be to find a way to service multiple clients at one time. Hosting courses or seminars is a way you could accomplish this. For example, Big Nerd Ranch offers <a href="https://training.bignerdranch.com/classes/advanced-ios-bootcamp">programming courses that cost $4,200</a>. At this point, the focus of the work changes. This is less of a consulting model and more of an information product model. There are plenty of gigs out there that pay $2,000 for smaller jobs, which are fine but those are hard to scale.</p>

<h3>Find 1,000 Customers That Pay You $200 (The Mice)</h3>

<p>At this level, you need a product that you can resell. It could be a course that requires little to no interaction for $200 (For example, a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/comprehensive-ruby-on-rails/?dtcode=Q73iZAp1GbIa">UDemy</a> course), or it could be some form of subscription product, which would cost just shy of $20/month. For software developers, you may be able to build a premium software framework or plugin that can sell for this amount. The <a href="http://www.magentocommerce.com/magento-connect/">Magento Connect marketplace</a> is a good example of people going this model. I can't think of any kind of repeatable service model that works at this scale.</p>

<h3>Find 10,000 Customers That Pay You $20 (The Files)</h3>

<p>You are a product business at this point. You could sell ebooks, themes, plugins, or something of that nature. You really can't call it a consultancy at this point. For this kind of business, it looks like the math doesn't scale don't quite so well at this point.</p>

<h3>Applying This To Your Business</h3>

<p>Do you want to work on $2,000 or $200,000 projects? Before you say "$200,000, duh." Think about the pros and cons of fewer clients vs. more, and smaller clients vs. large. Fewer larger clients means a more rigorous, in-depth sales process, and a higher risk if you lose a client.</p>

<p>What kind of consultancy do you want to run, and how are you going to scale it? You can scale not only by getting more clients, but by getting bigger ones as well. If you think about the kind of business you <strong>want</strong> to be running, then you can start making deliberate steps to get there.</p>

<p><div class="ck_form">
  <div class="ck_form_content">
    <h3 class="ck_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
    <div class="ck_description">
      <span class="ck_image">
        <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
      </span>
      <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.</p>
    </div>
  </div>   
  
  
  <div class="ck_form_fields">
    
    <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
      <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
    </div>
    
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
        <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>
      
      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
</div> 
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=15"></script>
</p>

<p><small>Image by <a href="http://christophjanz.blogspot.com/2014/10/five-ways-to-build-100-million-business.html">Christoph Janz</a></small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning To Say No]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/no.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I just looked in the mirror. I had several more gray hairs in my beard than I had before. I had taken on more client work than I could handle, and had been working long nights and weekends. I knew I was tired and stressed, but it was a real wake up call to see the physical effects of burnout, in addition to the mental. It was at that moment I realized something had to change with how I was managing my business. If you are a freelancer, You have to learn how to say no. Your business, just like a product, is going to be designed. If you don't carefully, mindfully design your own business, then other people will do it for you. And they won't have your best interest at heart.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>The Overworked Freelancer</h3>

<p>It's a common story: The freelancer who is working long hours into the night and on weekends. As freelancers, we should be in control. Why do people who are in charge of their own career and lifestyle decide to do such stressful, harmful things to themselves? Taking on too many responsibilities is not just harmful to ourselves, it's harmful to the quality of our work and our relationships with clients, which is the backbone of our business.</p>

<p>It seems counter intuitive, but by doing so much we are getting so much less done. By taking on <em>less</em> work, we are able to provide a better customer experience and deliver better work.</p>

<h3>Fear of Famine</h3>

<p>The reason that most people say yes to any job, no matter the circumstance, is that they are afraid of where the next one will come from. People will take on a job that is detrimental to their career because they are afraid of not having any client work at all. The issue is that again, the most intuitive solution is not the most effective one. If you spent the same number of hours you work you would spend on a toxic client defining and look for clients you like, you could easily get enough work to sustain yourself, and feel a lot better about your work.</p>

<h3>Saying no to Toxic Clients</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, your clients ARE your business. As such, you need to be selective as to whom you allow into your business. Toxic clients are clients that are a drain on your time, and your resources, while providing little in return. If you have clients like this, I would suggest you fire them immediately. Take the time that you would have spent working with them and start spending it finding better clients. I would also work on setting up a qualification process for your potential clients, so that you can prevent toxic clients from meeting with you in the first place. I send out a standard email with a few questions to potential clients, and if they don't have a good budget, or the project seems like something I would not be interested in, Then I politely decline. If they seem like good clients who are just not a good fir for myself in particular, I will pass them along to another one of my contacts who may be a better fit. By doing this, I have more time to spend on client work that I love.</p>

<h3>How to Say No</h3>

<p>It may feel like saying 'No' is rude in a lot of circumstances, but that, much like the fear of famine, is a fear that can reasoned away. If you don't want to take something on, then you can simply say that you are busy or that you don't have the bandwidth for it. If it is a client, then saying "We wouldn't be a good fit" is a magic phrase that gets you out of most engagements. When dealing with no-longer-potential clients, always take the blame on yourself if you can, it will make your rejection much more palpable.</p>

<p>Some people may resent you, but even more will respect you. It shows that your time is valuable and that you won't just give it up to anyone for any reason. It also allows you to play a little "hard to get" with clients, which makes you seem more valuable in their eyes.</p>

<h3>HELL YES or No</h3>

<p>Derek Sivers summed this up perfectly: You should say <a href="http://sivers.org/hellyeah">"Hell YEAH! or No"</a> to any opportunities you are provided. If something doesn't excite you, if a commitment on your time or energy is a maybe in your mind, then you need to say no. It feels good to say yes to people, but this is what leads to feeling too busy, and too stressed. You have to start saying no more often to escape.</p>

<p>But by saying no to these things, we are enabling ourselves to say "Yes" to things we <strong>really</strong> love. Here is a chart from a new book called <a href="http://gregmckeown.com/essentialism-the-disciplined-pursuit-of-less/">"Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less"</a> That sums this philosophy up perfectly. Instead of sending our energy out in a hundred directions, and feeling like we aren't making any progress, By eliminating the nonessential we can focus our energy in a direction that really matters.</p>

<p><img src="/images/essentialism.jpg"></p>

<p>It can be scary, but once you get used to it, the feeling of saying no is incredibly freeing.</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Freelance Pricing Handbook Launch Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T10:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Whenever I finish a product, I like to write a post-mortem. A post-mortem answers a few important questions: What w went well? What went wrong? What could be done better next time? I usually keep these to myself, but this time I wanted to share. Building an email list is something every business should be doing, and I wanted to share the specific techniques I used in order to increase the size of a list 500% in 2 days.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Goal</h3>

<p>Start building a mailing list, and learn more about effective email marketing in the process. I plan on releasing a book targeted at freelancers hopefully in July, so I would like to start building a list now in order to build trust and have a targeted audience when I am ready to sell.</p>

<h3>The Process</h3>

<p> I signed up for Nathan Barry's <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a> Email list software. This includes enrolling in his "ConvertKit Academy" Which is an email course along with a few Google Hangout sessions with Nathan where you get a chance to talk about your personal goals.</p>

<p> Nathan heavily suggested that you have some form on incentive to get people to sign up for your list. He mentioned that you could do a free book, and it could just be a compilation of old writings. He also mentioned setting up a drip marketing course, and ConvertKit comes with a template for that. I looked over some past blog posts and decided to go that route.</p>

<h3>Writing The Book</h3>

<p> Writing the book, and I use the term writing loosely, took about a day. It's a compilation of a few different blog articles I had written, along with some content from a chapter I already had completed for my larger book profit. I drafted up a table of contents, and edited the content together, and wrote about 4 - 5 pages of new content to fill in gaps.  I made the PDF in Pages on the mac.</p>

<p> Then it came to the editing stage. I sent my current list of about 15 people an email announcing the book and asking if anyone wanted a copy. I also did the same of Twitter. I got a lot of amazing responses of people willing to read my book and offer feedback.</p>

<p> After I took a couple hours to edit the content together, I was ready to launch.</p>

<h3>Launching the book</h3>

<p>  Here were the steps I took in order to launch the book</p>

<ul>
<li>I added the ConvertKit form to several blog posts that I thought were relevant to the audience.</li>
<li>Created a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">new landing page</a></li>
<li>Wrote two announcement posts, one on <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/">My personal domain</a> and on my <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/announcing-freelance-pricing-handbook/">company domain</a></li>
<li>Posted links on Facebook, Twitter, Reddit, and LinkedIn</li>
<li>Sent an email out to my original list about the book being released. Also included a P.S. asking them to share on Facebook &amp; Twitter if they felt so inclined</li>
<li>Asked my <a href="http://www.fourathens.com/">local tech community</a> to take a look and help out on social media if they wanted to.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Results</h3>

<p>  By the end of the week I had 84 new subscribers to my list. This was with 323 visitors and a conversion rate of 25.8%</p>

<p>  According to Google Analytics, My site had ~600 visits this week, mostly coming from direct traffic (which is odd, I feel like there are some referrals that don't get tracked properly), then Reddit, then Facebook, in that order.</p>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<p>  Having friends help out on social media seemed like a huge boost. I don't think I've gotten that much traffic from Facebook before. I also had a few people say nice things on Twitter, which I quickly embedded on the landing page as testimonials. The best way to expand your audience is to find ways you can leverage the audience of others.</p>

<p>  Also, writing a book, even when that book is just a PDF "best-of" of your blog, seems really cool to a lot of people. Content in PDF form is just seen as more valuable, and I think having this product out there gives me more credibility.</p>

<h3>What went wrong</h3>

<p>  I found out after the fact the form didn't render correctly on mobile devices, and made it impossible to sign up if you landed on the landing page via a phone. :( That definitely costs me a few conversions. I added a link below that links to a form directly, though perhaps I should find a better way to set up the form so that it renders in a more responsive friendly way.</p>

<h3>What I learned</h3>

<p>  Using incentives to build email lists really does work! My list went from 15 to 100 in a few days. It is also nice to always have something free to offer users in order to provide value for them.</p>

<p>  My next goal is to take these principles and find a way to apply them in a way I can use to target potential clients for my consulting services. I'm not sure what that is going to look like, but I'm sure if I keep writing it'll make sense eventually.</p>

<p>  If you'd like the read the book (and join my mailing list for freelancers), you can get the book below:</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing The Freelance Pricing Handbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> <img class="left" src="/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p> Today I'm proud to announce a new free eBook guide. The book is called the <em>Freelance Pricing Handbook</em>, and it's designed to help freelancers find their perfect rate. The most common question I hear from current and aspiring freelancers is "How much should I charge?" This book sets out to answer this question.</p>

<p> <!-- more --></p>

<p> This book is designed to be a short and easy read to help you understand how to find your perfect price. In addition to help you find your rate, it also includes different ways to package and bill for your services. How you price and position your services has a bigger impact on your bottom line than the amount of skill you have. This book is designed to make sure you aren't undervaluing yourself and are getting paid the rates you deserve.
If you'd like a copy of the book, enter your email address below and I'll email you a copy.</p>

<p>Be sure to let me know what you think!</p>

<p><div class="ck_embed_form ck_horizontal_subscription_form">
  <div class="ck_embed_form_content">
      <h3 class="ck_embed_form_title">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <div class="ck_embed_description">
        <span class="ck_image">
          <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
        </span>
          <p>Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      </div>
  </div>   
   
  <div id='ck_success_msg'  style='display:none;'>
    <p>Thanks! Now check your email.</p>
  </div>
  
    <!--  Form starts here  -->
    <form id="ck_subscribe_form" class="ck_subscribe_form" action="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531/subscribe" data-remote="true" onSubmit="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Newsletter','FPH Download','standard']);">
    <div class="ck_image mobile-only">
    <img alt="Book-portrait" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/convertkit/subscription_forms/images/004/811/858/standard/Book-Portrait.png?1398265358" />
    </div>
      <h3 class="mobile-only">Freelance Pricing Handbook</h3>
      <p class="mobile-only">Figure out how much to charge for your services. Learn when to bill hourly, when to bill a flat rate, and when to do something completely different.<a href='http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook'>Learn More...</a></p>
      <input type="hidden" name="id" value="531" id="landing_page_id"></input>
      <p class="ck_errorArea"></p>
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_firstNameField">First Name</label>
        <input type="text" name="first_name" class="ck_first_name" id="ck_firstNameField" required></input>
      </div>  
      <div class="ck_control_group">
        <label class="ck_label" for="ck_emailField">Email Address</label>
          <input type="email" name="email" class="ck_email_address" id="ck_emailField" required></input>
      </div>

      <button class="subscribe_button ck_subscribe_button btn fields" id='ck_subscribe_button'>
        Download the Free Book
      </button>
      <span class="ck_guarantee">We won't send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.</span>
    </form>
  </div>
<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/assets/CKJS4.js?v=12"></script>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
