<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: freelance | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/freelance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-14T19:51:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning To Say No]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/no.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I just looked in the mirror. I had several more gray hairs in my beard than I had before. I had taken on more client work than I could handle, and had been working long nights and weekends. I knew I was tired and stressed, but it was a real wake up call to see the physical effects of burnout, in addition to the mental. It was at that moment I realized something had to change with how I was managing my business. If you are a freelancer, You have to learn how to say no. Your business, just like a product, is going to be designed. If you don't carefully, mindfully design your own business, then other people will do it for you. And they won't have your best interest at heart.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>The Overworked Freelancer</h3>

<p>It's a common story: The freelancer who is working long hours into the night and on weekends. As freelancers, we should be in control. Why do people who are in charge of their own career and lifestyle decide to do such stressful, harmful things to themselves? Taking on too many responsibilities is not just harmful to ourselves, it's harmful to the quality of our work and our relationships with clients, which is the backbone of our business.</p>

<p>It seems counter intuitive, but by doing so much we are getting so much less done. By taking on <em>less</em> work, we are able to provide a better customer experience and deliver better work.</p>

<h3>Fear of Famine</h3>

<p>The reason that most people say yes to any job, no matter the circumstance, is that they are afraid of where the next one will come from. People will take on a job that is detrimental to their career because they are afraid of not having any client work at all. The issue is that again, the most intuitive solution is not the most effective one. If you spent the same number of hours you work you would spend on a toxic client defining and look for clients you like, you could easily get enough work to sustain yourself, and feel a lot better about your work.</p>

<h3>Saying no to Toxic Clients</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, your clients ARE your business. As such, you need to be selective as to whom you allow into your business. Toxic clients are clients that are a drain on your time, and your resources, while providing little in return. If you have clients like this, I would suggest you fire them immediately. Take the time that you would have spent working with them and start spending it finding better clients. I would also work on setting up a qualification process for your potential clients, so that you can prevent toxic clients from meeting with you in the first place. I send out a standard email with a few questions to potential clients, and if they don't have a good budget, or the project seems like something I would not be interested in, Then I politely decline. If they seem like good clients who are just not a good fir for myself in particular, I will pass them along to another one of my contacts who may be a better fit. By doing this, I have more time to spend on client work that I love.</p>

<h3>How to Say No</h3>

<p>It may feel like saying 'No' is rude in a lot of circumstances, but that, much like the fear of famine, is a fear that can reasoned away. If you don't want to take something on, then you can simply say that you are busy or that you don't have the bandwidth for it. If it is a client, then saying "We wouldn't be a good fit" is a magic phrase that gets you out of most engagements. When dealing with no-longer-potential clients, always take the blame on yourself if you can, it will make your rejection much more palpable.</p>

<p>Some people may resent you, but even more will respect you. It shows that your time is valuable and that you won't just give it up to anyone for any reason. It also allows you to play a little "hard to get" with clients, which makes you seem more valuable in their eyes.</p>

<h3>HELL YES or No</h3>

<p>Derek Sivers summed this up perfectly: You should say <a href="http://sivers.org/hellyeah">"Hell YEAH! or No"</a> to any opportunities you are provided. If something doesn't excite you, if a commitment on your time or energy is a maybe in your mind, then you need to say no. It feels good to say yes to people, but this is what leads to feeling too busy, and too stressed. You have to start saying no more often to escape.</p>

<p>But by saying no to these things, we are enabling ourselves to say "Yes" to things we <strong>really</strong> love. Here is a chart from a new book called <a href="http://gregmckeown.com/essentialism-the-disciplined-pursuit-of-less/">"Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less"</a> That sums this philosophy up perfectly. Instead of sending our energy out in a hundred directions, and feeling like we aren't making any progress, By eliminating the nonessential we can focus our energy in a direction that really matters.</p>

<p><img src="/images/essentialism.jpg"></p>

<p>It can be scary, but once you get used to it, the feeling of saying no is incredibly freeing.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Freelance Pricing Handbook Launch Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T10:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/05/09/freelance-pricing-handbook-launch-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p>Whenever I finish a product, I like to write a post-mortem. A post-mortem answers a few important questions: What w went well? What went wrong? What could be done better next time? I usually keep these to myself, but this time I wanted to share. Building an email list is something every business should be doing, and I wanted to share the specific techniques I used in order to increase the size of a list 500% in 2 days.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The Goal</h3>

<p>Start building a mailing list, and learn more about effective email marketing in the process. I plan on releasing a book targeted at freelancers hopefully in July, so I would like to start building a list now in order to build trust and have a targeted audience when I am ready to sell.</p>

<h3>The Process</h3>

<p> I signed up for Nathan Barry's <a href="http://www.convertkit.com">ConvertKit</a> Email list software. This includes enrolling in his "ConvertKit Academy" Which is an email course along with a few Google Hangout sessions with Nathan where you get a chance to talk about your personal goals.</p>

<p> Nathan heavily suggested that you have some form on incentive to get people to sign up for your list. He mentioned that you could do a free book, and it could just be a compilation of old writings. He also mentioned setting up a drip marketing course, and ConvertKit comes with a template for that. I looked over some past blog posts and decided to go that route.</p>

<h3>Writing The Book</h3>

<p> Writing the book, and I use the term writing loosely, took about a day. It's a compilation of a few different blog articles I had written, along with some content from a chapter I already had completed for my larger book profit. I drafted up a table of contents, and edited the content together, and wrote about 4 - 5 pages of new content to fill in gaps.  I made the PDF in Pages on the mac.</p>

<p> Then it came to the editing stage. I sent my current list of about 15 people an email announcing the book and asking if anyone wanted a copy. I also did the same of Twitter. I got a lot of amazing responses of people willing to read my book and offer feedback.</p>

<p> After I took a couple hours to edit the content together, I was ready to launch.</p>

<h3>Launching the book</h3>

<p>  Here were the steps I took in order to launch the book</p>

<ul>
<li>I added the ConvertKit form to several blog posts that I thought were relevant to the audience.</li>
<li>Created a <a href="http://glennstovall.com/books/freelance-pricing-handbook/">new landing page</a></li>
<li>Wrote two announcement posts, one on <a href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/">My personal domain</a> and on my <a href="http://concordantsolutions.com/announcing-freelance-pricing-handbook/">company domain</a></li>
<li>Posted links on Facebook, Twitter, Reddit, and LinkedIn</li>
<li>Sent an email out to my original list about the book being released. Also included a P.S. asking them to share on Facebook &amp; Twitter if they felt so inclined</li>
<li>Asked my <a href="http://www.fourathens.com/">local tech community</a> to take a look and help out on social media if they wanted to.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Results</h3>

<p>  By the end of the week I had 84 new subscribers to my list. This was with 323 visitors and a conversion rate of 25.8%</p>

<p>  According to Google Analytics, My site had ~600 visits this week, mostly coming from direct traffic (which is odd, I feel like there are some referrals that don't get tracked properly), then Reddit, then Facebook, in that order.</p>

<h3>What went well</h3>

<p>  Having friends help out on social media seemed like a huge boost. I don't think I've gotten that much traffic from Facebook before. I also had a few people say nice things on Twitter, which I quickly embedded on the landing page as testimonials. The best way to expand your audience is to find ways you can leverage the audience of others.</p>

<p>  Also, writing a book, even when that book is just a PDF "best-of" of your blog, seems really cool to a lot of people. Content in PDF form is just seen as more valuable, and I think having this product out there gives me more credibility.</p>

<h3>What went wrong</h3>

<p>  I found out after the fact the form didn't render correctly on mobile devices, and made it impossible to sign up if you landed on the landing page via a phone. :( That definitely costs me a few conversions. I added a link below that links to a form directly, though perhaps I should find a better way to set up the form so that it renders in a more responsive friendly way.</p>

<h3>What I learned</h3>

<p>  Using incentives to build email lists really does work! My list went from 15 to 100 in a few days. It is also nice to always have something free to offer users in order to provide value for them.</p>

<p>  My next goal is to take these principles and find a way to apply them in a way I can use to target potential clients for my consulting services. I'm not sure what that is going to look like, but I'm sure if I keep writing it'll make sense eventually.</p>

<p>  If you'd like the read the book (and join my mailing list for freelancers), you can get the book below:</p>

<p>  <script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>
If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing The Freelance Pricing Handbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/04/29/announcing-the-freelance-pricing-handbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p> <img class="left" src="/images/freelance_pricing_handbook.png" width="260"></p>

<p> Today I'm proud to announce a new free eBook guide. The book is called the <em>Freelance Pricing Handbook</em>, and it's designed to help freelancers find their perfect rate. The most common question I hear from current and aspiring freelancers is "How much should I charge?" This book sets out to answer this question.</p>

<p> <!-- more --></p>

<p> This book is designed to be a short and easy read to help you understand how to find your perfect price. In addition to help you find your rate, it also includes different ways to package and bill for your services. How you price and position your services has a bigger impact on your bottom line than the amount of skill you have. This book is designed to make sure you aren't undervaluing yourself and are getting paid the rates you deserve.
If you'd like a copy of the book, enter your email address below and I'll email you a copy.</p>

<p>Be sure to let me know what you think!</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to bill Daily or Weekly]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T16:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/02/21/how-to-bill-daily-or-weekly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/calendar.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>When it comes to freelancing, you may think you only have two options when it comes to how you bill your clients: You can bill by the hour, or you can bill by the project. But these aren't your only options, and in many cases they are not your best ones.</p>

<p>Two alternatives to this is billing by the day, or billing by the week. These billing structures are a little more uncommon, but in my experience as a consultant, they have been the most effective and productive. Since these structures are a little bit different, they often require a little bit of explanation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What's In A Day?</h3>

<p>An hour is a definite measure of time. it's 60 minutes. When you bill a client for a hour, they expect to be providing value during those 60 minutes. A day is also a definite measure of time, but if you bill a client for a day they don't expect 24 hours of productivity from you.</p>

<p>You make think that a work day of 8 hours is a more reasonable assumption, but that also isn't the case. Many studies have shown that creative workers are only productive for <a href="http://qz.com/157092/the-case-for-a-six-hour-workday/">5 to 6 hours a day</a>, and that increased hours can in fact lead to decreased productivity. So when it comes to billing by the day, it just means whatever you think a good day's work means to you. It doesn't mean that it has to be all of your time, or that if you bill for a day you can't do any other productive work for another client.</p>

<p>If you have been working in freelancing or consulting and have been keeping track of your hours, you can use that data to determine your day rate.</p>

<h3>Weekly Billing and Deadlines</h3>

<p>Weekly billing tends to work a little bit differently. When you bill by the week, you do so with a goal and a deliverable for the week. Weekly billing is in a way like billing a flat project rate, but you are delivering smaller projects in a smaller time frame.</p>

<p>Weekly billing may seem strange at first, but if you think about it, this is how salaried employees basically work.</p>

<p>With my clients, I set milestones every two weeks, and tell them that I will deliver on those milestones in the time frame. It doesn't matter if I am working 30 hours a week, or 40, or 60, or 5. As long as the results and value are delivered, that is what counts.</p>

<p>The other thing I like about weekly billing is that it makes scheduling my availability much simpler. I can look at my calendar, see that I have worked booked for the next 6 weeks, and have a clear date for when I am available for more work.</p>

<h3>How to Decide on a Pricing Model</h3>

<p>I don't think that any consultant should stick to just one pricing structure, unless you work on a narrow type of project. Different projects and different clients will work better with different billing structures. Here is when I would consider each one:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Hourly Billing:</strong> For jobs where the scope is unknown and flexibility is needed.</li>
<li><strong>Flat Rate Billing:</strong> When the scope of a project can be well defined and the project is small.</li>
<li><strong>Daily Billing:</strong> Works well for one day consulting arrangements, and also for projects that you want to commit to part time (such as 2 - 3 days per week)</li>
<li><strong>Weekly Billing:</strong> My personal favorite. Tends to work well on larger projects, and projects that need flexibility and aren't committed to a hard scope.</li>
</ul>


<p>By thinking about how you price and position your services, you can come up with plans that can make your scheduling better, and help you price your services more aggressively.</p>

<p><strong>EDIT:</strong> Just found this episode of The Freelancer's Show where they discuss <a href="http://www.freelancersshow.com/the-freelancers-show-097-weekly-billing/">weekly billing</a>, Worth a listen if you want to hear more about this subject.</p>

<script src="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531.js?orient=horz"></script>


<p>If the form above doesn't work, you can get it <a href="https://app.convertkit.com/landing_pages/531">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
