<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-28T15:11:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Add a Contact Form to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/07/04/how-to-add-a-contact-form-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-04T11:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/07/04/how-to-add-a-contact-form-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/wufoo.png">
While Octopress is a nice blogging platform, using static generated pages can lead to being unable to have some of the features of other blogging platforms. One of the most common missed features is being able to have a contact us page.  In this tutorial I'll show you how to add a contact form to octopress by using <a href="http://www.wufoo.com">Wufoo</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://www.wufoo.com">Wufoo</a> Is an online form generator that allows you to create and manage forms, and then include them on your pages via JavaScript. Once you've logged in, start a new form, and add the fields you want. For a free account, you can have up to 10 fields, and 3 forms, this should be plenty for a simple contact form. There are also theming options so that the look of the form will better match your site. Once the form is set up, you can also set up notification to an email account and / or SMS, so that you will recieve the messages.</p>

<p>Now that you've created your form, it's time to create our new contact page. Go to the root directory of your Octopress checkout and run the following command:</p>

<pre><code>rake new_page['contact']
</code></pre>

<p>This should create a new page file located at <code>/source/contact/index.markdown</code> . Now in Wufoo, click the 'code' button on your newly created form, then, 'embed form code' and get the JavaScript version. Go to your newly created page and paste the code. I'd also recommend removing the date from the page file and settings comments and sharing both to false.</p>

<p>Once that is done, you'll also probably want to add it to the navigation. You can add pages to the navigation by editing the file located in <code>source/_includes/custom/navigation.html</code> and adding the following line inside of the <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code> tag:</p>

<pre><code>  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/contact"&gt;Contact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>once this is done, all you have to do is regenrate your page files and deploy:</p>

<pre><code>rake generate
rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>and you're done! You can see an exmaple of this turns out on <a href="http://www.glennstovall.com/contact">My Contact Page</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-11T10:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2012/02/11/blogging-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/articles/blog_with_octopress.png" width="260">
If you're reading this, then I've successfully got my octopress blog up and running on Github pages. Why the switch to octopress?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Writing with Octopress</h2>

<p>I love being able to write in emacs using markdown. It feels simple. It feels easy. It feels right.</p>

<h2>Deploying with Github</h2>

<p>This also allows me to host with github pages for free, and use git for deployment. So many headaches just went away for me when it comes to writing.</p>

<h2>Version Control based writing.</h2>

<p>I can take the same approach to writing as I can with coding, publishing fast, fixing mistakes as they are found, and changing content as need be. What you are currently reading isn't the first version of the post, and likely not the last.
I also like the idea of 'open source' writing. If anyone has anything they would like to add or change, feel free to send a pull request to this repo, and I'll take it under consideration.</p>

<h2>The Right Plugins</h2>

<p>There aren't many plugins or themes available for octopress (yet), but it has all the things that are needed to get good content going. That's what I love about it, it is all content based. The default theme is a beautiful starting off point, it's clear and responsive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
