<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: essentialism | Glenn Stovall]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/essentialism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-19T19:36:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Essentialism Through The Ages]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/10/essentialism-through-the-ages/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T08:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/09/10/essentialism-through-the-ages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>The Single Philosophy That Drives Artists, Designers, and Entrepreneurs</h3>

<p><img src="/images/articles/simple_long.jpg"></p>

<p>In design, I've always been a fan of minimalism. Minimalism is a philosophy about boiling things down to their essential elements. It's about having a philosophy of "less but better". Great thinkers from all walks of life have touted the benefits of this kind of approach:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><blockquote><p>Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication</p><footer><strong>Leonard Da Vinci</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Everything should be made as simple as possible, but not simpler.</p><footer><strong>Albert Einstein</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Simplicity is the final achievement. After one has played a vast quantity of notes and more notes, it is simplicity that emerges as the crowning reward of art.</p><footer><strong>Fredric Chopin</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Any intelligent fool can make things bigger, more complex, and more violent. It takes a touch of genius – and a lot of courage – to move in the opposite direction.</p><footer><strong>E.F. Schumacher</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Simple can be harder than complex: You have to work hard to get your thinking clean to make it simple. But it's worth it in the end because once you get there, you can move mountains.</p><footer><strong>Steve Jobs</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>There is a universal truth that drives all of these musicians, artists, and visionaries. They all speak of the beauty and elegance of simplicity in all things. As entrepreneurs, we have the power to design not only our businesses, but our entire lives. However, many people end up working long hours, taking on lots of stress, and doing physical and mental harm to ourselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning To Say No]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T16:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2014/06/02/learning-to-say-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/no.jpeg" width="260"></p>

<p>I just looked in the mirror. I had several more gray hairs in my beard than I had before. I had taken on more client work than I could handle, and had been working long nights and weekends. I knew I was tired and stressed, but it was a real wake up call to see the physical effects of burnout, in addition to the mental. It was at that moment I realized something had to change with how I was managing my business. If you are a freelancer, You have to learn how to say no. Your business, just like a product, is going to be designed. If you don't carefully, mindfully design your own business, then other people will do it for you. And they won't have your best interest at heart.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>The Overworked Freelancer</h3>

<p>It's a common story: The freelancer who is working long hours into the night and on weekends. As freelancers, we should be in control. Why do people who are in charge of their own career and lifestyle decide to do such stressful, harmful things to themselves? Taking on too many responsibilities is not just harmful to ourselves, it's harmful to the quality of our work and our relationships with clients, which is the backbone of our business.</p>

<p>It seems counter intuitive, but by doing so much we are getting so much less done. By taking on <em>less</em> work, we are able to provide a better customer experience and deliver better work.</p>

<h3>Fear of Famine</h3>

<p>The reason that most people say yes to any job, no matter the circumstance, is that they are afraid of where the next one will come from. People will take on a job that is detrimental to their career because they are afraid of not having any client work at all. The issue is that again, the most intuitive solution is not the most effective one. If you spent the same number of hours you work you would spend on a toxic client defining and look for clients you like, you could easily get enough work to sustain yourself, and feel a lot better about your work.</p>

<h3>Saying no to Toxic Clients</h3>

<p>At the end of the day, your clients ARE your business. As such, you need to be selective as to whom you allow into your business. Toxic clients are clients that are a drain on your time, and your resources, while providing little in return. If you have clients like this, I would suggest you fire them immediately. Take the time that you would have spent working with them and start spending it finding better clients. I would also work on setting up a qualification process for your potential clients, so that you can prevent toxic clients from meeting with you in the first place. I send out a standard email with a few questions to potential clients, and if they don't have a good budget, or the project seems like something I would not be interested in, Then I politely decline. If they seem like good clients who are just not a good fir for myself in particular, I will pass them along to another one of my contacts who may be a better fit. By doing this, I have more time to spend on client work that I love.</p>

<h3>How to Say No</h3>

<p>It may feel like saying 'No' is rude in a lot of circumstances, but that, much like the fear of famine, is a fear that can reasoned away. If you don't want to take something on, then you can simply say that you are busy or that you don't have the bandwidth for it. If it is a client, then saying "We wouldn't be a good fit" is a magic phrase that gets you out of most engagements. When dealing with no-longer-potential clients, always take the blame on yourself if you can, it will make your rejection much more palpable.</p>

<p>Some people may resent you, but even more will respect you. It shows that your time is valuable and that you won't just give it up to anyone for any reason. It also allows you to play a little "hard to get" with clients, which makes you seem more valuable in their eyes.</p>

<h3>HELL YES or No</h3>

<p>Derek Sivers summed this up perfectly: You should say <a href="http://sivers.org/hellyeah">"Hell YEAH! or No"</a> to any opportunities you are provided. If something doesn't excite you, if a commitment on your time or energy is a maybe in your mind, then you need to say no. It feels good to say yes to people, but this is what leads to feeling too busy, and too stressed. You have to start saying no more often to escape.</p>

<p>But by saying no to these things, we are enabling ourselves to say "Yes" to things we <strong>really</strong> love. Here is a chart from a new book called <a href="http://gregmckeown.com/essentialism-the-disciplined-pursuit-of-less/">"Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less"</a> That sums this philosophy up perfectly. Instead of sending our energy out in a hundred directions, and feeling like we aren't making any progress, By eliminating the nonessential we can focus our energy in a direction that really matters.</p>

<p><img src="/images/essentialism.jpg"></p>

<p>It can be scary, but once you get used to it, the feeling of saying no is incredibly freeing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
