<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Essentialist Software Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glennstovall.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-29T13:30:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://glennstovall.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glenn Stovall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Get Through Your Inbox in Under 30 Minutes a Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-19T06:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://glennstovall.com/blog/2015/05/19/how-to-get-through-your-inbox-in-under-30-minutes-a-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Your inbox is a trap. It’s a place you can go at any point in the day, spend any amount of time, and it will trick you into thinking this is time well spent. You might have your phone or a desktop application configured to ring with a siren’s call every time someone sends you a message, causing you to pay your inbox a visit and spend more time there.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Email is rarely important and never urgent. I guarantee that right this second there is something you could spend your time doing that would produce more value to your customers, your family, or yourself than piddling around the inbox.</p>

<p>Email is a task that is unimportant and necessary to your business. While most people can’t slay the beast, it can be tamed. You can reduce the amount of noise if your inbox, and put a system in place so that you can get through your inbox effectively, and get on with your life.</p>

<p>I’ve lost entire weekdays to my inbox before, and I realized I needed a change. Here’s how I tackle my emails in just 30 minutes a day. It takes some time to get going but getting a good email system in place will pay dividends for life. You’ll have more time to focus on what’s important, and you’ll impress many a middle manager.</p>

<h2>Step 1: Move Towards Inbox Zero</h2>

<blockquote><p>opens inbox.</p>

<p>sees 3,000 messages.</p>

<p><em>{eye twitches}</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Nothing is going to be allowed to live in our inbox anymore. <strong>Look at your inbox as a list of emails that need to be handled, not as a place to store information.</strong> Getting there can be hard, but once you are there, it is easy to stay there.</p>

<h3>The fastest way to inbox zero:</h3>

<ol>
<li>Open your email program of choice.</li>
<li>Select all messages.</li>
<li>Click ‘archive’.</li>
<li>You’re done!</li>
</ol>


<p>Archiving or deleting all emails of a certain age is declaring <strong>email bankruptcy</strong>. It’s drastic, but you can’t tell me it doesn’t work. It’s dangerous as there are some emails in your inbox right that you probably should read and get a response. If you can’t take this step, then you can archive any email that is 15, 30, or 60 or more days old. That’ll make cleaning the whole inbox easier.</p>

<p>I’ll talk about how to deal with the remaining emails at the end. But first let’s look at two techniques you can use right now to cut down on the noise in your inbox.</p>

<h2>Step 2: Kill Your Notifications</h2>

<blockquote><p><em>gets tagged in a photo on Facebook.</em></p>

<p><em>pop-up on Facebook: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>email inbox: “Someone tagged a photo of you.”</em></p>

<p><em>phone blips: “You’ve got mail!”</em></p>

<p><em><eye twitches></em></p></blockquote>

<p>Are there any apps you check daily? Twitter? Facebook? Productive ones? They have their notification system. Deal with Facebook notifications during a time you have to peruse Facebook. Mark Zuckerberg has taken up enough of your time, Don’t let him have some of your valuable inbox time as well.</p>

<p>Go through your common applications and turn off email notifications. Most of these notifications should have an ‘unsubscribe’ link or links to disable them somewhere in them.</p>

<p>If there are applications that you don’t check regularly, and you need to receive email notifications from them, they are exempt from this process. But if you find yourself deleting a notification for the 12th time, take an extra second, and take the steps necessary to disable it. If it is not easy to disable, you can always set up a filter to delete them automatically for you.</p>

<h2>Step 3: Quarantine Newsletters</h2>

<p>I’m a bit of a newsletter junkie.  While there are plenty of good newsletters filled with valuable information. But that doesn’t mean when I am quickly moving through my inbox I want to take 15 minutes to read an in-depth article, regardless of the value of the content.</p>

<p>The next time you receive a newsletter, you need to ask yourself  a single question:</p>

<h3>Is the newsletter valuable to me?</h3>

<p><strong>If the answer is no, then unsubscribe</strong>. Life is too short to spend it on crummy newsletters.</p>

<p><strong>If the answer is yes, then tag and archive it.</strong> I tag mine “Newsletters to Read” and send them automatically to another folder. When I want to read newsletters, I set aside time for them. If you don’t find yourself willing or able to make time to read newsletters, then they weren’t as valuable as you thought when you subscribed.</p>

<h2>Step 4: Process Your Inbox</h2>

<p>Now it’s time to deal with what’s left. Go through each of your emails from oldest to newest, no skipping. You are going to deal with every single one of them, so there is no point in skipping.</p>

<p>This process will take a little while to get through at first. It gets easier with time, I promise. If you still have hundreds of emails in your inbox, then tackle a few, and come back later.</p>

<p>Once you get to each email, you <em>must</em> decide to do one of the following things with it:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Act on it.</strong> Can this email be dealt with by write a short response? If so, write a short response, hit send and archive the message.</li>
<li><strong>Archive/Delete it.</strong> If the message only needed to read and not acted upon, then read it. If you may need to reference the email later, then archive it. If not, delete it. If you are deleting it, ask yourself if it is a newsletter or notification you can do without, and if so, take the steps to prevent getting it again.</li>
<li><strong>Defer It.</strong> Sometimes emails don’t need immediate attention. If this is the case, You can use Mailbox or Boomerang to ‘snooze’ emails until you can deal with them.</li>
<li><strong>Delegate It.</strong> Delegate your email either to another person, another information repository or another task tracker. For example, I may forward an email to Evernote, or to Asana if it the email mentions a task that I need to come back.</li>
</ul>


<p>Repeat until you are at inbox zero. Now go grab yourself a coffee, you’ve earned it.</p>

<h2>Step 5: Timebox</h2>

<p>Once you have gotten used to the process, you need to set aside time that is exclusively for email and remove email from the other parts of your day. I have two 15-minute periods, at 10am and 4pm.</p>

<p>This strategy is ideal for me as I have to keep a maker’s <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">schedule</a> (long uninterrupted work) instead of a manager’s schedule (small meetings and tasks). If you need more time periods in the day or more time allowed then go for it. I fudge on my schedule when I am in heavy <strong>sales mode</strong>. It’s like beast mode but with less aggression and more cold emailing.</p>

<p>If you used to constantly checking email, it could be hard to drop down to just 30 minutes a day. You can’t go the gym and start with a 300-pound squat, you have to work your way there. Here are some baby steps I recommend to make the transition:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Don’t check email first thing in the morning.</strong> The first hour is a rudder for the rest of your day. Checking email first thing is a great way to throw yourself off course. Focus on spending your first hour being productive, and come back to email afterward.</li>
<li><strong>Turn off phone and desktop notifications.</strong> You want to make checking your email a <em>proactive</em> choice, not a <em>reactive</em> choice. Turn off phone notifications, desktop notifications, and don’t keep a browser tab open in the background.</li>
<li><strong>Don’t check email before bed.</strong> I have never done this and then thought “that was a good decision. I am glad I did that.”</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you’ve done this, you’ve changed your relationship with your inbox. You don’t work on your inbox’s schedule; it works on yours. Email doesn’t control you; you control your email.</p>

<h2>BONUS Step 6: Automation</h2>

<p>These are some additional steps that I use to automate and streamline the time I spend in my email inbox.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Use canned responses.</strong> <a href="http://time.com/12436/quick-gmail-trick-pre-write-email-messages-with-canned-responses/">Canned responses</a> are a Gmail Labs feature. They allow you to save and reuse common responses and messages you send. I use these for common use cases such as follow-ups, initial emails, and even snippets of emails, such as links to my <a href="http://glennstovall.com/case-studies/">portfolio</a> and <a href="http://careers.stackoverflow.com/glennstovall">CV</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Write short responses.</strong> Email is simply a way for people to try and get your time for their agenda. Remember that when you are sending email, you are doing the same, and you should be respecting of other people’s time. Emails should rarely be more than a few sentences.</li>
<li><strong>Take the “<a href="http://unlessiheardifferently.com/">Unless I Hear Otherwise</a>” Approach.</strong> Instead of offering options and opinions, offer a choice with an out. Compare these two emails:</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><em>The slow email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of reasons X, Y, and Z. Which would you prefer?</p>

<p><em>The productive email</em>
I have two options for how I can solve this problem for you, option A and option B. I would recommend option A because of {reasons}.  <strong>Unless I hear otherwise</strong> by close of business, I’ll move forward with option A.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
